Hello, my name is Andre and I've been training deep neural networks for a bit more than a decade and in this lecture
I'd like to show you what neural network training looks like under the hood. So in particular
we are going to start with a blank jubyter notebook and by the end of this lecture
we will define and train in your own that in order to see everything that goes on under the hood and exactly
sort of how that works in an intuitive level. Now specifically what I would like to do is I would like to take you through
building of micrograd. Now micrograd is this library that I released on github about two years ago
but at the time I only uploaded this source code and you'd have to go and buy yourself and really
figure out how it works. So in this lecture I will take you through it step by step and kind of
kind of call it in all the pieces of it. So what's micrograd and why is it interesting?
Micrograd is basically an autograd engine. Autograd is short for automatic gradient and really
what it does is it implements backpropagation. Now backpropagation is this algorithm that allows
you to efficiently evaluate the gradient of some kind of a loss function with respect to the weights
of a neural network and what that allows us to do then is we can iteratively tune the weights of
that neural network to minimize the loss function and therefore improve the accuracy of the network.
So backpropagation would be at the mathematical core of any modern deep neural network library
like say PyTorch or Jax. So the functionality of micrograd is I think best illustrated by an
example. So if we just scroll down here you'll see that micrograd basically allows you to build
out mathematical expressions and here what we are doing is we have an expression that we're
building out where you have two inputs A and B and you'll see that A and B are negative four and two
but we are wrapping those values into this value object that we are going to build out as part of
micrograd. So this value object will wrap the numbers themselves and then we are going to build
out a mathematical expression here where A and B are transformed into C, D and eventually E, F and G
and I'm showing some of the functionality of micrograd and the operations that it supports.
So you can add two value objects, you can multiply them, you can raise them to a constant power,
you can offset by one, negate, squash at zero, square, divide by constant, divide by hit, etc.
And so we're building out an expression graph with these two inputs A and B and we're creating
an output value of G and micrograd will in the background build out this entire mathematical
expression. So it will for example know that C is also a value, C was a result of an addition
operation and the child nodes of C are A and B because the and all maintain pointers to A and B
value objects. So we'll basically know exactly how all of this is laid out. And then not only can
we do what we call the forward pass where we actually look at the value of G of course that's
pretty straightforward. We will access that using the data attribute. And so the output of the forward
pass, the value of G is 24.7, it turns out. But the big deal is that we can also take this G value
object and we can call dot backward. And this will basically initialize backpropagation at the node G.
And what backpropagation is going to do is going to start a G and it's going to go backwards through
that expression graph, and it's going to recursively apply the chain rule from calculus. And what
that allows us to do then is we're going to evaluate basically the derivative of G with respect to
all the internal nodes, like Ed and C, but also with respect to the inputs, a and B. And then we
can actually query this derivative of G with respect to a, for example, that's a dot grad. In
this case, it happens to be 138. And the derivative of G with respect to B, which also happens to be
here, 645. And this derivative we'll see soon is very important information, because it's telling us
how a and B are affecting G through this mathematical expression. So in particular, A dot grad is 138.
So if we slightly nudge a and make it slightly larger, 138 is telling us that G will grow,
and the slope of that growth is going to be 138. And the slope of growth of B is going to be 645.
So that's going to tell us about how G will respond if A and B get tweaked a tiny amount
in a positive direction. Okay. Now, you might be confused about what this expression is that
we built out here. And this expression, by the way, is completely meaningless. I just made it up.
I'm just flexing about the kinds of operations that are supported by micrograd. What we actually
really care about are neural networks. But it turns out that neural networks are just mathematical
expressions, just like this one, but actually slightly bit less crazy even neural networks are
just a mathematical expression. They take the input data as an input, and they take the weights
of a neural network as an input. And some mathematical expression and the output are your predictions
of your neural net or the loss function. We'll see this in a bit. But basically, neural networks
teaches us happen to be a certain class of mathematical expressions. But back propagation is actually
significantly more general. It doesn't actually care about neural networks at all. It only
tells about arbitrary mathematical expressions. And then we happen to use that machinery for
training of neural networks. Now, one more note I would like to make at the stage is that as you
see here, micro grad is a scalar valued autograd engine. So it's working on the level of individual
scalars like negative four and two. And we're taking neural nets and we're breaking them down
all the way to these atoms of individual scalars and all the little pluses and times. And it's just
excessive. And so obviously, you would never be doing any of this in production. It's really just
put down for pedagogical reasons, because it allows us to not have to deal with these
and dimensional tensors that you would use in modern deep neural network library. So this is
really done so that you understand and refactor out back propagation and chain rule and understanding
of your training. And then if you actually want to train bigger networks, you have to be using
these tensors, but none of the math changes. This is done purely for efficiency. We are basically
taking scale value, all the scale values, we're packaging them up into tensors, which are just
arrays of these scalars. And then because we have these large arrays, we're making operations on
those large arrays that allows us to take advantage of the parallelism in a computer. And all those
operations can be done in parallel. And then the whole thing runs faster. But really, none of the
math changes and that's done purely for efficiency. So I don't think that it's pedagogically useful
to be dealing with tensors from scratch. And I think, and that's why fundamentally wrote micro grad,
because you can understand how things work at the fundamental level. And then you can speed it up
later. Okay, so here's the fun part. My claim is that micro grad is what you need to train neural
networks and everything else is just efficiency. So you'd think that micro grad would be a very
complex piece of code. And that turns out to not be the case. So if we just go to micro grad,
and you will see that there's only two files here in micro grad, this is the actual engine.
It doesn't know anything about neural nets. And this is the entire neural nets library on top
of micro grad. So engine and and and pi. So the actual back propagation autograd engine
that gives you the power of neural networks is literally
a hundred lines of code of like very simple Python, which we'll understand by the end of this
lecture. And then and and pi, this neural network library built on top of the autograd engine,
um, is like a joke. It's like we have to define what is a neuron, and then we have to define what
is a layer of neurons. And then we define what is a multilateral perceptron, which is just a
sequence of layers of neurons. And so it's just a total joke. So basically, um, there's a lot of power
that comes from only 150 lines of code. And that's only need to understand to understand neural
network training and everything else is just efficiency. And of course, there's a lot too
efficiency. But fundamentally, that's all that's happening. Okay, so now let's dive right in and
implement micro grad step by step. The first thing I'd like to do is I'd like to make sure
that you have a very good understanding intuitively of what a derivative is and exactly what information
it gives you. So let's start with some basic imports that I copy based in every Jupyter Notebook
always. And let's define the function, scalar valid function f of x as follows. So I just make
this up randomly. I just wanted a scalar value function that takes a single scalar x and returns
a single scalar y. And we can call this function, of course, so we can pass in say 3.0 and get 20
back. Now we can also plot this function to get a sense of its shape. You can tell from the
mathematical expression that this is probably a parabola, it's a quadratic. And so if we just
create a set of, um, sk, scalar values that we can feed in using, for example, a range from
negative five to five and steps up point two five. So this is, so x is just from negative five to five,
not including five in steps of point two five. And we can actually call this function on this
non-py array as well. So we get a set of y's if we call f on x's. And these y's are basically
also applying, um, function on every one of these elements independently. And we can plot this
using matplotlib. So the ulti dot plot x is in y's. And we get a nice parabola. So previously
here we fed in 3.0 somewhere here, and we received 20 back, which is here the y coordinate. So now
I'd like to think through what is the derivative of this function at any single input point x.
Right. So what is the derivative at different points x of this function? Now if you remember
back to your calculus class, you've probably derived derivatives. So we take this mathematical
expression 3x square minus 4x plus five, and you would write out on a piece of paper and you would,
you know, apply the product rule and all the other rules and derive the mathematical expression
of the great derivative of the original function. And then you could plug in different taxes and
see what the derivative is. We're not going to actually do that because no one in neural networks
actually writes out the expression for neural net. It would be a massive expression. It would be,
you know, thousands since thousands of terms. No one actually derives the derivative, of course.
And so we're not going to take this kind of symbolic approach. Instead, what I'd like to do is I'd
like to look at the definition of derivative and just make sure that we really understand
what derivative is measuring, what is telling you about the function. And so if we just look up
we see that. Okay. So this is not a very good definition of derivative. This is a definition
of what it means to be differentiable. But if you remember from your calculus, it is the limit
as h goes to zero of f of x plus h minus f of x over h. So basically what it's saying is if you
slightly bump up, you're at some point x that you're interested in, or a, and if you slightly
bump up, you know, you slightly increase it by small number h. How does the function respond with
what sensitivity does it respond? What is the slope at that point? Does the function go up or does
it go down and by how much? And that's the slope of that function, the slope of that response
at that point. And so we can basically evaluate the derivative here numerically by taking a very
small h. Of course, the definition would ask us to take h to zero, or just going to pick a very
small h 0.001. And let's say we're interested in 0.3.0. So we can look at f of x, of course, as 20.
And now f of x plus h. So if we slightly nudge x in a positive direction, how is the function
going to respond? And just looking at this, do you expect f of x plus h to be slightly greater?
Than 20? Or do you expect to be slightly lower than 20? And since this three is here, and this is 20,
if we slightly go positively, the function will respond positively. So you'd expect this to be
slightly greater than 20. And by how much is telling you the sort of the strength of that slope,
right, the size of that slope? So f of x plus h, f of x, this is how much the function responded
in a positive direction. And we have to normalize by the run. So we have the rise over run to get
the slope. So this, of course, is just a numerical approximation of the slope, because we have to
make a very, very small to converge to the exact amount. Now, if I'm doing too many zeros,
at some point, I'm going to get an incorrect answer, because we're using floating point arithmetic.
And the representations of all these numbers in computer memory is finite. And at some point,
we get into trouble. So we can converge towards the right answer with this approach.
But basically, at three, the slope is 14. And you can see that by taking 3x squared minus 4x plus
5, and differentiating it in our head. So 3x squared would be 6x minus 4. And then we plug in x equals
3. So that's 18 minus 4 is 14. So this is correct. So that's a three. Now, how about the slope at
say, negative three? Would you expect, what would you expect for the slope? Now, telling the exact
value is really hard. But what is the sign of that slope? So at negative three, if we slightly go in
the positive direction at x, the function would actually go down. And so that tells you that the
slope would be negative. So we'll get a slight number below 20. And so if we take the slope,
we expect something negative, negative 22. Okay. And at some point here, of course, the slope would be
zero. Now, for this specific function, I looked it up previously, and it's at point two over three.
So at roughly two over three, that's somewhere here, this derivative would be zero. So basically,
at that precise point, yeah, at that precise point, if we nudge in a positive direction,
the function doesn't respond, this stays the same almost. And so that's why the slope is zero.
Okay, now let's look at a bit more complex case. So we're going to start, you know,
complexifying a bit. So now we have a function here, with output variable d, there is a function
of three scalar inputs, a B and C. So a B and C are some specific values, three inputs into our
expression graph, and a single output d. And so if we just print d, we get four. And now what I
like to do is I'd like to again look at the derivatives of d with respect to a B and C.
And think through, again, just the intuition of what this derivative is telling us. So in order
to evaluate this derivative, we're going to get a bit hacky here, we're going to again have a very
small value of H. And then we're gonna fix the inputs at some values that we're interested in.
So these are the, this is the point ABC, at which we're going to be evaluating the
derivative of D with respect to all a B and C at that point. So there are the inputs. And now we
have D one is that expression. And then we're going to, for example, look at the derivative of
D with respect to a. So we'll say a and we'll bump it by H. And then we'll get D two to be the
exact same function. And now we're going to print, you know, funk, F one, D one is D one,
D two is D two, and print slope. So the derivative or slope here will be,
of course, D two minus D one divided H. So D two minus D one is how much the function
increased when we bumped the specific input that we're interested in by a tiny amount. And
this is the normalized by H to get the slope. So, yeah. So this, so I just from this, we're going to
print D one, which we know is four. Now D two will be bumped A will be bumped by H.
So let's just think through a little bit, what D two will be printed out here. In particular,
D one will be four, will D two be a number slightly greater than four or slightly lower than four.
And it's going to tell us the the sign of the derivative. So we're bumping A by H.
B is minus three CS 10. So you can just intuitively think through this derivative and what it's doing.
A will be slightly more positive. And but B is a negative number. So if A is slightly more positive,
because B is negative three, we're actually going to be adding less to D. So you'd actually expect
that the value of the function will go down. So let's just see this. Yeah. And so we went from four
to 3.9996. And that tells you that the slope will be negative. And then
will be negative number, because we went down. And then the exact number of slope will be
exact number of slope is negative three. And you can also convince yourself that negative three is
the right answer mathematically and analytically, because if you have eight times B plus C and you
are, you know, you have calculus, then differentiating eight times B plus C with respect to A gives you
just B. And indeed, the value of B is negative three, which is the derivative that we have.
So you can tell that that's correct. So now if we do this with B. So if we bump B by a little bit
in a positive direction, we'd get different slopes. So what is the influence of B on the output D?
So if we bump B by tiny amount in a positive direction, then because A is positive,
we'll be adding more to D. Right. So, and now what is the, what is the sensitivity? What is the
slope of that addition? And it might not surprise you that this should be two. And why is it two?
Because D of D by DB, the fraction with respect to B would be would give us A and the value of A is
two. So that's also working well. And then if C gets bumped a tiny amount in H by H, then of
course, H times B is unaffected. And now C becomes slightly bit higher. What does that do to the
function? It makes it slightly bit higher, because we're simply adding C. And it makes
it slightly bit higher by the exact same amount that we added to C. And so that tells you that the
slope is one. That will be the, the rate at which D will increase as we scale C. Okay, so we now
have some intuitive sense of what this derivative is telling you about the function. And we'd like
to move to neural networks. Now, as I mentioned, neural networks will be pretty massive expressions,
mathematical expressions. So we need some data structures that maintain these expressions. And
that's what we're going to start to build out now. So we're going to build out this value object
that I showed you in the read me page of micro grad. So let me copy paste a skeleton of the first
very simple value object. So class value takes a single scalar value that it wraps and keeps track
of. And that's it. So we can, for example, do value of 2.0, and then we can get, we can look at its
content. And Python will internally use the wrapper function to return this string. So this is a
value object with data equals two that we're creating here. Now we'd like to do is like, we'd
like to be able to have not just like two values, but we'd like to do a wealthy, right, we'd like to
add them. So currently, you'd get an error because Python doesn't know how to add two value objects.
So we have to tell it. So here's addition. So you have to basically use these special double
underscore methods in Python to define these operators for these objects. So if we call
the, if we use this plus operator, Python will internally call a dot add of B. That's what will
happen internally. And so B will be the other, and self will be a. And so we see that what we're
going to return is a new value object. And it's just, is going to be wrapping the plus of their
data. But remember now, because data is the actual like numbered Python number. So this operator
here is just the typical floating point plus addition now, it's not an addition of value objects.
And we'll return a new value. So now a plus B should work. And it should print value of
negative one, because that's two plus minus three. There we go. Okay, let's now implement
multiply, just so we can recreate this expression here. So multiply, I think it won't surprise you,
will be fairly similar. So instead of add, we're going to be using mall. And then here, of course,
we want to do tons. And so now we can create a C value object, which will be 10.0. And now we
should be able to do a times B. Well, let's just do a times B first. That's value of negative six now.
And by the way, I skipped over this a little bit, suppose that I didn't have the wrapper
function here, then it's just that you'll get some kind of an ugly expression. So what
wrapper is doing is it's providing us a way to print out like a nicer looking expression in Python.
So we don't just have something cryptic, we actually are, you know, it's value of negative six. So this
gives us a times. And then this we should now be able to add C to it, because we've defined and
told the Python how to do mall and add. And so this will call, this will basically be equivalent to a
dot mall of B. And then this new value object will be dot add of C. And so let's see if that work.
Yep. So that worked well. That gave us four, which is what we expect from before.
And I believe you can just call the manually as well. There we go. So
Yeah. Okay. So now what we are missing is the connective tissue of this expression. As I mentioned,
we want to keep these expression graphs. So we need to know and keep pointers about what values
produce what other values. So here, for example, we are going to introduce a new variable, which
will call children. And by default, it will be an empty tuple. And then we're actually going to keep
a slightly different variable in the class, which we'll call underscore private, which will be the
set of children. This is how I did it in the original micro grad looking at my code here.
I can't remember exactly the reason I believe it was efficiency. But this underscore children
will be a tuple for convenience. But then when we actually maintain it in the class, it will be
just this set. I believe for efficiency. So now when we are creating a value like this with a
constructor, children will be empty and prep will be the empty set. But when we are creating a value
through addition or multiplication, we're going to feed in the children of this value,
which in this case is self another. So those are the children here.
So now we can do D dot prep. And we'll see that the children of the we now know are this value of
negative six and value of 10. And this, of course, is the value resulting from a times B and the C
value, which is 10. Now the last piece of information we don't know. So we know that the children of
every single value, but we don't know what operation created this value. So we need one more element
here. Let's call it underscore pop. And by default, this is the empty set for leaves. And then we'll
just maintain it here. And now the operation will be just a simple string. And in the case of addition,
it's plus in the case of multiplication is times. So now we not just have D dot prep, we also have
a D dot op. And we know that D was produced by an addition of those two values. And so now we have
the full mathematical expression. And we're building out this data structure. And we know exactly how
each value came to be by word expression and from what other values. Now, because these expressions
are about to get quite a bit larger, we'd like a way to nicely visualize these expressions that
we're building out. So for that, I'm going to copy paste a bunch of slightly scary code that's
going to visualize this, these expression graphs for us. So here's the code and I'll explain it in
a bit. But first, let me just show you what this code does. Basically, what it does is it creates
a new function draw dot that we can call on some root node. And then it's going to visualize it.
So if we call draw dot on D, which is this final value here, that is a times B plus C.
It creates something like this. So this is D. And you see that this is a times B, creating an
iterative value plus C gives us the output node D. So that's draw out of D. And I'm not going to go
through this in complete detail. You can take a look at graphis and its API. Graphis is a open
source graph visualization software. And what we're doing here is we're building out this graph in
the graph is API. And you can basically see that trace is this helper function that enumerates all
the nodes and edges in the graph. So that just builds a set of all the nodes and edges. And then
we iterate for all the nodes and we create special node objects for them in using dot node. And
then we also create edges using dot dot edge. And the only thing that's like slightly tricky here
is you'll notice that I basically add these fake nodes, which are these operation nodes. So for
example, this node here is just like a plus node. And I create these special op nodes here. And I
connect them accordingly. So these nodes, of course, are not actual nodes in the original graph.
They're not actually a value object. The only value objects here are the things in squares.
Those are actual value objects or representations thereof. And these op nodes are just created in
this draw dot routine so that it looks nice. Let's also add labels to these graphs just so we know
what variables are where. So let's create a special underscore label. Or let's just do label
equals empty by default, and save it to each node. And then here, we're going to do label is a
label is the label is C. And then let's create a special equals a times B.
And label will be. It's kind of naughty. And he will be a plus C. And D dot label will be
D. Okay, so nothing really changes. I just added this new function, new variable. And then here,
when we are printing this, I'm going to print the label here. So this will be a percent S bar.
And this will be end up label. And so now we have the label on the left here. So it says a b
creating E and then E plus C creates D, just like we have it here. And finally, let's make this
expression just one layer deeper. So D will not be the final output node. Instead, after D,
we are going to create a new value object called f. We're gonna start running out of variable soon.
f will be negative 2.0. And it's label. Of course, just the f. And then L capital L will be the
output of our graph. And L will be D times f. Okay, so L will be negative 8 is the output.
So now we don't just draw a D, D draw L. Okay. And somehow the label of L is undefined. Oops.
All that label has to be explicitly given to it. There we go. So L is the output. So let's quickly
recap what we've done so far. We are able to build out mathematical expressions using only plus
in times so far. They are scalar valued along the way. And we can do this forward pass and build
out a mathematical expression. So we have multiple inputs here, a B C and f going into a mathematical
expression that produces a single output L. And this here is just watching the forward pass. So the
output of the forward pass is negative 8. That's the value. Now what we'd like to do next is we
like to run back propagation. And in back propagation, we are going to start here at the end. And we're
going to reverse and calculate the gradient along along all these intermediate values. And really
what we're computing for every single value here, we're going to compute the derivative of that
node with respect to L. So the derivative of L with respect to L is just one. And then we're
going to derive what is the derivative of L with respect to f with respect to D with respect to C
with respect to E with respect to B and with respect to A. And in neural network setting,
you'd be very interested in the derivative of basically this loss function L with respect to
the weights of a neural network. And here, of course, we have just these variables A, B, C and F. But
some of these will eventually represent the weights of a neural net. And so we'll need to know how
those weights are impacting the loss function. So we'll be interested basically in the derivative
of the output with respect to some of its leaf nodes. And those leaf nodes will be the weights of
the neural net. And the other leaf nodes, of course, will be the data itself. But usually we will not
want or use the derivative of the loss function with respect to data, because the data is fixed.
But the weights will be iterated on using the gradient information. So next, we are going to
create a variable inside the value class that maintains the derivative of L with respect to that
value. And we will call this variable grad. So there's a data, and there's a self that grad.
And initially, it will be zero. And remember that zero is basically means no effect. So at
initialization, we're assuming that every value does not impact does not affect the output.
Right, because if the gradient zero, that means that changing this variable is not changing the
loss function. So by default, we assume that the gradient is zero. And then
now that we have grad, and it's 0.0,
we are going to be able to visualize it here after data. So here grad is 0.4f.
And this will be in the graph. And now we are going to be showing both the data and the grad
initialize that zero. And we are just about getting ready to calculate the back propagation.
And of course, this grad again, as I mentioned, is representing the derivative of the output.
In this case, L with respect to this value. So with respect to, so this is the derivative
of L with respect to f, respect to D, and so on. So let's now fill in those gradients and
actually do back propagation manually. So let's start filling in these gradients and start all
the way at the end, as I mentioned here. First, we are interested to fill in this gradient here.
So what is the derivative of L with respect to L? In other words, if I change L by a tiny amount
H, how much does L change? It changes by H. So it's proportional, and therefore,
there will be one. We can of course measure these or estimate these numerical gradients
numerically, just like we've seen before. So if I take this expression, and I create a def LLL
function here, and let this here. Now, the reason I'm creating a gating function LLL here is because
I don't want to pollute or mess up the global scope here. This is just kind of like a little
staging area. And as you know, in Python, all of these will be local variables to this function.
So I'm not changing any of the global scope here. So here, L1 will be L. And then copy-facing this
expression, we're going to add a small amount H in, for example, A, right? And this would be
measuring the derivative of L with respect to A. So here, this will be L2. And then we want to
print that derivative. So print L2 minus L1, which is how much L changed, and then normalize it by
H. So this is the rise over run. And we have to be careful because L is a value node. So we
actually want its data. So that these are floats divided by H. And this should print the derivative
of L with respect to A, because A is the one that we bumped a little bit by H. So what is the
derivative of L with respect to A? It's six. Okay. And obviously, if we change L by H,
then that would be here effectively. This looks really awkward, but changing L by H,
you see the derivative here is one. That's kind of like the base case of what we are doing here.
So basically, we can come up here and we can manually set L dot grad to one. This is our manual
backpropagation. L dot grad is one. And let's redraw. And we'll see that we filled in grad is one
for L. We're now going to continue to pack propagation. So let's here look at the derivatives of L with
respect to D and F. Let's do a D first. So what we are interested in, if I create a markdown on here,
is we'd like to know basically, we have that L is D times F. And we'd like to know what is D
L by D D. What is that? And if you know you're a calculus, L is D times F. So what is D L by D D,
it would be F. And if you don't believe me, we can also just derive it because the proof would
be fairly straightforward. We go to the definition of the derivative, which is F of X plus H minus F
of X divided H as a limit, limit of H goes to zero of this kind of expression. So when we have L is
D times F, then increasing D by H would give us the output of D plus H times F. That's basically
F of X plus H, right? Minus D times F. And then divide H. And symbolically expanding out here,
we would have basically D times F plus H times F minus D times F divided H. And then you see how
the D of minus D of cancels, so you're left with H times F divided H, which is F. So in the limit,
this H goes to zero of, you know, derivative definition, we just get F in a case of D times F.
So symmetrically, D L by D F will just be D. So what we have is that F dot grad, we see now,
it's just the value of D, which is four. And we see that D dot grad is just the value of F.
And so the value of F is negative two. So we'll set those manually.
Let me erase this markdown node, and then let's redraw what we have.
Okay, and let's just make sure that these were correct. So we seem to think that D L by D D is
negative two. So let's double check. Let me erase this plus H from before. And now we want
the derivative with respect to F. So let's just come here when I create F, and let's do a plus
H here. And this should print a derivative of L with respect to F. So we expect to see four.
Yeah, and this is four up to floating point funkiness. And then D L by D D should be F,
which is negative two. grad is negative two. So if we again come here and we change D,
D dot data plus equals H right here. So we expect, so we've added a little H, and then we see how
L changed, and we expect to print negative two. There we go. So we've numerically verified,
what we're doing here is kind of like an inline gradient check. Gradient check is when we are
driving this like back propagation and getting the derivative with respect to all the intermediate
results. And then numerical gradient is just, you know, estimating it using small step size.
Now we're getting to the crux back propagation. So this will be the most important node to understand,
because if you understand the gradient for this node, you understand all of back propagation and
all training of neural nets, basically. So we need to derive D L by B C. In other words,
the derivative L with respect to C, because we've computed all these other gradients already.
Now we're coming here and we're continuing the back propagation manually. So we want D L by D C,
and then we'll also derive D L by D E. Now here's the problem. How do we derive D L by D C?
We actually know the derivative L with respect to D. So we know how L is sensitive to D,
but how is L sensitive to C? So if we wiggle C, how does that impact L through D?
So we know D L by D C. And we also here know how C impacts D. And so just very intuitively,
if you know the impact that C is having on D, and the impact that D is having on L,
then you should be able to somehow put that information together to figure out how C impacts
L. And indeed, this is what we can actually do. So in particular, we know just concentrating on D
first. Let's look at how what is the derivative basically of D with respect to C. So in other
words, what is D D by D C? So here we know that D is C times C plus E E. That's what we know.
And now we're interested in D D by D C. If you just know your calculus again, and you remember
that the differentiating C plus E with respect to C, you know that that gives you 1 to 0.
And we can also go back to the basics and derive this. Because again, we can go to our f of x plus
H minus f of x divided by h. That's the definition of a derivative as h goes to 0.
And so here, focusing on C and its effect on D, we can basically do the f of x plus h will be C
is incremented by h plus E. That's the first evaluation of our function, minus C plus E.
And then divide h. And so what is this? Just expanding this out, this will be C plus H plus E
minus C minus E divided h. And then you see here how C minus E cancels E minus E cancels
were left with h over h, which is 1.0. And so my symmetry also, D D by D E will be 1.0 as well.
So basically the derivative of a sum expression is very simple. And this is the local derivative.
So I call this the local derivative because we have the final output value all the way at the
end of this graph. And we're now like a small node here. And this is a little plus node. And
it, the little plus node, doesn't know anything about the rest of the graph that it's embedded in.
All it knows is that it did it plus. It took a C and an E, added them and created a D.
And this plus node also knows the local influence of C on D, or rather the derivative of D with
respect to C. And it also knows the derivative of D with respect to E. But that's not what we
want. That's just a local derivative. What we actually want is D L by D C. And L could, L is
here just one step away. But in a general case, this little plus node could be embedded in a
massive graph. So again, we know how L impacts D. And now we know how C and E impact D.
How do we put that information together to arrive D L by D C? And the answer, of course, is the chain
rule in calculus. And so I pulled up a chain rule here from Kepedia. And I'm going to go through
this very briefly. So chain rule, we could be there sometimes can be very confusing and calculus can
be very confusing. Like, this is the way I learned chain rule and was very confusing. Like what is
happening? It's just complicated. So I like this expression much better. If a variable z depends
on a variable y, which itself depends on a variable x, then z depends on x as well, obviously,
through the intermediate variable y. And in this case, the chain rule is expressed as, if you want
DZ by DX, then you take the DZ by dy and you multiply it by dy by DX. So the chain rule fundamentally
is telling you how we chain these derivatives together correctly. So to differentiate through a
function composition, we have to apply a multiplication of those derivatives. So that's really what
chain rule is telling us. And there's a nice little intuitive explanation here, which I also think
is kind of cute. The chain rule says that knowing the instantaneous rate of change of z with respect
to y and y relative to x allows one to calculate the instantaneous rate of change of z relative to
x as a product of those two rates of change, simply the product of those two. So here's a good one.
If a car travels twice as fast as a bicycle and the bicycle is four times as fast as walking men,
then the car travels two times four, eight times as fast as a man. And so this makes it very clear
that the correct thing to do sort of is to multiply. So cars twice as fast as bicycle and
bicycle is four times as fast as men. So the car will be eight times as fast as the men.
And so we can take these intermediate rates of change, if you will, and multiply them together.
And that justifies the chain rule intuitively. So have a look at chain rule about here.
Really what it means for us is there's a very simple recipe for deriving what we want, which is dL
by dC. And what we have so far is we know one and we know what is the impact of d on L. So we know
dL by dD, the derivative of L with respect to dD, we know that that's negative two. And now because
of this local reasoning that we've done here, we know dD by dC. So how does C impact D? And in
particular, this is a plus node. So the local derivative is simply 1.0. It's very simple.
And so the chain rule tells us that dL by dC, going through this intermediate variable,
will just be simply dL by dD times dD by dC. That's chain rule. So this is identical to what's happening
here, except Z is our L, Y is our D, and X is our C. So we literally just have to multiply these.
And because these local derivatives like dD by dC are just one, we basically just copy over
dL by dD because this is just times one. So what is it? So because dL by dD is negative two,
what is dL by dC? Well, it's the local gradient 1.0 times dL by dD, which is negative two.
So literally what a plus node does, you can look at it that way, is it literally just routes the
gradient because the plus nodes local derivatives are just one. And so in the chain rule, one times
dL by dD is just dL by dD. And so that derivative just gets routed to both C and to E in the
case. So basically, we have that E dot grad, or let's start with C, since that's the one we looked at,
is negative two times one negative two. And in the same way, my symmetry, E dot grad, will be
negative two. Let's decline. So we can set those. We can redraw. And you see how we just assign
negative to negative two. So this back propagating signal, which is carrying the information of
like, what is the derivative of L with respect to all the intermediate nodes? We can imagine it
almost like flowing backwards through the graph. And a plus node will simply distribute the derivative
to all the leaf nodes, sorry, to all the children nodes of it. So this is the claim. And now let's
verify it. So let me remove the plus H here from before. And now instead, what we're going to do
is we want to incurrence C. So C data will be incremented by H. And when I run this, we expect
to see negative two, negative two. And then of course, for E. So E data plus equals H. And we
expect to see negatives. Simple. So those are the derivatives of these internal nodes. And now we're
going to recurse our way backwards again. And we're again going to apply the chain rule.
So here we go, our second application of chain rule. And we will apply it all the way through the
graph, which just happened to only have one more node remaining. We have that d L by d e,
as we have just calculated, is negative two. So we know that. So we know the derivative of L
with respect to E. And now we want d L by d A, right? And the chain rule is telling us that that's just
d L by d e, negative two, times the local gradient. So what is the local gradient? Basically d E by
d A, we have to look at that. So I'm a little times node inside a massive graph. And I only
know that I did a times B and I produced an E. So now what is d E by d A and d E by d B? That's
the only thing that I sort of know about. That's my local gradient. So because we have that E is
A times B, we're asking what is d E by d A? And of course, we just did that here. We had times,
so I'm not going to redrive it. But if you want to differentiate this with respect to A, you'll
just get B, right? The value of B, which in this case is negative 3.0. So basically we have that d L
by d A. Well, let me just do it right here. We have that A dot grad and we are applying chain
rule here is d L by d E, which we see here is negative two times what is d E by d A? It's the
value of B, which is negative three. That's it. And then we have B dot grad is again d L by d E,
which is negative two, just the same way, times what is d E by d D B is the value of A, which is
two dot two point zero, as the value of A. So these are our claimed derivatives. Let's redraw.
And we see here that A dot grad turns out to be six because that is negative two times negative
three. And B dot grad is negative four times sorry is negative two times two, which is negative four.
So those are our claims. Let's delete this and let's verify them. We have A here, A dot data plus
equals H. So the claim is that A dot grad is six. Let's verify six. And we have B data data plus
equals H. So nudging B by H and looking at what happens, we claim it's negative four and indeed
it's negative four plus minus again float oddness. And that's it. This, that was the manual back
propagation all the way from here to all the leaf nodes. And I'm done at piece by piece. And really
all we've done is as you saw, we iterated through all the nodes one by one and locally applied the
chain rule. We always know what is the derivative of L with respect to this little output. And then
we look at how this output was produced. This output was produced through some operation. And we have
the pointers to the children nodes of this operation. And so in this little operation, we know what
the local derivatives are. And we just multiply them onto the derivative always. So we just go
through and recursively multiply on the local derivatives. And that's what back propagation is,
is just a recursive application of chain rule backwards through the computation graph.
Let's see this power in action, just very briefly. What we're going to do is we're going to
notch our inputs to try to make L go up. So in particular, what we're doing is we want a data
data, we're going to change it. And if you want L to go up, that means we just have to go in the
direction of the gradient. So a should increase in the direction of gradient, by like some small
step amount, this is the step size. And we don't just want this for being, but also for being
also for C, also for F, those are leaf nodes, which we usually have control over. And if we
notch in direction of the gradient, we expect a positive influence on L. So we expect L to go up
positively. So it should become less negative. It should go up to say negative, you know,
six or something like that. It's hard to tell exactly. And we'd have to rerun the forward pass.
So let me just do that here. This would be the forward pass. F would be unchanged. This is
effectively the forward pass. And now if we print L dot data, we expect, because we nudged all the
values or the inputs in the direction of gradient, we expected a less negative L, we expected to go up.
So maybe it's negative six or so, let's see what happens. Okay, negative seven. And this is
basically one step of an optimization that will end up running. And really, this gradient just
gave us some power because we know how to influence the final outcome. And this will be extremely
useful for training. You know, that's as well as CMC. So now I would like to do one more
example of manual backpropagation using a bit more complex and useful example. We are going to
back propagate through a neuron. So we want to eventually build out neural networks. And in the
simplest case, these are multilateral perceptrons, as they're called. So this is a two layer neural
nut. And it's got these hidden layers made up of neurons. And these neurons are fully connected
to each other. Now biologically, neurons are very complicated devices. But we have very simple
mathematical models of them. And so this is a very simple mathematical model of a neuron.
You have some inputs, axis. And then you have these synapses that have weights on them. So
the W's are weights. And then the synapse interacts with the input to this neuron,
multiplicatively. So what flows to the cell body of this neuron is W times X. But there's
multiple inputs. So there's many W times X is flowing to the cell body. The cell body then has
also like some bias. So this is kind of like the inert innate sort of trigger happiness of this
neuron. So this bias can make it a bit more trigger happy or a bit less trigger happy,
regardless of the input. But basically, we're taking all the W times X of all the inputs,
adding the bias. And then we take it through an activation function. And this activation
function is usually some kind of a squashing function, like a sigmoid or 10 H or something
like that. So as an example, we're going to use the 10 H in this example. NumPy has a Np dot 10 H.
So we can call it on a range, and we can plot it. Those are the 10 H function. And you see that
the inputs as they come in, get squashed on the white coordinate here. So right at zero,
we're going to get exactly zero. And then as you go more positive in the input,
then you'll see that the function will only go up to one and then plateau out. And so if you pass
in very positive inputs, we're going to cap it smoothly at one. And on the negative side,
we're going to cap it smoothly to negative one. So that's 10 H. And that's the squashing function
or an activation function. And what comes out of this neuron is just the activation function applied
to the dot product of the weights and the inputs. So let's write one out. I'm going to copy-based
because I don't want to type too much. But okay, so here we have the inputs x1, x2. So this is a
two dimensional neuron. So two inputs are going to come in. These are thought out as the weights of
this neuron, weights w1, w2. And these weights again are the synaptic strengths for each input.
And this is the bias of the neuron B. And now what we want to do is according to this model,
we need to multiply x1 times w1 and x2 times w2. And then we need to add bias on top of it.
And it gets a little messy here, but all we are trying to do is x1, w1 plus x2, w2 plus B.
And these are multiply here. Except I'm doing it in small steps so that we actually have pointers
to all these intermediate nodes. So we have x1, w1 variable, x times x2, w2 variable, and I'm also
labeling them. So n is now the cell body raw activation without the activation function from now.
And this should be enough to basically plot it. So draw a dot of n
gives us x1 times w1, x2 times w2 being added. And the bias gets added on top of this. And this
n is this sum. So we're now going to take it through an activation function. And let's say we
use the 10H so that we produce the output. So what we'd like to do here is we'd like to do the output
and I'll call it o is n dot 10H. Okay, but we haven't yet written the 10H. Now the reason that
we need to implement another 10H function here is that 10H is a hyperbolic function. And we've only
so far implemented plus and the times and you can't make a 10H out of just pluses and times.
You also need exponentiation. So 10H is this kind of a formula here. You can use either one of these.
And you see that there's exponentiation involved, which we have not implemented yet for our low value
node here. So we're not going to be able to produce 10H yet and we have to go back up and
implement something like it. Now one option here is we could actually implement exponentiation.
And we could return the x of a value instead of a 10H of a value. Because if we had x,
then we have everything else that we need. So because we know how to add and we know how to
we know how to add and we know how to multiply. So we'd be able to create 10H if we knew how to
exp. But for the purposes of this example, I specifically wanted to show you that we don't
necessarily need to have the most atomic pieces in this value object. We can actually like create
functions at arbitrary points of abstraction. They can be complicated functions, but they can be
also very, very simple functions like a plus. And it's totally up to us. The only thing that matters
is that we know how to differentiate through any one function. So we take some inputs and we make
an output. The only thing that matters can be arbitrarily complex function as long as you know
how to create the local derivative. If you know the local derivative of how the inputs impact the
output, then that's all you need. So we're going to cluster up all of this expression. And we're
not going to break it down to its atomic pieces. We're just going to directly implement 10H. So
let's do that. Death 10H. And then out will be a value of, and we need this expression here. So
let me actually copy paste. Let's grab N, which is a cell data. And then this, I believe, is the
10H. Math dot X of two, you know, n minus one over two n plus one. Maybe I can call this X.
Just so that it matches exactly. Okay. And now this will be T.
And children of this node, they're just one child. And I'm wrapping it in a tuple. So this is a
tuple of one object, just self. And here the name of this operation will be 10H. And we're going to
return that. Okay. So now values should be implementing 10H. And now we can scroll all the
way down here. And we can actually do n dot 10H. And that's going to return the 10H output of N.
And now we should be able to draw that of Oh, not of N. So let's see how that worked.
There we go. N went through 10H to produce this up. So now 10H is a sort of our little
micrograt supported node here as an operation. And as long as we know derivative of 10H,
then we'll be able to back propagate through it. Now let's see this 10H in action. Currently,
it's not squashing too much because the input to it is pretty low. So the bias was increased
to say eight. Then we'll see that what's flowing into the 10H now is two. And 10H is squashing
it to 0.96. So we're already hitting the tail of this 10H. And it will sort of smoothly go up to one
and then plateau out over there. Okay, so I'm going to do something slightly strange. I'm going to
change this bias from eight to this number, 6.88, etc. And I'm going to do this for specific reasons
because we're about to start back propagation. And I want to make sure that our numbers come
out nice. They're not like very crazy numbers. They're nice numbers that we can sort of understand
in our head. Let me also add those label. Oh, a short four output here. So that's the R. Okay, so
pointing eight flows into 10H comes out point seven. So now we're going to do back propagation.
And we're going to fill in all the gradients. So what is the derivative of with respect to
all the inputs here? And of course, in a typical neural network setting, what we really care about
the most is the derivative of these neurons on the weights specifically, the W2 and W1,
because those are the weights that we're going to be changing part of the optimization. And the
other thing that we have to remember is here we have only a single neuron, but in the neural
nut, you typically have many neurons and they're connected. So this is only like a one small neuron,
a piece of a much bigger puzzle. And eventually there's a loss function that sort of measures the
accuracy of the neural nut. And we're back propagating with respect to that accuracy and trying to
increase it. So let's start off by propagation here and what is the derivative of O with respect to
O, the base case sort of we know always is that the gradient is just 1.0. So let me fill it in.
And then let me split out the drawing function here.
And then here cell clear this output here. Okay. So now when we draw O, we'll see that
or that grad is one. So now we're going to back propagate through the 10H. So to back propagate
through 10H, we need to know the local derivative of 10H. So if we have that O is 10H of N,
then what is D O by D N? Now what you could do is you could come here and you could take this
expression and you could do your calculus derivative taking. And that would work. But we can also just
scroll down with the PDI here into a section that hopefully tells us that derivative D by
D X of 10H of X is N of E's. I like this one, 1 minus 10H square of X. So this is 1 minus 10H
of X squared. So basically what this is saying is that D O by D N is 1 minus 10H of N squared.
And we already have 10H of N. It's just O. So it's 1 minus O squared. So O is the output here.
So the output is this number. O dot data is this number. And then what this is saying is that
D O by D N is 1 minus this squared. So 1 minus O dot data squared is 0.5 conveniently. So the
local derivative of this 10H operation here is 0.5. And so that would be D O by D N. So we can fill
in that in that grad is 0.5. We'll just fill it in. So this is exactly 0.5. 1/2. So now we're
going to continue the back propagation. This is 0.5 and this is a plus node. So how is back
prop going to what is back prop going to do here? And if you remember our previous example,
a plus is just a distributor of gradient. So this gradient will simply flow to both of these
equally. And that's because the local derivative of this operation is one for every one of its
nodes. So one times 0.5 is 0.5. So therefore we know that this node here, which we called this,
its grad is just 0.5. And we know that B dot grad is also 0.5. So let's set those and let's draw.
So those are 0.5. Continuing we have another plus 0.5. Again, we'll just distribute. So 0.5
will flow to both of these. So we can set theirs.
X2W2 as well. That grad is 0.5. And let's redraw. Plus this are my favorite operations to back
propagate through because it's very simple. So now it's flowing into these expressions,
this 0.5. And so really again, keep in mind what derivative is telling us at every point in time
along here. This is saying that if we want the output of this neuron to increase,
then the influence on these expressions is positive on the output. Both of them are positive
contribution to the output. So now back propagating to X2 and W2 first, this is a times node. So we
know that the local derivative is the other term. So if we want to calculate X2 dot grad,
then can you think through what it's going to be?
So X2 dot grad will be W2 dot data times this X2W2 dot grad. And W2 dot grad will be
X2 dot data times X2W2 dot grad. So that's the local piece of chain rule.
Let's set them and let's redraw. So here we see that the gradient on our weight
2 is 0 because X2's data was 0. But X2 will have the gradient 0.5 because data here was 1.
And so what's interesting here is because the input X2 was 0 and because of the way the times
works, of course this gradient will be 0. And to think about intuitively why that is,
derivative always tells us the influence of this on the final output. If I wiggle W2,
how is the output changing? It's not changing because we're multiplying by 0. So because it's
not changing, there is no derivative and 0 is the correct answer because we're splashing
with that 0. And let's do it here. 0.5 should come here and flow through this times.
And so we'll have that X1 dot grad is, can you think through a little bit what this should be?
The local derivative of times with respect to X1 is going to be W1. So W1's data times
X1 W1 dot grad and W1 dot grad will be X1 dot data times X1 W2 W1 dot grad.
Let's see what those came out to be. So this is 0.5 so this would be negative 1.5 and this would be
1. And we back propagate it through this expression. These are the actual final derivatives. So if we
want this neurons output to increase, we know that what's necessary is that W2, we have no gradient.
W2 doesn't actually matter to this neuron right now, but this neuron, this weight should go up.
So if this weight goes up, then this neurons output would have gone up and proportionally
because the gradient is 1. Okay, so doing the back propagation manually is obviously ridiculous.
So we are now going to put an end to this suffering and we're going to see how we can implement
the backward pass a bit more automatically. We're not going to be doing all of it manually out here.
It's now pretty obvious to us by example how these pluses and times are back propagating
ingredients. So let's go up to the value object and we're going to start codifying what we've seen
in the examples below. So we're going to do this by storing a special self dot backward.
And underscore backward. And this will be a function which is going to do that little piece of chain
rule at each little node that compute that took inputs and produced output. We're going to store
how we are going to chain the outputs gradient into the inputs gradients. So by default,
this will be a function that doesn't do anything. So and you can also see that here in the value
in micro grad. So with this backward function, by default, doesn't do anything. This is a empty
function. And that would be sort of the case, for example, for leaf node, for leaf node, there's
nothing to do. But now if when we're creating these out values, these out values are an addition
of self and other. And so we're going to want to sell set outs backward to be the function that
propagates the gradient. So let's define what should happen.
And we're going to store it in a closure. Let's define what should happen when we call
out grad. For addition, our job is to take out grad and propagate it into self grad and other
grad. So basically we want to solve self grad to something. And we want to set others that grad
to something. Okay. And the way we saw below how chain rule works, we want to take the local
derivative times the sort of global derivative, I should call it, which is the derivative of the
final output of the expression with respect to outs data, respect to out. So the local derivative
of self in an addition is 1.0. So it's just 1.0 times outs grad. That's the chain rule. And others
that grad will be 1.0 times out grad. And what you basically what you're seeing here is that
outs grad will simply be copied onto self's grad and others grad, as we saw happens for an
addition operation. So we're going to later call this function to propagate the gradient
having done an addition. Let's now do multiplication. We're going to also define that backward.
And we're going to set its backward to be backward. And we want to chain out grad into
self that grad and others that grad. And this will be a little piece of chain rule for multiplication.
So we'll have, so what should this be? Can you think through?
So what is the local derivative? Here, the local derivative was others that data.
And then others that data. And then times out that grad, that's chain rule. And here we have
self that data times out that grad. That's what we've been doing. And finally here for 10H
that backward. And then we want to set outs backwards to be just backward.
And here we need to back propagate. We have out that grad and we want to chain it into
self that grad. And self that grad will be the local derivative of this operation that we've done
here, which is 10H. And so we saw that the local gradient is one minus the 10H of x squared,
which here is T. That's the local derivative because that's T is the output of this 10H.
So one minus T square is the local derivative. And then gradients,
as we multiplied because of the chain rule. So out grad is chained through the local gradient
into self that grad. And that should be basically it. So we're going to redefine our value node.
We're going to swing all the way down here. And we're going to redefine our expression.
Make sure that all the grads are zero. Okay. But now we don't have to do this manually anymore.
We are going to basically be calling the dot backward in the right order. So first, we want to call
o's dot backward. So o was the outcome of 10H. Right. So calling o's that those goes backward
will be this function. This is what it will do. Now we have to be careful.
Because there's a times out that grad and out that grad remember is initialized to zero.
So here we see grad zero. So as a base case, we need to set o's dot grad to 1.0
to initialize this with one.
And then once this is one, we can call o dot backward. And what that should do is it should
propagate this grad through 10H. So the local derivative times the global derivative,
which is initialized at one. So this should
a dough. So I thought about redoing it, but I figured I should just leave the error in here
because it's pretty funny. Why is not object not callable? It's because I screwed up.
We're trying to save these functions. So this is correct. This here, we don't want to call
the function because that returns none. These functions return none. We just want to store the
function. So let me redefine the value object. And then we're going to come back in redefine
the expression draw dot. Everything is great. O dot grad is one. O dot grad is one. And now
math this should work, of course. Okay. So all that backward should have, this grad should now be
0.5 if we redraw and everything went correctly, 0.5. Yay. Okay. So now we need to call n's dot grad
and it's not backward. Sorry. And it's backward. So that seems to have worked.
So n step backward, wrapped the gradient to both of these. So this is looking great.
Now we can of course call called B dot grad, B dot backward. Sorry. What's going to happen?
Well, B doesn't have it backward. B is backward because B is a leaf node. B is backward is by
initialization d empty function. So nothing would happen, but we can call call it on it. But when we
call this one, it's backward. Then we expect this point five to get further routed. Right. So
there we go. 0.5. And then finally, we want to call it here on X two, w two.
And on X one, w one.
Let's do both of those. And there we go. So we get 0.5 negative 1.5 and one exactly as we did
before. But now we've done it through calling that backward sort of manually. So we have the
last one last piece to get rid of, which is us calling underscore backward manually. So let's
think through what we are actually doing. We've laid out a mathematical expression and now we're
trying to go backwards through that expression. So going backwards through the expression just
means that we never want to call a dot backward for any node before we've done sort of
everything after it. So we have to do everything after it before ever going to call
dot backward on any one node. We have to get all of its full dependencies. Everything that
depends on has to propagate to it before we can continue back propagation. So this ordering of
graphs can be achieved using something called topological sort. So topological sort is basically
a laying out of a graph such that all the edges go only from left to right, basically.
So here we have a graph, it's a directory, a cyclic graph, a DAG. And this is two different
topological orders of it, I believe, where basically you'll see that it's laying out of the nodes such
that all the edges go only one way from left to right. And implementing topological sort,
you can look in Wikipedia and so on, I'm not going to go through it in detail. But basically,
this is what builds a topological graph. We maintain a set of visited nodes. And then we are
going through starting at some root node, which for us is oh, that's what I want to start the
topological sort. And starting at oh, we go through all of its children, and we need to lay them out
from left to right. And basically, this starts at oh, if it's not visited, then it marks it as
visited. And then it iterates through all of its children, and calls built topological on them.
And then after it's gone through all the children, it adds itself. So basically,
this node that we're going to call it on, like say, oh, is only going to add itself to the topo list
after all of the children have been processed. And that's how this function is guaranteeing
that you're only going to be in the list once all your children are in the list. And that's
the invariant that is being maintained. So if we built up on Oh, and then inspect this list,
we're going to see that it ordered our value objects. And the last one is the value of 0.707,
which is the output. So this is oh, and then this is n. And then all the other nodes get laid out
before it. So that built the topological graph. And really what we're doing now is we're just
calling dot underscore backward on all of the nodes in a topological order. So if we just reset
the gradients, they're all zero. What did we do? We started by setting o dot grad to be one.
That's the base case. Then we built the topological order.
And then we went for node in reversed off topo. Now, in the reverse order, because this list goes
from, you know, we need to go through it in reversed order. So starting at Oh, node backward.
And this should be it. There we go. Those are the correct derivatives. Finally, we are going to
hide this functionality. So I'm going to copy this. And we're going to hide it inside the value
class, because we don't want to have all that code lying around. So instead of an underscore
backward, we're now going to define an actual backward. So that backward, without the underscore.
And that's going to do all the stuff that we just arrived. So let me just clean this up a little bit.
So we're first going to build the topological graph, starting at self. So build topo of self
will populate the topological order into the topo list, which is a local variable. Then we set self
that grad to be one. And then for each node in the reversed list, so starting at us and going to
all the children underscore backward. And that should be it. So save. Come down here, redefine.
Okay, all the grads are zero. And now what we can do is without backward, without the underscore, and
there we go. And that's, that's back propagation. Please for one neuron. We shouldn't be too happy
with ourselves actually, because we have a bad bug. And we have not surfaced the bug because of
some specific conditions that we are have, we have to think about right now. So here's the
simplest case that shows the bug. Say I create a single node a. And then I create a B that is a
plus a. And then I call backward. So what's going to happen is a is three. And then a is a plus a.
So there's two arrows on top of each other here. Then we can see that B is, of course, the forward
pass works. B is just a plus a, which is six. But the gradient here is not actually correct,
that we calculate it automatically. And that's because, of course, just doing calculus in your
head, the derivative of B with respect to a should be two. One plus one. It's not one.
Intuitively, what's happening here, right? So B is the result of a plus a. And then we call
backward on it. So let's go up and see what that does. B is a result of addition. So how it is B.
And then when we call backward, what happened is self that grad was set to one. And then other
that grad was set to one. But because we're doing a plus a, self and other are actually the exact
same object. So we are overriding the gradient. We are setting it to one. And then we are setting
it again to one. And that's why it stays at one. So that's a problem. There's another way to
see this in a little bit more complicated expression. So here we have a and B. And then D will be the
multiplication of the two. And E will be the addition of the two. And then we multiply it
times D to get F. And then we call it F that backward. And these gradients, if you check,
will be incorrect. So fundamentally, what's happening here, again, is basically we're going to
see an issue anytime we use a variable more than once. Until now, in these expressions above,
every variable is used exactly once. So we didn't see the issue. But here, if a variable is used
more than once, what's going to happen during backward pass? We're back propagating from F to
E to D. So far so good. But now E calls it backward. And it deposits its gradients to A and B. But
then we come back to D and call backward. And it overrides those gradients at A and B. So that's
obviously a problem. And the solution here, if you look at the multivariate case of the chain rule,
and its generalization there, the solution there is basically that we have to accumulate these
gradients, these gradients add. And so instead of setting those gradients, we can simply do plus
equals, we need to accumulate those gradients, plus equals, plus equals, plus equals, plus equals.
And this will be okay, remember, because we are initializing them at zero. So they start at zero.
And then any contribution that flows backwards, we'll simply add. So now if we redefine this one,
because the plus equals this now works, because a dad grad started at zero. And we call beta backward,
we deposit one, and then we deposit one again. And now this is two, which is correct. And here,
this will also work. And we'll get correct gradients. Because when we call it a backward,
we will deposit the gradients from this branch. And then we get to back to detail backward,
it will deposit its own gradients. And then those gradients simply add on top of each other. And so
we just accumulate those gradients and that fixes the issue. Okay, now before we move on,
let me actually do a bit of cleanup here and delete some of these, some of this intermediate work.
So I'm not going to need any of this, now that we've derived all of it. We are going to keep this
because I want to come back to it. Delete the 10 H, delete our morning example,
delete the step, delete this, keep the code that draws, and then delete this example,
and leave behind only the definition of value. And now let's come back to this nonlinearity
here that we implemented the 10 H. Now I told you that we could have broken down 10 H into its
explicit atoms in terms of other expressions if we had the exp function. So if you remember,
10 H is defined like this, and we chose to develop 10 H as a single function. And we can do that
because we know it's derivative and we can back propagate through it. But we can also break down
10 H into an expressative function of exp. And I would like to do that now because I want to prove
to you that you get all the same results and all the same gradients. But also because it forces
us to implement a few more expressions. It forces us to do exponentiation, addition, subtraction,
division, and things like that. And I think it's a good exercise to go through a few more of these.
Okay, so let's scroll up to the definition of value. And here, one thing that we currently
can't do is we can do like a value of say 2.0. But we can't do, you know, here, for example,
we want to add constant one, and we can't do something like this. And we can't do it because
it says into object has no attribute data. That's because a plus one comes right here to add.
And then other is the integer one. And then here Python is trying to access one dot data,
and that's not a thing. And that's because basically one is not a value object. And we only have
addition form value objects. So as a matter of convenience, so that we can create expressions
like this and make them make sense, we can simply do something like this. Basically,
we let other alone, if other is an instance of value, but if it's not an instance of value,
we're going to assume that it's a number like an integer afloat. And we're going to simply
wrap it in in value. And then other will just become value of other. And then other will have a
data attribute. And this should work. So if I just say this read farm value, then this should work.
There we go. Okay, now let's do the exact same thing for multiply, because we can't do something
like this. Again, for the exact same reason. So we just have to go to mall. And if other is
not a value, then let's wrap it in value. Let's redefine value. And now this works.
Now here's a kind of unfortunate and not obvious part. A times two works, we saw that. But two times
a is that gonna work? You'd expect it to write, but actually it will not. And the reason it won't
is because Python doesn't know. Like when you do a times two, basically, so a times two,
Python will go and it will basically do something like a dot mall of two. That's basically what
we'll call but to it two times a is the same as two dot mall of a. And it doesn't to can't multiply
value. And so it's really confused about that. So instead, what happens is in Python, the way this
works is you are free to define something called the our mall. And our mall is kind of like a
fallback. So if the Python can't do two times a, it will check if if by any chance a knows how to
multiply two, and that will be called into our mall. So because Python can't do two times a,
it will check is there an our mall in value? And because there is, it will now call that.
And what we'll do here is we will swap the order of the operands. So basically, two times a will
redirect to our mall, and our mobile basically call a times two. And that's how that will work.
So redefining that with our mall, two times a becomes four. Okay, now looking at the other
elements that we still need, we need to know how to exponentiate and how to divide. So let's first
the explanation to the exponentiation part. We're going to introduce a single function X here.
And X is going to mirror 10 age in the sense that it's a simple, single function that
transforms a single scalar value and outputs a single scalar value. So we pop out the Python
number, we use method X to exponentiate it, create a new value object, everything that we've seen
before. The tricky part of course is how do you back propagate through e to the X. And so here,
you can potentially pause the video and think about what should go here.
Okay, so basically, I'm going to need to know what is the local derivative of e to the X. So
d by dx of e to the X is famously just e to the X. And we've already just calculated e to the X,
and it's inside out that data. So we can do out that data times, and out that grad, that's the
chain. So we're just chaining on to the current running grad. And this is what the expression
looks like. It looks a little confusing, but this is what it is. And that's the explanation.
So redefining, we should not be able to call a data exp. And hopefully the backward pass works
as well. Okay, and the last thing we'd like to do, of course, is we'd like to be able to divide.
Now, I actually will implement something slightly more powerful than division,
because division is just a special case of something a bit more powerful. So in particular,
just by rearranging, if we have some kind of a b equals value of 4.0 here, we'd like to
basically be able to do a divided b. And we'd like this to be able to give us 0.5. Now,
division actually can be reshuffled as follows. If we have a divided b, that's actually the same
as a multiplying 1 over b. And that's the same as a multiplying b to the power of negative 1.
And so what I'd like to do instead is I basically like to implement the operation of X to the k
for some constant k. So it's an integer or a float. And we would like to be able to differentiate
this. And then as a special case, negative 1 will be division. And so I'm doing that just because
it's more general and, yeah, you might as well do it that way. So basically, what I'm saying is we
can redefine division, which we will put here somewhere. Yeah, we can put this here somewhere.
What I'm saying is that we can redefine division. So self divide other can actually be rewritten
as self times other to the power of negative one. And now value raised to the power of negative one,
we have now defined that. So here's, so we need to implement the power function. What am I going to
put the power function maybe here somewhere? This is this color from Fort. So this function will be
called when we try to raise a value to some power. And other will be that power. Now, I'd like to
make sure that other is only an int or a float. Usually other is some kind of a different value
object. But here other will be forced to be an int or a float. Otherwise, the math won't work
for forward trying to achieve in the specific case. That would be a different derivative expression
if we wanted other to be a value. So here, we create the output value, which is just, you know,
this data raised to the power of other. And other here could be, for example, negative one. That's
what we are hoping to achieve. And then this is the backward stub. And this is the fun part,
which is what is the chain rule expression here for back for back propagating through the power
function, where the power is to the power of some kind of a constant. So this is the exercise,
and maybe pause the video here and see if you can figure it out yourself as to what we should put here.
Okay, so you can actually go here and look at derivative rules as an example. And we see lots
of derivatives that you can hopefully know from calculus. In particular, what we're looking for
is the power rule, because that's telling us that if we're trying to take d by dx of x to the n,
which is what we're doing here, then that is just n times x to the n minus one, right? Okay.
So that's telling us about the local derivative of this power operation. So all we want here,
basically n is now other, and self dot data is x. And so this now becomes other, which is n times
self dot data, which is now a Python int or a float. It's not a value object. We're accessing the data
attribute raised to the power of other minus one or n minus one. I can put brackets around this,
but this doesn't matter because power takes precedence over multiply and by hand. So that
would have been okay. And that's the local derivative only. But now we have to chain it. And we change
it just simply by multiplying by our top grad, that's chain rule. And this should technically work.
And we're gonna find out soon. But now if we do this, this should now work. And we get point five.
So the forward pass works, but does the backward password. And I realized that we actually also
have to know how to subtract. So right now, a minus b will not work. To make it work, we need one more
piece of code here. And basically, this is the subtraction. And the way we're going to implement
subtraction is we're going to implement it by addition of a negation. And then to implement
negation, we're going to multiply by negative one. So just again, using the stuff we've already
built and just expressing it in terms of what we have, and a minus b does not work. Okay, so now
let's scroll again to this expression here for this neuron. And let's just compute the backward
pass here once we've defined O. And let's draw it. So here's the gradients for all these leaf notes
for this two dimensional neuron that has a 10 H that we've seen before. So now what I'd like to
do is I'd like to break up this 10 H into this expression here. So let me copy paste this here.
And now instead of, we'll preserve the label. And we will change how we define O. So in particular,
we're going to implement this formula here. So we need e to the two X minus one over e to the
X plus one. So e to the two X, we need to take two times n and we need to exponentiate it.
That's e to the two X. And then because we're using it twice, let's create an intermediate variable,
E, and then define O as E plus one over E minus one over E plus one, E minus one over E plus one.
And that should be it. And then we should be able to draw that above. So now before I run this,
what do we expect to see? Number one, we're expecting to see a much longer graph here,
because we've broken up 10 H into a bunch of other operations. But those operations are
mathematically equivalent. And so what we're expecting to see is number one, the same result
here. So the forward pass works. And number two, because of that mathematical equivalence,
we expect to see the same backward pass and the same gradients on these late nodes. So these
gradients should be identical. So let's run this. So number one, let's verify that instead of a
single 10 H node, we have now PEXP. And we have plus, we have times negative one. This is the
division. And we end up with the same forward pass here. And then the gradients, we have to be
careful because they're in slightly different order, potentially. The gradients for W two X
two should be zero and point five, W two and X two are zero and point five. And W one X one are one
and negative one point five, one and negative one point five. So that means that both our forward
passes and backward passes were correct, because this turned out to be equivalent to 10 H before.
And so the reason I wanted to go through this exercise is number one, we got to practice a few
more operations and writing more backwards passes. And number two, I wanted to illustrate the point
that the level at which you implement your operations is totally up to you. You can implement backward
passes for tiny expressions, like a single individual plus or single times, or you can implement them
for say 10 H, which is a kind of a potentially you can see it as a composite operation, because
it's made up of all these more atomic operations. But really, all of this is kind of like a fake
concept. All that matters is we have some kind of inputs and some kind of an output. And this
output is a function of the inputs in some way. And as long as you can do forward pass and the
backward pass of that little operation, it doesn't matter what that operation is and how composite it
is. If you can write the local gradients, you can change the gradient and you can continue
back propagation. So the design of what those functions are is completely up to you.
So now I would like to show you how you can do the exact same thing by using a modern deep
neural network library, like for example, PyTorch, which I've roughly modeled micro grad by. And so
PyTorch is something you would use in production. And I'll show you how you can do the exact same
thing, but in PyTorch API. So I'm just going to copy paste it in and walk you through it a little
bit. This is what it looks like. So we're going to import PyTorch. And then we need to define these
value objects like we have here. Now micro grad is a scalar valued engine. So we only have
scalar values like 2.0. But in PyTorch, everything is based around tensors. And like I mentioned,
tensors are just end dimensional arrays of scalars. So that's why things get a little bit
more complicated here. I just need a scalar valued tensor, a tensor with just a single element.
But by default, when you work with PyTorch, you would use more complicated tensors like this.
So if I import PyTorch, then I can create tensors like this. And this tensor, for example, is a
2x3 array of scalars in a single compact representation. So you can check its shape. We see that it's a
2x3 array. And so this is usually what you would work with in the actual libraries. So here I'm
creating a tensor that has only a single element 2.0. And then I'm casting it to be double because
Python is by default using double precision for its floating point numbers. So I'd like
everything to be identical. By default, the data type of these tensors will be float 32.
So it's only using a single precision float. So I'm casting it to double so that we have
float 64 just like in Python. So I'm casting to double. And then we get something similar to
value of two. The next thing I have to do is because these are leaf nodes, by default PyTorch
assumes that they do not require gradients. So I need to explicitly say that all of these nodes
require gradients. Okay, so this is going to construct scalar valued one element tensors.
Make sure that PyTorch knows that they require gradients. Now by default, these are set to
false by the way because of efficiency reasons, because usually you would not want gradients for
leaf nodes, like the inputs to the network. And this is just trying to be efficient in the most
common cases. So once we've defined all of our values in PyTorch land, we can perform arithmetic
just like we can here in micro grad land. So this would just work. And then there's a torch.10h
also. And when we get back is a tensor again, and we can just like in micro grad, it's got a data
attribute and it's got grad attributes. So these tensor objects just like in micro grad have a dot
data and a dot grad. And the only difference here is that we need to call a dot item because
otherwise PyTorch dot item basically takes a single tensor of one element and it just returns
that element stripping out the tensor. So let me just run this and hopefully we are going to get
this is going to print the forward pass, which is 0.707. And this will be the gradients,
which hopefully are 0.50 negative 1.5 and 1. So if we just run this, there we go, 0.7. So the
forward pass agrees and then 0.50, a 1.5 and 1. So PyTorch agrees with us. And just to show you
here, basically, oh, here's a tensor with a single element. And it's a double. And we can call that
item on it to just get the single number out. So that's what item does. And oh is a tensor object
like I mentioned, and it's got a backward function just like we've implemented. And then all of these
also have a dot grad. So like X2, for example, on the grad, and it's a tensor. And we can pop out
the individual number with that item. So basically, tortious, torch can do what we did in my
program as a special case, when your tensors are all single element tensors. But the big deal with
PyTorch is that everything is significantly more efficient because we are working with these tensor
objects. And we can do lots of operations in parallel on all of these tensors. But otherwise,
what we've built very much agrees with the API of PyTorch. Okay, so now that we have some machinery
to build out pretty complicated mathematical expressions, we can also start building up neural
nets. And as I mentioned, neural nets are just a specific class of mathematical expressions.
So we're going to start building out a neural net piece by piece, and eventually we'll build out a
two layer multilayer perceptron as it's called. And I'll show you exactly what that means.
Let's start with a single individual neuron. We've implemented one here. But here I'm going to
implement one that also subscribes to the PyTorch API in how it designs its neural network modules.
So just like we saw that we can like match the API of PyTorch on the autograd side,
we're going to try to do that on the neural network modules. So here's class neuron.
And just for the sake of efficiency, I'm going to copy paste some sections that are
relatively straightforward. So the constructor will take number of inputs to this neuron,
which is how many inputs come to a neuron. So this one, for example, is three inputs.
And then it's going to create a weight that is some random number between negative one and one
for every one of those inputs and a bias that controls the overall trigger happiness of this
neuron. And then we're going to implement a depth underscore underscore call of self and x,
some input x. And really what we don't do here is w times x plus b, or w times x here is a dot
product specifically. Now, if you haven't seen call, let me just return 0.0 here from now,
the way this works now is we can have an x, which is say like 2.0, 3.0, then we can initialize a
neuron that is two dimensional, because these are two numbers. And then we can feed those two
numbers into that neuron to get an output. And so when you use this notation, n of x,
Python will use call. So currently, call just returns 0.0.
So we're going to do here. Now we'd like to actually do the forward pass of this neuron instead.
So we're going to do here first is we need to basically multiply all of the elements of
w with all of the elements of x pairwise, we need to multiply them. So the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to zip up salta w and x. And in Python, zip takes two iterators,
and it creates a new iterator that iterates over the topples of their corresponding entries.
So for example, just to show you we can print this list and still return 0.0 here.
So we see that these w's are paired up with the x's w with x.
And now what we want to do is for wy xi in, we want to multiply w times xi,
and then we want to sum all of that together to come up with an activation and add also
sub that b on top. So that's the raw activation. And then of course, we need to pass that through
a nonlinearity. So what we're going to be returning is act dot 10 h. And here's out. So now we see
that we are getting some outputs, and we get a different output from neuron each time because
we are initializing different weights and biases. And then to be a bit more efficient here, actually,
sum by the way, takes a second optional parameter, which is the start. And by default, the start is
0. So these elements of this sum will be added on top of 0 to begin with. But actually, we can
just start with cell dot b. And then we just have an expression like this. And then the generator
expression here must be parenthesized by thumb. There we go. Yep. So now we can forward a single
neuron. Next up, we're going to define a layer of neurons. So here we have a schematic for a
mlp. So we see that these mls each layer, this is one layer, has actually a number of neurons,
and they're not connected to each other. But all of them are fully connected to the input.
So what is a layer of neurons? It's just it's just a set of neurons evaluated independently.
So in the interest of time, I'm going to do something fairly straightforward here.
It's literally a layer is just a list of neurons. And then how many neurons do we have? We take that
as an input argument here, how many neurons do you want in your layer number of outputs in this
layer? And so we just initialize completely independent neurons with this given dimensionality. And
we call on it, we just independently evaluate them. So now instead of a neuron, we can make a layer
of neurons, we have two dimensional neurons, and let's have three of them. And now we see that we
have three independent evaluations of three different neurons. Right? Okay, finally, let's complete this
picture and define an entire multilateral perception or mlp. And as we can see here in an mlp, these
layers just feed into each other sequentially. So let's come here, and I'm just going to copy
the code here in interest of time. So an mlp is very similar. We're taking the number of inputs,
as before, but now instead of saying taking a single and out, which is number of neurons in a
single layer, we're going to take a list of and outs. And this list defines the sizes of all the
layers that we want in our mlp. So here we just put them all together, and then iterate over
consecutive pairs of these sizes and create layer objects for them. And then in the call function,
we are just calling them sequentially. So that's an mlp really. And let's actually
re-implement this picture. So we want three input neurons, and then two layers of four and an output
unit. So we want three dimensional input, say this is an example input, we want three inputs
into two layers of four and one output. And this, of course, is in the mlp. And there we go. That's
a forward pass of an mlp. To make this a little bit nicer, you see how we have just a single element,
but it's wrapped in a list because layer always returns lists. Circum, for convenience,
return outs at zero if len outs is exactly a single element else return full list. And this
will allow us to just get a single value out at the last layer that only has a single neuron.
And finally, we should be able to draw dot of n of x. And as you might imagine,
these expressions are now getting relatively involved. So this is an entire mlp that we're
defining now. All the way until a single output. Okay. And so obviously you would never differentiate
on pen and paper these expressions, but with micro grad, we will be able to back propagate all
the way through this and back propagate into these weights of all these neurons. So let's see how
that works. Okay, so let's create ourselves a very simple example data set here. So this data
set has four examples. And so we have four possible inputs into the neural net. And we have four
desired targets. So we'd like the neural net to assign or output 1, 1, 0, when it's fed this
example, negative one when it's fed these examples, and one when it's fed this example. So it's a
very simple binary classifier neural net, basically that we would like here. Now let's think what
the neural net currently thinks about these four examples. We can just get their predictions.
Basically, we can just call n of x for x in axis. And then we can print. So these are the outputs
of the neural net on those four examples. So the first one is 0.91, but we like it to be 1. So we
should push this one higher, this one we want to be higher. This one says 0.88, and we want this to be
negative one. This is 0.88, we want it to be negative one. And this one is 0.88, we want it to be one.
So how do we make the neural net and how do we tune the weights to better predict the desired
targets? And the trick used in deep learning to achieve this is to calculate a single number that
somehow measures the total performance of your neural net. And we call this single number the loss.
So the loss first is a single number that we're going to define that basically measures how well
the neural net is performing. Right now we have the intuitive sense that it's not performing very
well, because we're not very much close to this. So the loss will be high, and we'll want to minimize
the loss. So in particular, in this case, what we're going to do is we're going to implement
the mean squared error loss. So this is doing is we're going to basically iterate for y ground
truth and y output in zip of y's and y-thread. So we're going to pair up the ground truths with
the predictions. And the zip iterates over tuples of them. And for each
y ground truth and y output, we're going to subtract them.
And square them. So let's first see what these losses are. These are individual loss components.
And so basically for each one of the four, we are taking the prediction and the ground truth,
we are subtracting them and squaring them. So because this one is so close to its target,
0.91 is almost one, subtracting them gives a very small number. So here we would get like a
negative point one, and then squaring it just makes sure that regardless of whether we are more
negative or more positive, we always get a positive number. Instead of squaring, we should
also take for example the absolute value. We need to discard the sign. And so you see that the
expression is arranged so that you only get 0 exactly when y out is equal to y ground truth.
When those two are equal, so your prediction is exactly the target, you are going to get 0.
And if your prediction is not the target, you are going to get some other number. So here,
for example, we are way off. And so that's why the loss is quite high. And the more off we are,
the greater the loss will be. So we don't want high loss, we want low loss. And so the final loss
here will be just the sum of all of these numbers. So you see that this should be 0 roughly plus 0
roughly, but plus 7. So loss should be about 7 here. And now we want to minimize the loss. We want
the loss to be low, because if loss is low, then every one of the predictions is equal to its target.
So the loss, the lowest it can be is 0. And the greater it is, the worse off the neural net is
predicting. So now, of course, if we do loss that backward, something magical happened when I hit
enter. And the magical thing, of course, that happened is that we can look at and add layers
that neuron and that layers at say like the first layer, that neurons at zero. Because remember that
MLP has the layers, which is a list. And each layer has neurons, which is a list. And that gives
us individual neuron. And then it's got some weights. And so we can, for example, look at the weights
at zero. Oops, it's not called weights, it's called w. And that's a value. But now this value
also has a graph, because of the backward pass. And so we see that because this gradient here on
this particular weight of this particular neuron of this particular layer is negative, we see that
its influence on the loss is also negative. So slightly increasing this particular weight of
this neuron of this layer would make the loss go down. And we actually have this information for
every single one of our neurons and all of their parameters. Actually, it's worth looking at
also the draw dot loss, by the way. So previously, we looked at the draw dot of a single neural
neuron forward pass. And that was already a large expression. But what is this expression? We actually
forwarded every one of those four examples. And then we have the loss on top of them with the mean
squared error. And so this is a really massive graph. Because this graph that we built up now,
oh my gosh, this graph that we built up now, we're just kind of excessive. It's excessive because
it has four forward passes of a neural net for every one of the examples. And then it has the loss
on top. And it ends with the value of the loss, which was 7.12. And this loss will now back propagate
through all the forward forward passes, all the way through just every single intermediate value of
the neural net, all the way back to, of course, the parameters of the weights, which are the input.
So these weight parameters here are inputs to this neural net. And these numbers here,
these scalars are inputs to the neural net. So if we went around here, we will probably find
some of these examples, this 1.0, potentially maybe this 1.0, or, you know, some of the others.
And you'll see that they all have gradients as well. The thing is these gradients on the
input data are not that useful to us. And that's because the input data seems to be
not changeable. It's, it's a given to the problem. And so it's a fixed input. We're not going to be
changing it or messing with it, even though we do have gradients for it. But some of these gradients
here will be for the neural network parameters, the W's and the B's. And those sweep, of course,
we want to change. Okay, so now we're going to want some convenience code to gather up all the
parameters of the neural net so that we can operate on all of them simultaneously. And every one of
them, we will nudge a tiny amount based on the gradient deformation. So let's collect the parameters
of the neural net all in one array. So let's create a parameters of self that just returns
self that W, which is a list, concatenated with a list of self that B. So this will just return a
list list, plus list just, you know, gives you a list. So that's parameters of neuron. And I'm
calling it this way because also PyTorch has a parameters on every single and in module. And it
does exactly what we're doing here, it just returns the parameter tensors for us is the parameter
scalars. Now layer is also a module. So it will have parameters, self. And basically what we want to
do here is something like this, like, params is here, and then for neuron in salt out neurons,
we want to get neuron parameters. And we want to params that extend. So these are the parameters
of this neuron. And then we want to put them on top of params. So params dot extend of piece.
And then we want to return params. So this is way too much code. So actually there's a way to
simplify this, which is return p for neuron in self dot neurons for p in neuron dot parameters.
So it's a single list comprehension in Python, you can sort of nest them like this, and you can
then create the desired array. So these are identical. We can take this out. And then let's do this same
here. That parameters, self, and return a parameter for layer in self dot layers for p in layer dot
parameters. And that should be good. Now let me pop out this. So we don't re initialize our network,
because we need to re initialize our Okay, so unfortunately, we will have to probably
re initialize network, because we just had functionality. Because this class, of course,
we I want to get all the end up parameters. That's not going to work, because this is the old class.
Okay. So unfortunately, we do have to re initialize the network, which will change some of the
numbers. But let me do that so that we pick up the new API, we can now do end up parameters.
And these are all the weights and biases inside the entire neural net. So in total, this MLP has
41 parameters. And now we'll be able to change them. If we recalculate the loss here, we see that
unfortunately, we have slightly different predictions and slightly different loss. But that's okay.
Okay, so we see that this neurons gradient is slightly negative. We can also look at its data
right now, which is 0.85. So this is the current value of this neuron. And this is its gradient
on the loss. So what we want to do now is we want to iterate for every p in and that parameters.
So for all the 41 parameters of this neural net, we actually want to change p data,
slightly according to the gradient information. Okay, so dot dot dot to do here. But this will
be basically a tiny update in this gradient descent scheme. And gradient descent, we are thinking of
the gradient as a vector pointing in the direction of increased loss. And so in gradient descent,
we are modifying p data by a small step size in the direction of the gradient. So the step size,
as an example, could be like a very small number, 0.01 is the step size times p dot grad.
Right. But we have to think through some of the signs here. So in particular, working with
this specific example here, we see that if we just left it like this, then this neurons value
would be currently increased by a tiny amount of the gradient. The gradient is negative. So this
value of this neuron would go slightly down. It would become like 0.84 or something like that.
But if this neurons value goes lower, that would actually increase the loss. That because
the derivative of this neuron is negative. So increasing this makes the loss go down. So
increasing it is what we want to do instead of decreasing it. So basically what we're missing
here is we're actually missing a negative sign. And again, this other interpretation,
and that's because we want to minimize the loss. We don't want to maximize the loss. We want to
decrease it. And the other interpretation, as I mentioned, is you can think of the gradient vector.
So basically just the vector of all the gradients as pointing in the direction of increasing
the loss. But then we want to decrease it. So we actually want to go in the opposite direction.
And so you can convince yourself that this sort of like does the right thing here with a negative
because we want to minimize the loss. So if we notch all the parameters by tiny amount,
then we'll see that this data will have changed a little bit. So now this neuron
is a tiny amount greater value. So 0.854, when it's 0.857. And that's a good thing because slightly
increasing this neuron data makes the loss go down according to the gradient. And so the
correcting has happened signwise. And so now what we would expect, of course, is that because we've
changed all these parameters, we expect that the loss should have gone down a bit. So we want to
reevaluate the loss. Let me basically, this is just a data definition that hasn't changed. But the
forward pass here of the network, we can recalculate. And actually, let me do it outside here so that
we can compare the two loss values. So here, if I recalculate the loss, we'd expect the new loss
now to be slightly lower than this number. So hopefully what we're getting now is a tiny bit
lower than 4.84, 4.36. Okay. And remember, the way we've arranged this is that low loss means that
our predictions are matching the targets. So our predictions now are probably slightly closer to
the targets. And now all we have to do is we have to iterate this process. So again, we've done the
forward pass, and this is the loss. Now we can lost that backward. Let me take these out. And we can
do a step size. And now we should have a slightly lower loss. 4.36 goes to 3.9. And okay, so we've
done the forward pass. Here's the backward pass, nudge. And now the loss is 3.66, 3.47. And you get
the idea, we just continue doing this. And this is a gradient descent. We're just iteratively doing
forward pass, backward pass update, forward pass, backward pass update. And the neural net is
improving its predictions. So here, if we look at y-pred now, y-pred, we see that this value
should be getting closer to one. So this value should be getting more positive. These should be
getting more negative. And this one should be also getting more positive. So if we just iterate this
a few more times, actually, we'll maybe able to afford to go a bit faster. Let's try a slightly
higher learning rate. Oops. Okay, there we go. So now we're at 0.31. If you go too fast, by the way,
if you try to make it too big of a step, you may actually overstep over confidence. Because,
again, remember, we don't actually know exactly about the loss function. The loss function has all
kinds of structure. And we only know about the very local dependence of all these parameters on
the loss. But if we step too far, we may step into, you know, a part of the loss that is completely
different. And that can destabilize training and make your loss actually blow up even.
So the loss is now 0.04. So actually, the predictions should be really quite close. Let's take a look.
So you see how this is almost one, almost negative one, almost one. We can continue going.
So backward update. Oops, there we go. So we went way too fast. And we actually overstepped.
So we got to to eager, where are we now? Oops. Okay, seven in negative nine. So this is very,
very low loss. And the predictions are basically perfect. So somehow we were basically, we were
doing way to the updates and we briefly exploded. But then somehow we ended up getting into a really
good spot. So usually this learning rate and the tuning of it is a subtle art. You want to set
your learning rate. If it's too low, you're going to take way too long to converge. But if it's too
high, the whole thing gets unstable. And you might actually even explode the loss, depending on your
loss function. So finding the step size to be just right, it's it's a pretty subtle art sometimes,
when you're using sort of vanilla gradient descent. But we happen to get into a good spot.
We can look at and parameters. So this is the setting of weights and biases that makes our network
predict the desired targets very, very close. And basically we've successfully trained in neural
nut. Okay, let's make this a tiny bit more respectable and implement an actual training loop and what
that looks like. So this is the data definition that stays. This is the forward pass. So for k
in range, you know, we're going to take a bunch of steps. First, you do the forward pass. We evaluate
the loss. Let's reinitialize the neural line from scratch. And here's the data. And we first do
forward pass, then we do the backward pass. And then we do an update. That's great in descent.
And then we should be able to iterate this and we should be able to print the current step,
the current loss. Let's just print the sort of number of the loss. And that should be it.
And then the learning rate 0.01 is a little too small 0.1. We saw is like a little bit dangerous
with UI. Let's go somewhere between and we'll optimize this for not 10 steps, but let's go for
say 20 steps. Let me erase all of this junk. And let's run the optimization. And you see how we've
actually converged slower in a more controlled manner and got to a loss that is very low.
So I expect Y-Pred to be quite good. There we go.
And that's it. Okay, so this is kind of embarrassing, but we actually have a really terrible bug
in here. And it's a subtle bug and it's a very common bug. And I can't believe I've done it for
the 20th time in my life, especially on camera. And I could have re-shocked the whole thing,
but I think it's pretty funny. And you get to appreciate a bit what working with neural
nuts maybe is like sometimes. We are guilty of a common bug. I've actually tweeted the most
common neural mistakes a long time ago now. And I'm not really going to explain any of these,
except for we are guilty of number three. You forgot to zero grad before Doug backward. What is that?
Basically, what's happening and it's a subtle bug and I'm not sure if you saw it, is that
all of these weights here have a dot data and a dot grad. And dot grad starts at zero.
And then we do backward and we fill in the gradients. And then we do an update on the data,
but we don't flush the grad. It stays there. So when we do the second
forward pass and we do backward again, remember that all the backward operations do a plus equals
on the grad. And so these gradients just add up and they never get reset to zero. So basically,
we didn't zero grad. So here's how we zero grad before backward. We need to iterate over all the
parameters. And we need to make sure that p dot grad is set to zero. We need to reset it to zero,
just like it is in the constructor. So remember, all the way here for all these value nodes,
grad is reset to zero. And then all these backward passes do a plus equals from that grad.
But we need to make sure that we reset these grads to zero. So that when we do backward,
all of them start at zero and the actual backward pass accumulates the loss derivatives into the
grads. So this is zero grad in PyTorch. And we will get a slightly different optimization.
Let's reset the neural net. The data is the same. This is now, I think, correct. And we get a much
more, you know, we get a much more slower descent. We still end up with pretty good results. And we
can continue to submit more to get down lower and lower and lower. Yeah. So the only reason that
the previous thing worked, it's extremely buggy. The only reason that worked is that
this is a very, very simple problem. And it's very easy for this neural net to fit this data.
And so the grads ended up accumulating and it effectively gave us a massive step size. And it
made us converge extremely fast. But basically, now we have to do more steps to get to very low
values of loss and get Y-pred to be really good. We can try to step a bit greater.
Yeah, we're going to get closer and closer to one minus one. So we're going to do a lot of
some times tricky because you may have lots of bugs in the code and your network might actually
work just like ours worked. But chances are is that if we had a more complex problem,
then actually this bug would have made us not optimize the loss very well. And we were only able
to get away with it because the problem is very simple. So let's now bring everything together
and summarize what we learned. What are neural nets? Neural nets are these mathematical expressions.
Fairly simple mathematical expressions, in case of multi-layered perceptron, that take input as
the data and they take input the weights and the parameters of the neural net. Mathematical
expression for the forward pass, followed by a loss function. And the loss function tries to
measure the accuracy of the predictions. And usually the loss will be low when your predictions
are matching your targets or where the new network is basically behaving well. So we manipulate the
loss function so that when the loss is low, the network is doing what you wanted to do on your problem.
And then we backward the loss, use back propagation to get the gradient. And then we know how to
tune all the parameters to decrease the loss locally. But then we have to iterate that process
many times in what's called the gradient descent. So we simply follow the gradient information and
that minimizes the loss and the losses arranged so that when the loss is minimized, the network is
doing what you wanted to do. And yeah, so we just have a blob of neural stuff and we can make it
do arbitrary things. And that's what gives neural nets their power. It's, you know, this is a very
tiny network with 41 parameters. But you can build significantly more complicated neural nets
with billions at this point, almost trillions of parameters. And it's a massive blob of neural
tissue, simulated neural tissue, roughly speaking. And you can make it do extremely complex problems.
And these neural nets then have all kinds of very fascinating emergent properties in when you
try to make them do significantly hard problems. As in the case of GPT, for example, we have massive
amounts of text from the internet. And we're trying to get a neural nets to predict, to take
like a few words and try to predict the next word in a sequence. That's the learning problem.
And it turns out that when you train this on all of internet, the neural net actually has like
really remarkable emergent properties. But that neural net would have hundreds of billions of
parameters. But it works on fundamentally these exact same principles. The neural net, of course,
will be a bit more complex. But otherwise, the evaluating the gradient is there and will be
identical. And the gradient descent would be there and would be basically identical. But people
usually use slightly different updates. This is a very simple stochastic gradient set update.
And loss function would not be in mean squared error. They would be using something called
the cross entropy loss for predicting the next token. So there's a few more details,
but fundamentally, the neural network setup and neural network training is identical and pervasive.
And now you understand intuitively how that works under the hood. In the beginning of this video,
I told you that by the end of it, you would understand everything in micro grad and it would
slowly build it up. Let me briefly prove that to you. So I'm going to step through all the code
that is in micro grad as of today. Actually, potentially, some of the code will change by the
time you watch this video, because I intend to continue developing micro grad. But let's look
at what we have so far at least in it that pie is empty. When you go to engine.py, that has the
value, everything here you should mostly recognize. So we have the data data that grad attributes,
we have the backward function, we have the previous set of children and the operation that produced
this value. We have addition multiplication and raising to a scalar power. We have the
reloon nonlinearity, which is slightly different type of nonlinearity than 10H that we used in
this video. Both of them are nonlinearities. And notably, 10H is not actually present in micro grad
as of right now, but I intend to add it later. We have the backward, which is identical,
and then all of these other operations, which are built up on top of operations here. So values
should be very recognizable, except for the nonlinearity used in this video. There's no massive
difference between relu and 10H and sigmoid and these other nonlinearities. They're all roughly
equivalent and can be used in MLPs. So I use 10H because it's a bit smoother and because it's a
little bit more complicated than relu. And therefore, it's stressed a little bit more the
local gradients and working with those derivatives, which I thought would be useful.
And in the pie is the neural networks library, as I mentioned. So you should recognize
identical implementation of their own layer and MLP. Notably, or not so much, we have a class
module here. There's a parent class of all these modules. I did that because there's an end up module
class in PyTorch. And so this exactly matches that API and end up module in PyTorch has also a zero
grad, which I refactored out here. So that's the end of micro grad, really. Then there's a test,
which you'll see basically creates two chunks of code, one in micro grad and one in PyTorch.
And we'll make sure that the forward and the backward paths agree identically. For a slightly
less complicated expression and slightly more complicated expression, everything agrees. So we
agree with PyTorch and all of these operations. And finally, there's a demo that I, by Y and B
here. And it's a bit more complicated binary classification demo than the one I covered in
this lecture. So we only had a tiny data set of four examples. Here, we have a bit more complicated
example with lots of blue points and lots of red points. And we're trying to again, build a binary
classifier to distinguish two dimensional points as red or blue. It's a bit more complicated MLP
here with bigger MLP. The loss is a bit more complicated because it supports batches. So because
our data set was so tiny, we always did a forward pass on the entire data set of four examples.
But when your data set is like a million examples, what we usually do in practice is we basically
pick out some random subset, we call that a batch. And then we only process the batch
forward, backward and update. So we don't have to forward the entire training set.
So this supports batching because there's a lot more examples here. We do a forward pass.
The loss is slightly more different. This is a max margin loss that I implement here.
The one that we used was the mean squared error loss, because it's simplest one. There's also
the binary cross entropy loss. All of them can be used for binary classification and don't make
too much of a difference in the simple examples that we looked at so far. There's something called
L2 regularization used here. This has to do with generalization of the neural net and controls
the overfitting in machine learning setting. But I did not cover these concepts in this video,
potentially later. And the training loop you should recognize. So forward, backward, with zero grad
and update and so on. You'll notice that in the update here, the learning rate is scaled as a
function of number of iterations and it shrinks. And this is something called learning rate decay.
So in the beginning, you have a high learning rate. And as the network sort of stabilizes near the
end, you bring down the learning rate to get some of the fine details in the end. And in the end,
we see the decision surface of the neural net. And we see that it learned to separate out the red
and the blue area based on the data points. So that's the slightly more complicated example and
the demo that I by Y and B that you're free to go over. But yeah, as of today, that is micro grad.
I also wanted to show you a little bit of real stuff so that you get to see how this is actually
implemented in production grade library like PyTorch. So in particular, I wanted to show I wanted to
find and show you the backward pass for 10 H in PyTorch. So here in micro grad, we see that the
backward pass for 10 H is one minus T square, where T is the output of the 10 H of X, times
of that grad, which is a chain rule. So we're looking for something that looks like this.
Now, I went to PyTorch, which has an open source GitHub code base. And I looked through a lot of
its code. And honestly, I spent about 15 minutes and I couldn't find 10 H. And that's because these
libraries, unfortunately, they grow in size and entropy. And if you just search for 10 H, you get
apparently 2800 results and 400 and 406 files. So I don't know what these files are doing, honestly.
And why there are so many mentions of 10 H. But unfortunately, these libraries are quite
complex. They're meant to be used, not really inspected. Eventually, I did stumble on someone
who tries to change the 10 H backward code for some reason. And someone here pointed to the CPU
kernel and the CUDA kernel for 10 H backward. So this so basically depends on if you're using
PyTorch on a CPU device or on a GPU, which these are different devices and I haven't covered this.
But this is the 10 H backward kernel for CPU. And the reason it's so large is that at number one,
this is like if you're using a complex type, which we haven't even talked about, if you're using a
specific data type of B float 16, which we haven't talked about. And then if you're not, then this
is the kernel and deep here, we see something that resembles our backward pass. So they have
eight times one minus B square. So this B, B here must be the output of the 10 H and this is the
out that grad. So here we found it deep inside PyTorch on this location for some reason inside
binary ops kernel, when 10 H is not actually a binary op. And then this is the GPU kernel.
We're not complex, we're here and here we go with online of code. So we did find it, but basically,
unfortunately, these code bases are very large and micro grad is very, very simple. But if you
actually want to use real stuff, finding the code for it, you'll actually find that difficult.
I also wanted to show you a little example here, where PyTorch is showing you how you can register
a new type of function that you want to add to PyTorch as a Lego building block. So here, if you
want to, for example, add a like gender polynomial three, here's how you could do it, you will register
it as a class that subclasses, torch.org, that function. And then you have to tell PyTorch how
to forward your new function and how to backward through it. So as long as you can do the forward
pass of this little function piece that you want to add, and as long as you know, the local derivative,
local gradients, which are implemented in the backward, PyTorch will be able to back propagate
through your function. And then you can use this as a Lego block in a larger Lego castle of all
the different Lego blocks that PyTorch already has. And so that's the only thing you have to tell
PyTorch and everything would just work. And you can register new types of functions in this way,
following this example. And that is everything that I wanted to cover in this lecture. So I hope
you enjoyed building out micro grad with me. I hope you find interesting, insightful, and
yeah, I will post a lot of the links that are related to this video in the video description below.
I will also probably post a link to a discussion forum or discussion group where you can ask
questions related to this video. And then I can answer or someone else can answer your questions.
And I may also do a follow up video that answers some of the most common questions.
But for now, that's it. I hope you enjoyed it. If you did, then please like and subscribe so
that YouTube knows to feature this video to more people. And that's it for now. I'll see you later.
Now here's the problem. We know dl by. Wait, what is the problem?
And that's everything I wanted to cover in this lecture. So I hope you enjoyed us building out
micro-grabbed micro-grab. Okay, now let's do the exact same thing for multiply because we can't do
something like eight times two. Oops. I know what happened there.