Hi everyone. Today we are continuing our implementation of Makemore. Now in the
last lecture we implemented the PyGram language model and we implemented both
using counts and also using a super simple neural network that has a single
linear layer. Now this is the Jupyter notebook that we both
out last lecture and we saw that the way we approached this is that we looked at
only the single previous character and we predicted the distribution for the
character that would go mixed in the sequence and we did that by taking counts
and normalizing them into probabilities so that each row here sums to one. Now
this is all well and good if you only have one character of previous context and
this works and it's approachable. The problem with this model of course is that
the predictions from this model are not very good because you only take one
character of context so the model didn't produce very name like sounding things.
Now the problem with this approach though is that if we are to take more
context into account when predicting the next character in a sequence things
quickly blow up and this table the size of this table grows and in fact it grows
exponentially with the length of the context because if we only take a single
character at a time that's 27 possibilities of context but if we take two
characters in the past and try to predict the third one suddenly the number of rows
in this matrix you can look at it that way is 27 times 27 so there's 729
possibilities for what could have come in the context. If we take three
characters as the context suddenly we have 20,000 possibilities of context and
so there's just way too many rows of this matrix it's way too few counts for
each possibility and the whole thing just kind of explodes and doesn't work
very well. So that's why today we're going to move on to this bullet point
here and we're going to implement a multi-layer perceptron model to predict
the next character in a sequence and this modeling approach that we're going to
adopt follows this paper Ben-Jue et al 2003. So I have the paper pulled up here.
Now this isn't the very first paper that proposed the use of multi-layer
perceptrons or neural networks to predict the next character or token in a
sequence but it's definitely one that was very influential around that time.
It is very often cited to stand in for this idea and I think it's a very nice
write-up and so this is the paper that we're going to first look at and then
implement. Now this paper has 19 pages so we don't have time to go into the full
detail of this paper but I invite you to read it. It's very readable, interesting
and has a lot of interesting ideas in it as well. In the introduction they
describe the exact same problem I just described and then to address it they
propose the following model. Now keep in mind that we are building a
character level language model so we're working on the level of characters. In
this paper they have a vocabulary of 17,000 possible words and they instead
build a word level language model but we're going to still stick with the
characters but we'll take the same modeling approach. Now what they do is
basically they propose to take every one of these words 17,000 words and
they're going to associate to each word a say 30-dimensional feature vector.
So every word is now embedded into a 30-dimensional space. You can think of it
that way. So we have 17,000 points or vectors in a 30-dimensional space and
that's you might imagine that's very crowded that's a lot of points for a very
small space. Now in the beginning these words are initialized completely
randomly so they're spread out that random but then we're going to tune these
embeddings of these words using that propagation. So during the course of
training of this neural network these points or vectors are going to basically
move around in this space and you might imagine that for example words that have
very similar meanings or there are indeed synonyms of each other might end
up in a very similar part of the space and conversely words that mean very
different things would go somewhere else in this space. Now their modeling
approach otherwise is identical to ours. They are using a multi-layer neural
network to predict the next word given the previous words and to train the
neural network they are maximizing the log likelihood of the training data just
like we did. So the modeling approach itself is identical. Now here they have a
concrete example of this intuition. Why does it work? Basically suppose that for
example you are trying to predict a dog was running in a blank. Now suppose that
the exact phrase a dog was running in a has never occurred in a training data
and here you are at sort of test time later when the model is deployed somewhere
and it's trying to make a sentence and it's saying a dog was running in a blank
and because it's never encountered this exact phrase in the training set you're
out of distribution as we say like you don't have fundamentally any reason to
suspect what might come next but this approach actually allows you to get
around that because maybe you didn't see the exact phrase a dog was running in a
something but maybe you've seen similar phrases maybe you've seen the phrase the
dog was running in a blank and maybe your network has learned that a and the
are like frequently are interchangeable with each other and so maybe it took the
embedding for a and the embedding for the and it actually put them like nearby
each other in the space and so you can transfer knowledge through that embedding
and you can generalize in that way. Similarly the network could know that
cats and dogs are animals and they co-occur in lots of very similar
contexts and so even though you haven't seen this exact phrase or if you haven't
seen exactly walking or running you can through the embedding space transfer
knowledge and you can generalize to novel scenarios. So let's not scroll down to
the diagram of the neural network they have a nice diagram here and in this
example we are taking three previous words and we are trying to predict the
fourth word in a sequence. Now these three previous words as I mentioned we
have a vocabulary of 17,000 possible words so every one of these basically are the
index of the incoming word and because there are 17,000 words this is an
integer between 0 and 16,999. Now there's also a lookup table that they
call C. This lookup table is a matrix that is 17,000 by say 30 and basically
what we're doing here is we're treating this as a lookup table and so every
index is plucking out a row of this embedding matrix so that each index is
converted to the 30-dimensional vector that corresponds to the embedding
vector for that word. So here we have the input layer of 30 neurons for three
words making up 90 neurons in total and here they're saying that this matrix C
is shared across all the words so we're always indexing into the same
matrix C over and over for each one of these words. Next up is the hidden layer
of this neural network. The size of this hidden neural layer of this neural net is
a hot parameter so we use the word hyperparameter when it's kind of like a
design choice up to the designer of the neural net and this can be as large as
you'd like or as small as you'd like so for example the size could be 100 and
we are going to go over multiple choices of the size of this hidden layer or
going to evaluate how well they work. So say there were 100 neurons here all of
them would be fully connected to the 90 words or 90 numbers that make up these
three words. So this is a fully connected layer then there's a 10-inch long
linearity and then there's this output layer and because there are 17,000
possible words that could come next this layer has 17,000 neurons and all of
them are fully connected to all of these neurons in the hidden layer. So there's
a lot of parameters here because there's a lot of words so most computation is
here this is the expensive layer. Now there are 17,000 logits here so on top of
there we have the softmax layer which we've seen in our previous video as well.
So every one of these logits is exponentiated and then everything is
normalized to sum to one so that we have a nice probability distribution for the
next word in the sequence. Now of course during training we actually have the
label we have the identity of the next word in a sequence that word or its
index is used to pluck out the probability of that word and then we are
maximizing the probability of that word with respect to the parameters of this
neural net. So the parameters are the weights and biases of this output layer,
the weights and biases of the hidden layer and the embedding lookup table C
and all of that is optimized using backpropagation and these dashed arrows
ignore those that represents a variation of a neural net that we are not going to
explore in this video. So that's the setup and now let's
implement it. Okay so I started a brand new notebook for this
lecture. We are importing PyTorch and we are importing
matplotlib so we can create figures. Then I am reading all the names into a list
of words like I did before and I'm showing the first eight right here.
Keep in mind that we have a 32,000 in total these are just the first eight
and then here I'm building out the vocabulary of characters and all the
mappings from the characters as strings to integers
and vice versa. Now the first thing we want to do is we want to compile the
dataset for the neural network and I had to rewrite this code.
I'll show you in a second what it looks like.
So this is the code that I created for the dataset creation so let me first run
it and then I'll briefly explain how this works.
So first we're going to define something called block size and this is basically
the context length of how many characters do we take to predict the next one.
So here in this example we're taking three characters to predict the fourth one
so we have a block size of three that's the size of the block
that supports the prediction. Then here I'm building out the
x and y. The x are the input to the neural net
and the y are the labels for each example inside x.
Then I'm areaing over the first five words. I'm doing first five just for
efficiency while we are developing all the code but then later we are going to
come here and erase this so that we use the entire training set.
So here I'm printing the word Emma and here I'm basically showing of the
examples that we can generate the five examples that we can generate
out of the single sort of word Emma. So when we are given the context of just
dot dot dot the first character in a sequence is
e. In this context the label is m. When the context is this the label is m
and so forth. And so the way I build this out is first I start with a padded
context of just zero tokens. Then I iterate over all the characters.
I get the character in the sequence and I basically build out the array y of
this current character and the array x which stores the current running context.
And then here see I print everything and here I crop the context and enter the
new character in a sequence. So this is kind of like a rolling window of context.
Now we can change the block size here to for example four
and in that case we would be predicting the fifth character given the previous
four or it can be five and then it would look like this.
Or it can be say 10 and then it would look something like this.
We're taking 10 characters to predict the 11th one and we're always
padding with dots. So let me bring this back to three
just so that we have what we have here in the paper.
And finally the data set right now looks as follows.
From these five words we have created a data set of 32 examples
and each input of the neural net is three integers and we have a label that is
also an integer y. So x looks like this. These are the individual
examples and then y are the labels.
So given this let's now write a neural network that takes these
x's and predicts two y's. First let's build the embedding look up table c.
So we have 27 possible characters and we're going to embed them in a lower
dimensional space. In the paper they have 17,000 words
and they embed them in spaces as small dimensional as 30.
So they cram 17,000 words into 30 dimensional space.
In our case we have only 27 possible characters. So let's cram them in
something as small as to start with for example a two-dimensional space.
So this lookup table will be random numbers and we'll have 27 rows
and we'll have two columns. Right so each 20 each one of 27 characters
will have a two-dimensional embedding. So that's our matrix
c of embeddings in the beginning initialized randomly.
Now before we embed all of the integers inside the input x
using this lookup table c let me actually just try to embed a
single individual integer like say five. So we get a sense of how this works.
Now one way this works of course is we can just take the c
and we can index into row five and that gives us a vector
the fifth row of c and this is one way to do it.
The other way that I presented in the previous lecture is actually
seemingly different but actually identical. So in the previous lecture what
we did is we took these integers and we used the one
hot encoding to first encode them. So if that one hot
we want to encode integer five and we want to tell it that their number of
classes is 27. So that's the 26-dimensional vector of all zeros
except the fifth bit is turned on. Now this actually doesn't work.
The reason is that this input actually must be a torched dot tensor
and I'm making some of these errors intentionally just so you get to see
some errors and how to fix them. So this must be a tensor not an int
fairly straightforward to fix. We get a one hot vector
the fifth dimension is one and the shape of this is 27.
And now notice that just as I briefly alluded to in a previous video
if we take this one hot vector and we multiply it by c
then what would you expect? Well number one, first you'd expect an error
because expected scalar type long but found float.
So a little bit confusing but the problem here is that one hot
the data type of it is long it's a 64-bit integer
but this is a float tensor and so PyTorch doesn't know how to multiply
an int with a float and that's why we had to explicitly cast this to a float
so that we can multiply. Now the output actually here
is identical and then it's identical because of the way the matrix
a multiplication here works. We have the one hot
vector multiplying columns of c and because of all the zeros
they actually end up masking out everything in c except for the fifth row
which is blocked out and so we actually arrive at the same result
and that tells you that here we can interpret this first piece here
this embedding of the integer. We can either think of it as the integer
indexing into a lookup table c but equivalently we can also think of
this little piece here as a first layer of this bigger neural net.
This layer here has neurons that have no nonlinearity there's no 10h
they're just linear neurons and their weight matrix is
c and then we are encoding integers into one hot and feeding those into a
neural net and this first layer basically
embeds them. So those are two equivalent ways of doing the same thing
we're just going to index because it's much much faster and we're going to discard
this interpretation of one hot inputs into neural nets
and we're just going to index integers and create and use
embedding tables. Now embedding a single integer like five is easy enough
we can simply ask by torch to retrieve the fifth row of c
or the row index five of c but how do we simultaneously embed
all of these 32 by 3 integers stored in array x? Luckily bytorch indexing is
fairly flexible and quite powerful so it doesn't just work to
ask for a single element five like this you can actually index using lists
so for example we can get the rows five six and seven
and this will just work like this we can index with a list
it doesn't just have to be a list it can also be a actually tensor of
integers and we can index with that so this is a
integer tensor five six seven and this will just work as well.
In fact we can also for example repeat row seven and retrieve it multiple times
and that same index will just get embedded multiple times here.
So here we are indexing with a one-dimensional tensor of integers
but it turns out that you can also index with multi-dimensional tensors of
integers here we have a two-dimensional in tensor of
integers so we can simply just do c at x and this just works
and the shape of this is 32 by 3 which is the original shape
and now for every one of those 32 by 3 integers we've retrieved the embedding
vector here so basically we have that as an example
the 13th or example index 13 the second dimension
is the integer one as an example and so here if we do c of x which gives us
that array and then we index into 13 by 2 of that
array then we get the embedding here and you can verify that
c at one which is the integer at that location
is indeed equal to this you see they're equal.
So basically long story short pytorch indexing is awesome and to embed
simultaneously all of the integers in x we can simply do c of x
and that is our embedding and that just works.
Now let's construct this layer here the hidden layer
so we have that w1 as I'll call it are these weights which we will initialize
randomly. Now the number of inputs to this layer
is going to be three times two right because we have two dimensional
embeddings and we have three of them so the number of inputs is
six and the number of neurons in this layer is a variable up to us.
Let's use 100 neurons as an example and then biases
will be also initialized randomly as an example
and let's and we just need 100 of them. Now the problem with this is
we can't simply normally we would take the input in this case that's embedding
and we like to multiply it with these weights and then we would like to add
the bias. This is roughly what we want to do
but the problem here is that these embeddings are stacked up
in the dimensions of this input tensor. So this will not work this matrix
multiplication because this is a shape 32 by 3 by 2
and I can't multiply that by 6 by 100. So somehow we need to concatenate
these inputs here together so that we can do something along these lines
which currently does not work. So how do we transform this 32 by 3
by 2 into a 32 by 6 so that we can actually perform
this multiplication over here? I'd like to show you that there are usually
many ways of implementing what you'd like to do
in Torch and some of them will be faster, better, shorter, etc.
And that's because Torch is a very large library and it's got lots and lots of
functions. So if we just go to the documentation
and click on Torch you'll see that my slider here is very tiny
and that's because there are so many functions that you can call on these
tensors to transform them, create them, multiply them, add them,
perform all kinds of different operations on them.
And so this is kind of like the space of possibility if you will.
Now one of the things that you can do is we can control here
control f for concatenate and we see that there's a function
Torque.cat, short for concatenate. And this concatenate is a given sequence
of tensors in a given dimension and these tensors must have the same shape,
etc. So we can use the concatenate operation to in a naive way
concatenate these three embeddings for each input.
So in this case we have m of the shape and really what we want to do is we want
to retrieve these three parts and concatenate them.
So we want to grab all the examples. We want to grab
first the zeroth index and then all of this. So this plucks out
the 32 by 2 embeddings of just the first word here.
And so basically we want this guy, we want the first dimension
and we want the second dimension and these are the three pieces individually.
And then we want to treat this as a sequence and we want to torch.cat
on that sequence. So this is the list. torch.cat takes a
sequence of tensors and then we have to tell it along which dimension to
concatenate. So in this case all these are 32 by
2 and we want to concatenate not across dimension zero but across
dimension one. So passing in one gets us a result
the shape of this is 32 by 6 exactly as we'd like.
So that basically took 32 and squashed these back on
concatenating them into 32 by 6. Now this is kind of ugly because
this code would not generalize if we want to later change the block size.
Right now we have three inputs, three words but what if we had five
then here we would have to change the code because I'm indexing directly.
Well torch comes to rescue again because that turns out to be
a function called unbind and it removes a tensor dimension.
So removes the tensor dimension returns a tuple of all slices along a given
dimension without it. So this is exactly what we need
and basically when we call torch.unbind torch.unbind
of m and passing dimension one index one. This gives us a list of
a list of tensors exactly equivalent to this.
So running this gives us a length three and it's exactly this list and so we
can call torch.cat on it and along the first
dimension and this works and this shape is the same
but now this is it doesn't matter if we have block size three or five or 10
this will just work. So this is one way to do it but it
turns out that in this case there's actually a significantly better and
more efficient way and this gives me an opportunity to hint at some of the
internals of torch.tensor. So let's create an array here
of elements from zero to 17 and the shape of this
is just 18. It's a single vector of 18 numbers.
It turns out that we can very quickly re-represent this
as different sized and dimensional tensors. We do this by calling
a view and we can say that actually this is not a single vector of 18.
This is a two by nine tensor or alternatively this is a nine by two
tensor or this is actually a three by three by two tensor.
As long as the total number of elements here multiply to be the same
this will just work and in pytorch this operation calling
that view is extremely efficient and the reason for that is that in each
tensor there's something called the underlying storage
and the storage is just the numbers always as a one-dimensional vector
and this is how this tensor has represented in the computer memory.
It's always a one-dimensional vector but when we call that view
we are manipulating some of attributes of that tensor
that dictate how this one-dimensional sequence
is interpreted to be an n-dimensional tensor.
And so what's happening here is that no memory is being changed, copied, moved,
or created when we call that view. The storage is identical but when you call
that view some of the internal attributes of
the view of this tensor are being manipulated and changed.
In particular that's something there's something called a storage offset,
strides, and shapes and those are manipulated so that this one-dimensional
sequence of bytes is seen as different and dimensional
rays. There's a blog post here from Eric called
Pytorch Internals where he goes into some of this with respect to tensor
and how the view of a tensor is represented and this is really just like a
logical construct of representing the physical memory.
And so this is a pretty good blog post that you can go into.
I might also create an entire video on the internals of Torch tensor and how this
works. For here we just note that this is an extremely
efficient operation and if I delete this and come back to our
M. We see that the shape of our M is 32 by 3 by 2
but we can simply ask for Pytorch to view this instead as a 32 by 6.
And the way this gets flattened into a 32 by 6 array
just happens that these two get stacked up
in a single row and so that's basically the concatenation operation
that we're after. And you can verify that this actually gives the exact same
result as what we had before. So this is an element y equals and you can see
that all the elements of these two tensors are the same
and so we get the exact same result. So long story short we can actually just
come here and if we just view this as a 32 by 6
instead then this multiplication will work and give us the hidden states
that we're after. So if this is h then h slash shape
is now the 100 dimensional activations for every one of our 32
examples and this gives the desired result. Let me do two things here.
Number one let's not use 32 we can for example do something like
m dot shape at zero so that we don't hardcode these numbers
and this would work for any size of this m or alternatively we can also do
negative one. When we do negative one pytorch will infer
what this should be because the number of elements must be the same
and we're saying that this is 6 pytorch will derive that this must be 32
or whatever else it is if m is of different size.
The other thing is here one more thing I'd like to point out is
here when we do the concatenation this actually is much less efficient
because this concatenation would create a whole new tensor with a whole new
storage so new memory is being created because there's no way to concatenate
tensors just by manipulating the view attributes.
So this is inefficient and creates all kinds of new memory.
So let me delete this now we don't need this and here to calculate h
we want to also dot 10 h of this to get our
oops to get our h. So these are now numbers between negative one and one
because of the 10 h and we have that the shape is 32 by 100
and that is basically this hidden layer of activations here
for every one of our 32 examples. Now there's one more thing I glossed over
that we have to be very careful with and that this
and that's this plus here. In particular we want to make sure that the
broadcasting will do what we like. The shape of this is 32 by 100
and b1's shape is 100. So we see that the addition here will broadcast these
two and in particular we have 32 by 100 broadcasting to 100.
So broadcasting will align on the right create a fake dimension here.
So this will become a 1 by 100 row vector and then it will copy vertically
for every one of these rows of 32 and do an element-wise addition.
So in this case the correcting will be happening because the same
bias vector will be added to all the rows of this matrix.
So that is correct that's what we'd like and it's always good practice just make
sure so that you don't treat yourself in the foot.
And finally let's create the final layer here. So let's create
w2 and b2. The input now is 100 and the output number of neurons
will be for us 27 because we have 27 possible
characters that come next. So the biases will be 27 as well.
So therefore the logits which are the outputs of this neural net
are going to be h multiplied by w2 plus b2.
Logis that shape is 32 by 27 and the logits look good.
Now exactly as we saw in the previous video we want to take these logits and
we want to first exponentiate them to get our fake counts
and then we want to normalize them into a probability.
So prob is counts divide and now counts that sum along the first
dimension and keep them as true exactly as in the previous video.
And so prob that shape now is 32 by 27
and you'll see that every row of prob sums to one so it's normalized.
So that gives us the probabilities. Now of course we have the actual error that
comes next and that comes from this array y which we
created during the data separation. So y is this last piece here which is the
un-netiting of the next character in a sequence that we'd like to now predict.
So what we'd like to do now is just as in the previous video we'd like to
index into the rows of prob and in each row we'd like to
pluck out the probability assigned to the correct character
as given here. So first we have torshot
a range of 32 which is kind of like an iterator over
numbers from 0 to 31 and then we can index into prob in the following way.
Prob in torched out a range of 32 which iterates the rows
and then in each row we'd like to grab this column as given by y.
So this gives the current probabilities as assigned by this neural network with
this setting of its weights to the correct character in the sequence.
And you can see here that this looks okay for some of these characters like
this is basically 0.2 but it doesn't look very good at all for
many other characters. Like this is 0.0701 probability
and so the network thinks that some of these are extremely unlikely.
But of course we haven't trained the neural network yet.
So this will improve and ideally all of these numbers here of course are one
because then we are correctly predicting the next character.
Now just as in the previous video we want to take these probabilities
we want to look at the log probability and then we want to look at the average
log probability and then the negative of it to create
the negative log likelihood loss. So the loss here is 17
and this is the loss that we'd like to minimize to get the network to predict
the correct character in the sequence. Okay so I rewrote everything here and
made it a bit more respectable. So here's our dataset.
Here's all the parameters that we defined. I'm now using a generator to make it
reproducible. I clustered all the parameters into a single list of
parameters so that for example it's easy to count them
and see that in total we currently have about 3,400
parameters. And this is the forward pass as we developed it
and we arrive at a single number here the loss
that is currently expressing how well this neural network works
with the current setting of parameters. Now I would like to make it even more
respectable. So in particular CVs lies here where we take
the logits and we calculate the loss. We're not actually
reinventing the wheel here. This is just classification
and many people use classification and that's why there is a
functional.cross entropy function in PyTorch to calculate this much more
efficiently. So we could just simply call f.cross entropy
and we can pass in the logits and we can pass in the array of targets y
and this calculates the exact same loss.
So in fact we can simply put this here and erase these three lines
and we're going to get the exact same result. Now there are actually many good
reasons to prefer f.cross entropy over rolling your own implementation like
this. I did this for educational reasons but you'd
never use this in practice. Why is that? Number one when you use f.cross entropy
PyTorch will not actually create all these intermediate tensors because these
are all new tensors in memory and all this is fairly inefficient
to run like this. Instead PyTorch will cluster up all these
operations and very often create have a fused
kernels that very efficiently evaluate these expressions that are sort of like
clustered mathematical operations. Number two the backward pass can be made
much more efficient and not just because it's a
fused kernel but also analytically and mathematically
it's much it's often a very much simpler backward pass to implement.
We actually sell this with micrograd. You see here when we implemented 10H
the forward pass of this operation to calculate the 10H
was actually a fairly complicated mathematical expression
but because it's a clustered mathematical expression
when we did the backward pass we didn't individually backward through the
x and the two times and the minus one and division etc.
We just said it's one minus t squared and that's a much simpler mathematical
expression and we were able to do this because we're able to reuse
calculations and because we are able to mathematically and analytically
derive the derivative and often that expression simplifies mathematically
and so there's much less to implement. So not only can
kind of be made more efficient because it runs in a fused kernel
but also because the expressions can take a much simpler form mathematically.
So that's number one. Number two under the hood f dot cross entropy can also be
significantly more numerically well behaved.
Let me show you an example of how this works.
Suppose we have a logit of negative two three negative three zero and five
and then we are taking the exponent of it and normalizing it to sum to one.
So when logits take on this values everything is well and good and we get a
nice probability distribution. Now consider what happens when some of
these logits take on more extreme values and that can happen during
optimization of a neural network. Suppose that some of these numbers grow
very negative like saying negative one hundred.
Then actually everything will come out fine. We still get a probability that
you know are well behaved and they sum to one and everything is great.
But because of the way the exports if you have very positive logits let's say
positive one hundred in here you actually start to run into trouble
and we get not a number here. And the reason for that is that these counts
have an mth here. So if you pass in a very negative number two
exp you just get a very negative sorry not negative but very small number
very near zero and that's fine. But if you pass in a very positive number
suddenly we run out of range in our floating point number
that represents these counts. So basically we're taking E and we're
raising it to the power of 100 and that gives us inf
because we run out of dynamic range on this floating point number that is
count. And so we cannot pass very large
logits through this expression. Now let me reset these numbers to
something reasonable. The way PyTorch solved this is that
you see how we have a really well behaved result here.
It turns out that because of the normalization here you can actually offset
logits by any arbitrary constant value that you want.
So if I add one here you actually get the exact same result
or if I add two or if I subtract three. Any offset will produce the exact same
probabilities. So because negative numbers are okay
but positive numbers can actually overflow this exp
what PyTorch does is it internally calculates the maximum value that occurs
in the logits and it subtracts it. So in this case it would subtract five.
And so therefore the greatest number in logits will become zero
and all the other numbers will become some negative numbers.
And then the result of this is always well behaved.
So even if we have a hundred here previously, not good,
but because PyTorch will subtract a hundred this will work.
And so there's many good reasons to call cross entropy.
Number one the forward pass can be much more efficient. The backward pass can be
much more efficient and also thinks can be much more
numerically well behaved. Okay so let's now set up the training of this neural
mat. We have the forward pass. We don't need these
is that we have the loss is equal to the path that cross entropy
does the forward pass. Then we need the backward pass.
First we want to set the gradients to be zero.
So for p-in parameters we want to make sure that p.grad is none
which is the same as setting it to zero in PyTorch.
And then loss the backward to populate those gradients.
Once we have the gradients we can do the parameter update.
So for p-in parameters we want to take all the
data and we want to nudge it learning rate times p.grad.
And then we want to repeat this a few times.
And let's print the loss here as well.
Now this won't suffice and it will create an error because we also have to go for
p-in parameters and we have to make sure that p.
requires grad is set to true in PyTorch.
And this should just work. Okay so we started off with loss of 17 and we're
decreasing it. Lots run longer and you see how the loss decreases a lot here.
So if we just run for a thousand times we get a very very low loss and that
means that we're making very good predictions.
Now the reason that this is so straightforward right now is because we're only
overfitting 32 examples. So we only have 32 examples of the first five words
and therefore it's very easy to make this neural mat fit only these 32 examples
because we have 3,400 parameters and only 32 examples.
So we're doing what's called overfitting a single batch of the data and getting a very low loss
and good predictions but that's just because we have so many parameters for so few examples.
So it's easy to make this be very low.
Now we're not able to achieve exactly zero and the reason for that is we can for example
look at logits which are being predicted and we can look at the max along the first dimension
and in PyTorch max reports both the actual values that take on the maximum number
but also the indices so piece and you'll see that the indices are very close to the labels
but in some cases they differ. For example in this very first example
the predicted index is 19 but the label is 5 and we're not able to make loss be zero and
fundamentally that's because here the very first or the zero index is the example where
dot dot dot is supposed to predict e but you see how dot dot dot is also supposed to predict
an O and dot dot dot is also supposed to predict an I and then S as well and so basically E, O,
A or S are all possible outcomes in a training set for the exact same input.
So we're not able to completely overfit and make the loss be exactly zero
but we're getting very close in the cases where there's a unique input for a unique output.
In those cases we do what's called overfit and we basically get the exact same
and the exact correct result. So now all we have to do is we just need to make sure that we read
in the full data set and optimize the neural line. Okay so let's swing back up where we created the
data set and we see that here we only use the first five words so let me now erase this
and let me erase the print statements otherwise we'd be printing way too much
and so when we process the full data set of all the words we now had 228,000 examples
instead of just 32. So let's now scroll back down to this is much larger, we initialize the weights
the same number of parameters they all require gradients and then let's push this print out
loss that item to be here and let's just see how the optimization goes if we run this.
Okay so we started with a fairly high loss and then as we're optimizing the loss is coming down.
But you'll notice that it takes quite a bit of time for every single iteration so let's actually
address that because we're doing way too much work forwarding and back wording 220,000 examples.
In practice what people usually do is they perform forward and backward passing update
on many batches of the data. So what we will want to do is we want to randomly select some
portion of the data set and that's a mini batch and then only forward backward and update on that
little mini batch and then we integrate on those many batches. So in PyTorch we can for example
use Torch.brandint we can generate numbers between 0 and 5 and make 32 of them.
I believe the size has to be a tuple in PyTorch so we can have a tuple 32 of numbers between 0 and
5 but actually we want x.chain of 0 here and so this creates integers that index into our data set
and there's 32 of them. So if our mini batch size is 32 then we can come here and we can first do
mini batch construct. So integers that we want to optimize in this single iteration are in iX
and then we want to index into x with iX to only grab those rows. So we're only getting 32 rows of x
and therefore embeddings will again be 32 by 3 by 2 not 200,000 by 3 by 2 and then this iX has
to be used not just to index into x but also to index into y and now this should be mini batches
and this should be much much faster. So it's instant almost. So this way we can run many many examples
nearly instantly and decrease the loss much much faster. Now because we're only dealing with
mini batches the quality of our gradient is lower so the direction is not as reliable it's not the
actual gradient direction but the gradient direction is good enough even when it's estimating on only
32 examples that it is useful and so it's much better to have an approximate gradient and just
make more steps than it is to evaluate the exact gradient and take fewer steps. So that's why in
practice this works quite well. So let's now continue the optimization. Let me take out this
loss.item from here and place it over here again. Okay so we're hovering around 2.5 or so
however this is only the loss for that mini batch. So let's actually evaluate the loss
here for all of x and for all of y just so we have a full sense of exactly how all the model is
doing right now. So right now we're at about 2.7 on the entire training set. So let's run the
optimization for a while. Okay we're at 2.6 2.57 2.53. Okay so one issue of course is we don't know
if we're stepping too slow or too fast. So this point one I just guessed it. So one question is
how do you determine this learning rate and how do we gain confidence that we're stepping in the
right sort of speed. So I'll show you one way to determine a reasonable learning rate. It works
as follows. Let's reset our parameters to the initial settings and now let's print in every step
but let's only do 10 steps or so or maybe maybe 100 steps. We want to find like a very
reasonable set search range if you will. So for example if this is like very low then
we see that the loss is barely decreasing. So that's not that's like too low basically. So let's try
this one. Okay so we're decreasing the loss but like not very quickly. So that's a pretty good
low range. Now let's reset it again and now let's try to find the place at which the loss kind of
explodes. So maybe at negative one. Okay we see that we're minimizing the loss but you see how
it's kind of unstable it goes up and down quite a bit. So negative one is probably like a fast
learning rate. Let's try negative 10. Okay so this isn't optimizing. This is not working very
well. So negative 10 is way too big. Negative one was already kind of big. So therefore
negative one was like somewhat reasonable if I reset. So I'm thinking that the right learning
rate is somewhere between negative 0.001 and negative 1. So the way we can do this here is we
can use a torque shot lens space and we want to basically do something like this between 0 and 1 but
a number of steps is one more parameter that's required. Let's do 1000 steps. This creates 1000
numbers between 0.001 and 1. But it doesn't really make sense to step between these linearly.
So instead let me create learning rate exponent and instead of 0.001 this will be a negative 3
and this will be a 0. And then the actual lars that we want to search over are going to be 10
to the power of LRE. So now what we're doing is we're stepping linearly between the exponents
of these learning rates. This is 0.001 and this is 1 because 10 to the power of 0 is 1.
And therefore we are spaced exponentially in this interval. So these are the candidate learning
rates that we want to serve like search over roughly. So now what we're going to do is
here we are going to run the optimization for 1000 steps. And instead of using a fixed number
we are going to use learning rate indexing into here lars of i and make this i.
So basically let me be set this to be again starting from random creating these learning rates between
negative 0.001 and 1 but exponentially stepped. And here what we're doing is we're iterating 1000
times we're going to use the learning rate that's in the beginning very very low. In the beginning
it's going to be 0.001 but by the end it's going to be 1. And then we're going to step with that
learning rate. And now what we want to do is we want to keep track of the learning rates that we
used and we want to look at the losses that resulted. And so here let me track stats. So lri.append
lr and loss i.append loss that item. Okay, so again reset everything and then run.
And so basically we started with a very low learning rate and we went all the way up to
a learning rate of negative 1. And now what we can do is we can pay all t that plot
and we can plot the two. So we can plot the learning rates on the x-axis and the losses we saw on the y-axis.
And often you're going to find that your plot looks something like this. Where in the beginning
you have very low learning rates. So basically anything barely anything happened. Then we got
to like a nice spot here. And then as we increase the learning rate enough we basically started to
be kind of unstable here. So a good learning rate turns out to be somewhere around here.
And because we have lri here we actually may want to
do not lr not the learning rate but the exponent. So that would be the lre at i is maybe what we
will log. So let me reset this and redo that calculation. But now on the x-axis we have the
exponent of the learning rate. And so we can see the exponent of the learning rate that is good to
use. It would be sort of like roughly in the valley here because here the learning rates are
just way too low. And then here we expect relatively good learning rate somewhere here.
And then here things are starting to explode. So somewhere around negative 1 x the exponent of
the learning rate is a pretty good setting. And 10 to the negative 1 is 0.1. So 0.1 is actually
a fairly good learning rate around here. And that's what we had in the initial setting.
But that's roughly how you would determine it. And so here now we can take out the tracking of these.
And we can just simply set lr to be 10 to the negative 1 or basically otherwise 0.1 as it was
before. And now we have some confidence that this is actually a fairly good learning rate.
And so now what we can do is we can crank up the iterations. We can reset our optimization.
And we can run for a pretty long time using this learning rate. Oops, and we don't want to print.
It's way too much printing. So let me again reset and run 10,000 steps.
Okay, so we're at 0.2, 2.48 roughly. Let's run another 10,000 steps.
2.46. And now let's do one learning rate decay. What this means is we're going to take our
learning rate and we're going to 10x lower it. And so we're at the late stages of training
potentially. And we may want to go a bit slower. Let's do one more actually at 0.1. Just to see if
we're making an indent here. Okay, we're still making dent. And by the way, the
bygram loss that we achieved last video was 2.45. So we've already surpassed the bygram level.
And once I get a sense that this is actually kind of starting to plateau off, people like to do
as I mentioned this learning rate decay. So let's try to decay the loss, the learning rate I mean.
And we achieve it about 2.3 now. Obviously, this is janky and not exactly how you would train it
in production. But this is roughly what you're going through. You first find a decent learning
rate using the approach that I showed you. Then you start with that learning rate and you train
for a while. And then at the end, people like to do a learning rate decay, where you decay the
learning rate by say a factor of 10, and you do a few more steps. And then you get a trained network
roughly speaking. So we've achieved 2.3 and dramatically improved on the bygram language model using this
simple neural net as described here, using these 3400 parameters. Now there's something we have to
be careful with. I said that we have a better model because we are achieving a lower loss 2.3,
much lower than 2.45 with the bygram model previously. Now that's not exactly true. And the
reason that's not true is that this is actually a fairly small model. But these models can get
larger and larger if you keep adding neurons and parameters. So you can imagine that we don't
potentially have 1000 parameters, we could have 10,000 or 100,000 or millions of parameters.
And as the capacity of the neural network grows, it becomes more and more capable of
overfitting your training set. What that means is that the loss on the training set,
on the data that you're training on, will become very, very low as low as zero. But all that the
model is doing is memorizing your training set for Bingham. So if you take that model, and it looks
like it's working really well, but you try to sample from it, you will basically only get examples
exactly as they are in the training set, you won't get any new data. In addition to that,
if you try to evaluate the loss on some withheld names, or other words, you will actually see that
the loss on those can be very high. So basically, it's not a good model. So the standard in the field,
it is to split up your data set into three splits, as we call them. We have the training split,
the dev split or the validation split, and the test split. So training split,
test or sorry, dev or validation split, and test split. And typically, this would be say 80%
of your data set, this could be 10% and this 10% roughly. So you have these three splits of the data.
Now, these 80% of your trainings of the data set, the training set, is used to optimize the
parameters of the model, just like we're doing here, using gradient descent. These 10% of the
examples, the dev or validation split, they're used for development over all the hyper parameters
of your model. So hyper parameters are, for example, the size of this hidden layer, the size of the
embedding. So this is 100 or a two for us, but we could try different things. The strength of the
realization, which we aren't using yet so far. So there's lots of different hyper parameters and
settings that go into defining your neural net. And you can try many different variations of them
and see whichever one works best on your validation split. So this is used to train the parameters.
This is used to train the hyper parameters. And test split is used to evaluate basically the
performance of the model at the end. So we're only evaluating the loss on the test split very,
very sparingly and very few times, because every single time you evaluate your test loss, and you
learn something from it, you are basically starting to also train on the test split. So you are
only allowed to test the loss on the test set very, very few times, otherwise you risk overfitting to
it as well as you experiment on your model. So let's also split up our training data into train,
depth and test. And then we are going to train on train and only evaluate on test very, very
sparingly. Okay, so here we go. Here is where we took all the words and put them into x and y tensors.
So instead, let me create a new cell here. And let me just copy paste some code here,
because I don't think it's that complex, but we're going to try to save a little bit of time.
I'm converting this to be a function now. And this function takes some list of words and builds
the erase x and y for those words only. And then here, I am shuffling up all the words. So
these are the input words that we get. We are randomly shuffling them all up. And then
we're going to set n one to be the number of examples that is 80% of the words and n two to be 90%
of the way of the words. So basically, if ln of words is 30,000, n one is, well, sorry, I should
probably run this. n one is 25,000, and n two is 28,000. And so here we see that I'm calling
build data set to build a training set x and y by indexing into up to n one. So we're going to have
only 25,000 training words. And then we're going to have roughly n two minus n one,
three 3000 validation examples, or dev examples. And we're going to have
ln of words basically minus n two or 3,200 and four examples here for the test set.
So now we have x's and y's for all those three splits.
Oh, yeah, I'm printing their size here and set it function as well.
But here we don't have words, but these are already the individual examples made from those words.
So let's now scroll down here. And the data set now for training is more like this.
And then when we reset the network,
when we're training, we're only going to be training using x train,
x train and y train. So that's the only thing we're training on.
Let's see where we are on a single batch. Let's now train maybe a few more steps.
Training neural networks can take a while. Usually you don't do it in line.
You launch a bunch of jobs and you wait for them to finish.
Can take in multiple days and so on. Luckily, this is a very small network.
Okay, so the loss is pretty good. Oh, we accidentally used our learning rate.
That is way too low. So let me actually come back.
We use the decay learning rate of 0.01.
So this will train much faster. And then here when we evaluate, let's use the depth set here.
x depth and y depth to evaluate the loss. Okay. And let's now decay the learning rate and only do,
say, 10,000 examples. And let's evaluate the dev loss once here. Okay, so we're getting about
2.3 on dev. And so the neural network running was training that not see these dev examples.
It hasn't optimized on them. And yet when we evaluate the loss on these dev, we actually get
a pretty decent loss. And so we can also look at what the loss is on all of training set.
Oops. And so we see that the training and the dev loss are about equal. So we're not overfitting.
This model is not powerful enough to just be purely memorizing the data. And so far,
we are what's called underfitting because the training loss and the dev or test losses are roughly
equal. So what that typically means is that our network is very tiny, very small. And we expect
to make performance improvements by scaling up the size of this neural net. So let's do that now.
So let's come over here and let's increase the size within neural net. The easiest way to do this
is we can come here to the hidden layer, which currently has 100 neurons. And let's just bump
this up. So let's do 300 neurons. And then this is also 300 biases. And here we have 300 inputs
into the final layer. So let's initialize our neural net. We now have 10,000
10,000 parameters instead of 3000 parameters. And then we're not using this. And then here,
what I'd like to do is I'd like to actually keep track of that. Okay, let's just do this.
Let's keep stats again. And here when we're keeping track of the loss, let's just also
keep track of the steps. And let's just have a eye here. And let's train on 30,000 or rather say,
let's try 30,000. And we are at point one. And we should run this and optimize neural net.
And then here, basically, I want to PLT dot plot the steps and paste the loss.
So these are the Xs and the Ys. And this is the last function and how it's being optimized.
Now you see that there's quite a bit of thickness to this. And that's because we are optimizing
over these mini batches. And the mini batches create a little bit of noise in this. Where are we
in the deficit? We are at 2.5. So we're still having to optimize this neural net very well.
And that's probably because we make it bigger, it might take longer for this neural net to converge.
And so let's continue training.
Yeah, let's just continue training. One possibility is that the batch size is so low
that we just have way too much noise in the training. And we may want to increase the batch size so
that we have a bit more correct gradient. And we're not thrashing too much. And we can actually
like optimize more properly. Okay, this will now become meaningless because we've reinitialized
these. So yeah, this looks not pleasing right now. But the problem is look at tiny improvement,
but it's so hard to tell. Let's go again, 2.52. Let's try to decrease the learning rate by factor of 2.
Okay, we're at 4.32. Let's continue training.
We basically expect to see a lower loss than what we had before, because now we have a much
much bigger model. And we were underfitting. So we'd expect that increasing the size of the model
should help the neural net 2.32. Okay, so that's not happening too well. Now one other concern is
that even though we've made the 10H layer here, or the hidden layer much, much bigger, it could be
that the bottleneck of the network right now are these embeddings that are two-dimensional.
It can be that we're just cramming way too many characters into just two dimensions,
and the neural net is not able to really use that space effectively. And that that is sort of like
the bottleneck to our network's performance. Okay, 2.23. So just by decreasing the learning rate,
I was able to make quite a bit of progress. Let's run this one more time. And then evaluate the
training and the dev loss. Now one more thing after training that I'd like to do is I'd like to
visualize the embedding vectors for these characters before we scale up the embedding size from 2,
because we'd like to make this bottleneck potentially go away. But once I make this
greater than 2, we won't be able to visualize them. So here, okay, we're at 2.23 and 2.24.
So we're not improving much more. And maybe the bottleneck now is the character embedding size,
which is two. So here I have a bunch of code that will create a figure, and then we're going to
visualize the embeddings that were trained by the neural net on these characters, because right now
the embedding size is just two. So we can visualize all the characters with the x and the y coordinates
as the two embedding locations for each of these characters. And so here are the x coordinates
and the y coordinates, which are the columns of C. And then for each one, I also include the text
of the little character. So here what we see is actually kind of interesting. The network has
basically learned to separate out the characters and cluster them a little bit. So for example,
you see how the vowels, A, E, I, O, U are clustered up here. So what that's telling us is that the
neural net treats these is very similar, right? Because when they feed into the neural net, the
embedding for all these characters is very similar. And so the neural net thinks that they're very
similar and kind of like interchangeable. And that makes sense. Then the points that are like
really far away are for example, Q, Q is kind of treated as an exception. And Q has a very special
embedding vector, so to speak. Similarly, dot, which is a special character is all the way out here.
And a lot of the other letters are sort of clustered up here. And so it's kind of interesting
that there's a little bit of structure here, after the training. And it's not definitely not random,
and these embeddings make sense. So we're now going to scale up the embedding size and won't be able
to visualize it directly. But we expect that because we're underfitting and we made this layer
much bigger, and did not sufficiently improve the loss, we're thinking that the
constraint to better performance right now could be these embedding factors. So let's make them
bigger. Okay, so let's scroll up here. And now we don't have two dimensional embeddings, we are
going to have say 10 dimensional embeddings for each word. Then this layer will receive
three times 10. So 30 inputs will go into the hidden layer. Let's also make the
layer a bit smaller. So instead of 300, let's just do 200 neurons in that in layer. So now the
total number of elements will be slightly bigger at 11,000. And then we hear we have to be a bit
careful because, okay, the learning rate, we set to 0.1. Here we are hard code in six. And
obviously, if you're working in production, you don't want to be hard coding magic numbers.
But instead of six, this should now be 30. And let's run for 50,000 iterations. And let me split
out the initialization here outside so that when we run this a multiple times, it's not going to wipe
out our loss. In addition to that, here, let's instead of logging in lost that item, let's actually
log the let's do log 10, I believe that's a function of the loss. And I'll show you why in a second,
let's optimize this. Basically, I'd like to plot the log loss instead of a loss, because when you
plot the loss, many times it can have this hockey stick appearance. And log splashes it in. So it
just kind of looks nicer. So the x-axis is step I, and the y-axis will be the lost eye.
And then here, this is 30. Ideally, we wouldn't be hard coding these
because let's look at the loss. Okay, it's again very thick because the mini batch size is very
small, but the total loss of the training set is 2.3, and the test or the deficit is 2.38 as well.
So so far, so good. Let's try to now decrease the learning rate by a factor of 10,
and train for another 50,000 iterations.
We'd hope that we would be able to beat 2.32.
But again, we're just kind of like doing this very haphazardly. So I don't actually have confidence
that our learning rate is set very well, that our learning rate decay, which we just do at random,
is set very well. And so the optimization here is kind of suspects, to be honest. And this is not
how you would do it typically in production. In production, you would create parameters or
hyper parameters out of all these settings. And then you would run lots of experiments and see
whichever ones are working well for you. Okay, so we have 2.17 now and 2.2. Okay, so you see how the
training and the evaluation performance are starting to slightly slowly depart. So maybe we're
getting the sense that the neural net is getting good enough or that number parameters are large
enough that we are slowly starting to overfit. Let's maybe run one more iteration of this
and see where we get. But yeah, basically, you would be running lots of experiments,
and then you're slowly scrutinizing whichever ones give you the best
depth performance. And then once you find all the hyper parameters that make your
depth performance good, you take that model and you evaluate the test set performance a single time.
And that's the number that you report in your paper or wherever else you want to talk about
and brag about your model. So let's then rerun the plot and rerun the train and dove.
And because we're getting lower loss now, it is the case that the embedding size of
these was holding us back very likely. Okay, so 2.16, 2.19 is what we're roughly getting.
So there's many ways to go from many ways to go from here. We can continue tuning the optimization.
We can continue, for example, playing with the size of the neural net, or we can increase the
number of words or characters in our case that we are taking as an input. So instead of just
three characters, we could be taking more characters than as an input. And that could further improve
the loss. Okay, so I changed the code slightly. So we have here 200,000 steps of the optimization.
And in the first 100,000, we're using a learning rate of 0.1. And then in the next 100,000,
we're using a learning rate of 0.01. This is the loss that I achieve. And these are the
performance on the training and validation loss. And in particular, the best validation
loss I've been able to obtain in the last 30 minutes or so is 2.17. So now I invite you to
beat this number. And you have quite a few knobs available to you to, I think, surpass this number.
So number one, you can, of course, change the number of neurons in the hidden layer of this model.
You can change the dimensionality of the embedding lookup table. You can change the number of
characters that are feeding in as an input as the context into this model. And then, of course,
you can change the details of the optimization. How long are we running? What is the learning rate?
How does it change over time? How does it decay? You can change the batch size, and you may be able
to actually achieve a much better convergence speed in terms of how many seconds or minutes it takes
to train the model and get your result in terms of really good loss. And then, of course, I actually
invite you to read this paper. It is 19 pages, but at this point, you should actually be able to read
a good chunk of this paper and understand pretty good chunks of it. And this paper also has quite a
few ideas for improvements that you can play with. So all of those are knobs available to you,
and you should be able to beat this number. I'm leaving that as an exercise to the reader.
And that's it for now. And I'll see you next time.
Before we wrap up, I also wanted to show how you would sample from the model.
So we're going to generate 20 samples. At first, we begin with all dots. So that's the context.
And then until we generate the 0th character again, we're going to embed the current context
using the embedding table C. Now, usually here, the first dimension was the size of the training
set. But here, we're only working with a single example that we're generating. So this is just
the mission one, just for simplicity. And so this embedding then gets projected into the end state.
You get the logits. Now we calculate the probabilities. For that, you can use f dot softmax
of logits. And that just basically explains chase the logits and makes them sum to one.
And similar to cross entropy, it is careful that there's no overflows.
Once we have the probabilities, we sample from them using torshot multinomial to get our next index.
And then we shift the context window to append the index and record it.
And then we can just decode all the integers to strings and print them out. And so these are
some examples samples. And you can see that the model now works much better. So the words here
are much more word like or name like. So we have things like ham,
jose, lilla, you know, it's starting to sound a little bit more name like. So we're definitely
making progress. But we can still improve on this model quite a lot. Okay, sorry, there's some bonus
content. I wanted to mention that I want to make these notebooks more accessible. And so I don't
want you to have to like install Jibir notebook and torture everything else. So I will be sharing
a link to a Google collab. And Google collab will look like a notebook in your browser. And you can
just go to URL, and you'll be able to execute all of the code that you saw in the Google collab.
And so this is me executing the code in this lecture. And I shortened it a little bit. But
basically you're able to train the exact same network and then plot and sample from the model.
And everything is ready for you to like tinker with the numbers right there in your browser,
no installation necessary. So I just wanted to point that out. And the link to this will be in
the video description.