Hi everyone. Today we are continuing our implementation of Makemore.
Now in the last lecture we implemented the Multilayer Perceptron along the lines of
Benjio et al 2003 for Character Level Language Modeling.
So we followed this paper, took in a few characters in the past,
and used an MLP to predict the next character in a sequence.
So what we'd like to do now is we'd like to move on to more complex and larger neural
networks like recurrent neural networks and their variations like the grew LSTM and so on.
Now before we do that though we have to stick around the level of multilayer perception for a bit
longer. And I'd like to do this because I would like us to have a very good intuitive
understanding of the activations in the neural net during training and especially the gradients
that are flowing backwards and how they behave and what they look like.
This is going to be very important to understand the history of the development of these architectures
because we'll see that recurrent neural networks while they are very expressive in that they are
a universal approximator and can in principle implement all the algorithms.
We'll see that they are not very easily optimizable with the first order gradient-based
techniques that we have available to us and that we use all the time.
And the key to understanding why they are not optimizable easily is to understand the
activations and the gradients and how they behave during training.
And we'll see that a lot of the variants since recurrent neural networks have tried to
improve that situation. And so that's the path that we have to take and let's go start it.
So the starting code for this lecture is largely the code from before but I've cleaned it up a
little bit. So you'll see that we are importing all the torch and map plotlet utilities. We're
reading into words just like before. These are eight example words. There's a total of 32,000 of them.
Here's a vocabulary of all the lowercase letters and the special dot token.
Here we are reading the dataset and processing it and creating three splits, the train,
dev and the test split. Now in MLP this is the identical same MLP except you see that I removed
a bunch of magic numbers that we had here. And instead we have the dimensionality of the embedding
space of the characters and the number of hidden units in the hidden layer. And so I've pulled
them outside here so that we don't have to go and change all these magic numbers all the time.
With the same neural net with 11,000 parameters that we optimize now over 200,000 steps with batch
size of 32. And you'll see that I refactored the code here a little bit but there are no functional
changes. I just created a few extra variables, a few more comments and I removed all the magic
numbers and otherwise is the exact same thing. Then when we optimize we saw that our loss looked
something like this. We saw that the train and val loss were about 2.16 and so on. Here I refactored
the code a little bit for the evaluation of arbitrary splits. So you pass in the string of
which split you'd like to evaluate. And then here, depending on train, val or test, I index in and
I get the correct split. And then this is the forward pass of the network and evaluation of the loss
and printing it. So just making it nicer. One thing that you'll notice here is I'm using a decorator
torch.no grad which you can also look up and read documentation of. Basically what this decorator
does on top of a function is that whatever happens in this function is seen by torch to never require
an ingredients. So it will not do any of the bookkeeping that it does to keep track of all the gradients
in anticipation of an eventual backward pass. It's almost as if all the tensors that get created here
have a requires grad of false. And so it just makes everything much more efficient because you're
telling torch that I will not call that backward on any of this computation and you don't need to
maintain the graph under the hood. So that's what this does. And you can also use a context manager
with torch.no grad and you can let those up. Then here we have the sampling from a model.
Just as before. Just a forward pass of a neural net getting the distribution sampling from it,
adjusting the context window and repeating until we get the special and token. And we see that we
are starting to get much nicer looking words simple from the model. It's still not amazing and they're
still not fully named like but it's much better than when we had it with the bigerm model.
So that's our starting point. Now the first thing I would like to scrutinize is the initialization.
I can tell that our network is very improperly configured at initialization. And there's multiple
things wrong with it. But let's just start with the first one. Look here on the zero federation,
the very first iteration. We are recording a loss of 27 and this rapidly comes down to roughly one
or two or so. So I can tell that the initialization is all messed up because this is way too high.
In training of neural nets, it is almost always the case that you will have a rough idea for
what loss to expect at initialization. And that just depends on the loss function and the problem
setup. In this case, I do not expect 27. I expect a much lower number and we can calculate it together.
Basically at initialization, what we'd like is that there's 27 characters that could come next
for any one training example. At initialization, we have no reason to believe any characters to be
much more likely than others. And so we'd expect that the probability distribution that comes out
initially is a uniform distribution assigning about equal probability to all the 27 characters.
So basically what we'd like is the probability for any character would be roughly 1 over 27.
That is the probability we should record. And then the loss is the negative log probability.
So let's wrap this in a tensor. And then we can take the log of it. And then the negative log
probability is the loss we would expect, which is 3.29, much, much lower than 27. And so what's
happening right now is that at initialization, the neural net is creating probability distributions
that are all messed up. Some characters are very confident and some characters are very
not confident. And then basically what's happening is that the network is very confidently wrong.
And that makes that's what makes it record very high loss. So here's a smaller four-dimensional
example of the issue. Let's say we only have four characters. And then we have logits that
come out of the neural net, and they are very, very close to zero. Then when we take the softmax
of all zeros, we get probabilities there are a diffuse distribution. So sums to one and is
exactly uniform. And then in this case, if the label is say two, it doesn't actually matter
if this if the label is two or three or one or zero, because it's a uniform distribution,
we're recording the exact same loss, in this case, 1.38. So this is the loss we would expect for
a four-dimensional example. And I can see, of course, that as we start to manipulate these
logits, we're going to be changing the loss here. So it could be that we lock out and by chance,
this could be a very high number, like, you know, five or something like that. Then in that case,
we'll record a very low loss because we're signing the correct probability at initialization by chance
to the correct label. Much more likely it is that some other dimension will have a high
logic. And then what will happen is we start to record much higher loss. And what can come,
what can happen is basically the logits come out like something like this, you know, and they take
on extreme values, and we record really high loss. For example, if we have torched out random
of four, so these are uniform, sorry, these are normally distributed numbers for them.
And here we can also print the logits, probabilities that come out of it and loss.
And so because these logits are near zero, for the most part, the loss that comes out is, is okay.
But suppose this is like time stand now, you see how because these are more extreme values,
it's very unlikely that you're going to be guessing the correct bucket, and then you're
confidently wrong and recording very high loss. If your logits are coming up even more extreme,
you might get extremely seen losses like infinity even at initialization.
So basically this is not good. And we want the logits to be roughly zero, when the network is
initialized. In fact, the logits can don't have to be just zero, they just have to be equal. So for
example, if all the logits are one, then because of the normalization inside the softmax, this will
actually come out okay. But by symmetry, we don't want it to be any arbitrary positive or negative
number. We just want it to be all zeros and record the loss that we expect at initialization.
So let's not concretely see where things go wrong in our example. Here we have the initialization.
Let me reinitialize the neural net. And here let me break after the very first iteration. So we
only see the initial loss, which is 27. So that's way too high. And intuitively now we can expect
the variables involved. And we see that the logits here, if we just print some of these,
if we just print the first row, we see that the logits take on quite extreme values.
And that's what's creating the fake confidence and incorrect answers and makes the loss
get very, very high. So these logits should be much, much closer to zero. So now let's think
through how we can achieve logits coming out of this neural net to be more closer to zero.
You see here that logits are calculated as the hidden states multiplied by w2 plus b2.
So first of all, currently we're initializing b2 as random values of the right size.
But because we want roughly zero, we don't actually want to be adding a bias of random numbers.
So in fact, I'm going to add a time to zero here to make sure that b2 is just
basically zero at initialization. And second, this is age multiplied by w2. So if we want
logits to be very, very small, then we would be multiplying w2 and making that smaller.
So for example, if we scale down w2 by 0.1 all the elements, then if I do again, just a very
first situation, you see that we are getting much closer to what we expect. So roughly what we
want is about 3.29, this is 4.2. I can make this maybe even smaller, 3.32. Okay, so we're getting
closer and closer. Now, you're probably wondering, can we just set this to zero?
Then we get, of course, exactly what we're looking for at initialization. And the reason I don't
usually do this is because I'm very nervous. And I'll show you in a second why you don't want to
be setting w's or weights of a neural net exactly to zero. You usually want it to be small numbers
instead of exactly zero. For this output layer in this specific case, I think it would be fine.
But I'll show you in a second where things go wrong very quickly if you do that. So let's just go
with 0.01. In that case, our loss is close enough, but has some entropy. It's not exactly zero.
It's got some little entropy and that's used for symmetry breaking, as we'll see in a second.
The logits are now coming out much closer to zero and everything is well and good.
So if I just erase these and I now take away the break statement,
we can run the optimization with this new initialization. And let's just see what losses
we record. Okay, so I'll let it run. And you see that we started off good. And then we came down a bit.
The plot of the loss now doesn't have this hockey shape appearance. Because basically what's
happening in the hockey stick, the very first few iterations of the loss, what's happening during
the optimization is the optimization is just squashing down the logits and then it's rearranging the
logits. So basically we took away this easy part of the loss function, we're just the weights,
we're just being shrunk down. And so therefore, we don't get these easy gains in the beginning,
and we're just getting some of the hard gains of training the actual neural net. And so there's no
hockey stick appearance. So good things are happening in that both number one, loss at initialization
is what we expect. And the loss doesn't look like a hockey stick. And this is true for any neural
net you might train. And something to look at for. And second, the loss that came out is actually
quite a bit improved. Unfortunately, I erased what we had here before. I believe this was 2.12. And
this was with this was 2.16. So we get a slightly improved result. And the reason for that is because
we're spending more cycles more time optimizing the neural net actually, instead of just spending the
first several thousand iterations probably just squashing down the weights, because they are
so way too high in the beginning of the initialization. So something to look out for. And that's number
one. Now let's look at the second problem. Let me reinitialize our neural net and let me reintroduce
the break statement. So we have a reasonable initial loss. So even though everything is looking
good on the level of the loss, and we get something that we expect, there's still a deeper problem
lurking inside this neural net and its initialization. So the logits are now okay. The problem now is
with the values of h, the activations of the hidden states. Now if we just visualize this vector,
sorry, this tensor h, it's kind of hard to see, but the problem here, roughly speaking, is you see
how many of the elements are one or negative one. Now recall that torch dot 10 h, the 10 h function
is a squashing function. It takes arbitrary numbers and it squashes them into a range of negative one
and one, and it does so smoothly. So let's look at the histogram of h to get a better idea of the
distribution of the values inside this tensor. We can do this first. Well, we can see that h is 32
examples and 200 activations in each example. We can view it as negative one to stretch it out
into one large vector. And we can then call two list to convert this into one large Python list
of floats. And then we can pass this into p l t dot his for histogram. And we say we want 50 bins
and a semicolon to suppress a bunch of output we don't want. So we see this histogram and we see
that most of the values by far take on value of native one and one. So this 10 h is very, very active.
And we can also look at basically why that is we can look at the preactivations that feed into the
10 h. And we can see that the distribution of the preactivations are is very, very broad. These take
numbers between negative 15 and 15. And that's why in a torture 10 h everything is being squashed and
capped to be in the range of negative one and one. And lots of numbers here take on very extreme
values. Now if you are new to neural networks, you might not actually see this as an issue. But if
you're well versed in the dark arts of back propagation and then have an intuitive sense of how these
gradients flow through a neural net, you are looking at your distribution of 10 h activations here,
and you are sweating. So let me show you why. We have to keep in mind that during back propagation,
just like we saw in micro grad, we are doing backward pass starting at the loss and flowing
through the network backwards. In particular, we're going to back propagate through this torqued
dot 10 h. And this layer here is made up of 200 neurons for each one of these examples.
And it implements an element twice 10 h. So let's look at what happens in 10 h in the backward pass.
We can actually go back to our previous micro grad code in the very first lecture and see how we
implement a 10 h. We saw that the inputs here was x, and then we calculate t, which is the 10 h of
x. So that's t and t is between negative one and one, it's the output of the 10 h. And then in the
backward pass, how do we back propagate through a 10 h? We take out that grad, and then we multiply
it. This is the chain rule with the local gradient, which took the form of one minus t squared.
So what happens if the outputs of your 10 h are very close to negative one or one? If you plug in
t equals one here, you're going to get zero multiplying out that grad. No matter what out
that grad is, we are killing the gradient and we're stopping effectively the backward propagation
through this 10 h unit. Similarly, when t is negative one, this will again become zero,
and out that grad just stops. And intuitively, this makes sense because this is a 10 h neuron.
And what's happening is if its output is very close to one, then we are in the tail of this 10 h.
And so changing basically the input is not going to impact the output of the 10 h too much,
because it's so it's in a flat region of the 10 h. And so therefore, there's no impact on the
loss. And so indeed, the weights and the biases along with this 10 h neuron do not impact the loss,
because the output of this 10 h unit is in a flat region of the 10 h. And there's no influence.
We can be changing them whatever we want, however we want, and the loss is not impacted.
That's another way to justify that indeed, the gradient would be basically zero, it vanishes.
Indeed, when t equals zero, we get one times out that grad. So when the 10 h takes on exactly
value of zero, then out that grad is just passed through. So basically what this is doing, right,
is if t is equal to zero, then this the 10 h unit is sort of inactive, and gradient just passes
through. But the more you are in the flat tails, the more the gradient is squashed. So in fact,
you'll see that the gradient flowing through 10 h can only ever decrease in the amount that it
decreases is proportional through a square here, depending on how far you are in the flat tails of
this 10 h. And so that's kind of what's happening here. And through this, the concern here is that
if all of these outputs h are in the flat regions of negative one and one, then the gradients that
are flowing through the network will just get destroyed at this layer. Now there is some redeeming
quality here, and that we can actually get a sense of the problem here as follows.
I've got some code here. And basically what we want to do here is we want to take a look at
h, take the absolute value, and see how often it is in the in a flat region. So say greater than
0.99. And what you get is the following. And this is a Boolean tensor. So in the Boolean tensor,
you get a white, if this is true, and a black, if this is false. And so basically what we have here
is the 32 examples and the 200 hidden neurons. And we see that a lot of this is white. And what
that's telling us is that all these 10 h neurons were very, very active. And they're in the flat
tail. And so in all these cases, the back, the backward gradient would get destroyed.
Now we would be in a lot of trouble if for for any one of these 200 neurons, if it was the case
that the entire column is white, because in that case, we have what's called the dead neuron. And
this could be a 10 h neuron where the initialization of the weights and the biases could be such that
no single example ever activates this 10 h in the sort of active part of the 10 h. If all the
examples land in the tail, then this neuron will never learn it is a dead neuron. And so just
scrutinizing this and looking for columns of completely white, we see that this is not the case. So
I don't see a single neuron that is all of, you know, white. And so therefore it is the case that
for every one of these 10 h neurons, we do have some examples that activate them in the active
part of the 10 h. And so some gradients will flow through and this neuron will learn and neuron
will change and it will move and it will do something. But you can sometimes get yourself in cases where
you have dead neurons. And the way this manifests is that for 10 h neurons, this would be when no
matter what inputs you plug in from your data set, this 10 h neuron always fires completely one or
completely negative one. And then it will just not learn because all the gradients will be just zero
that. This is true not just for 10 h, but for a lot of other nonlinearities that people use in
neural networks. So we certainly use 10 h a lot, but sigmoid will have the exact same issue because
it is a squashing neuron. And so the same will be true for sigmoid, but, but, you know,
basically the same will actually apply to sigmoid. The same will also apply to rel.
So rel has a completely flat region here below zero. So if you have a rel in neuron, then it is a
pass through. If it is positive, and if it's if the pre activation is negative, it will just
shut it off. Since the region here is completely flat, then during back propagation, this would be
exactly zeroing out the gradient. Like all of the gradient would be set exactly to zero,
instead of just like a very, very small number, depending on how positive or negative t is.
And so you can get, for example, a dead rel neuron and a dead rel neuron would basically look like
basically what it is is if a neuron with a relo nonlinearity never activates. So for any
examples that you plug in in the data set, it never turns on. It's always in this flat region.
Then this rel neuron is a dead neuron. It's weights and bias will never learn. They will never get
a gradient because the neuron never activated. And this can sometimes happen at initialization,
because the weights in the bias is just make it so that by chance some neurons are just forever
dead. But it can also happen during optimization. If you have like a too high learning rate, for
example, sometimes you have these neurons that gets too much of a gradient and they get knocked
out off the data manifold. And what happens is that from then on, no example ever activates this
neuron. So this neuron remains dead forever. So it's kind of like a permanent brain damage in a,
in a mind of a network. And so sometimes what can happen is if your learning rate is very high,
for example, and you have a neural net with a really neurons, you train the neural net and you
get some last loss. But then actually what you do is you go through the entire training set and you
forward your examples and you can find neurons that never activate. They are dead neurons in your
network. And so those neurons will will never turn on. And usually what happens is that during
training, these real neurons are changing, moving, etc. And then because of a high gradient somewhere
by chance, they get knocked off. And then nothing ever activates them. And from then on, they are
just dead. So that's kind of like a permanent brain damage that can happen to some of these
neurons. These other nonlinearities like leaky relu will not suffer from this issue as much,
because you can see that it doesn't have flat tails. You'll almost always get gradients. And
elu is also fairly frequently used. It also might suffer from this issue because it has flat parts.
So that's just something to be aware of and something to be concerned about. And in this case, we have
way too many activations H that take on extreme values. And because there's no column of white,
I think we will be okay. And indeed, the network optimizes and gives us a pretty decent loss.
But it's just not optimal. And this is not something you want, especially during initialization.
And so basically what's happening is that this H preactivation that's flowing to 10H.
It's too extreme. It's too large. It's creating a distribution that is too saturated in both sides
of the 10H. And it's not something you want because it means that there's less training
for these neurons because they update less frequently. So how do we fix this? Well, HP
activation is MCAT, which comes from C. So these are uniform Gaussian. But then it's multiplied by
W1 plus B1. And HP react is too far off from zero. And that's causing the issue. So we want
this reactivation to be closer to zero, very similar to what we had with logits. So here,
we want actually something very, very similar. Now, it's okay to set the biases to very small
number. We can either multiply by 001 to get like a little bit of entropy. I sometimes like to do
that just so that there's like a little bit of variation and diversity in the original
initialization of these 10H neurons. And I find in practice that that can help optimization a little
bit. And then the weights, we can also just like squash. So let's multiply everything by 0.1.
Let's rerun the first batch. And now let's look at this. And well, first, let's look here.
You see now, because we multiply double by 0.1, we have a much better histogram. And that's because
the preactivations are now between negative 1.5 and 1.5. And this we expect much, much less
white. Okay, there's no white. So basically, that's because there are no neurons that saturated
above 0.99 in either direction. So it's actually a pretty decent place to be.
Maybe we can go up a little bit. Sorry, am I changing w1 here? Maybe we can go to 0.2.
Okay, so maybe something like this is a nice distribution. So maybe this is what our
initialization should be. So let me now erase these. And let me starting with initialization,
let me run the full optimization without the break. And let's see what we get. Okay, so the
optimization finished. And I rerun the loss. And this is the result that we get. And then just
as a reminder, I put down all the losses that we saw previously in this lecture. So we see that
we actually do get an improvement here. And just as a reminder, we started off with a validation
loss of 2.17 when we started. By fixing the softmax being confidently wrong, we came down to 2.13.
And by fixing the 10 H layer being way too saturated, we came down to 2.10. And the reason this is
happening, of course, is because our initialization is better. And so we're spending more time being
productive training, instead of not very productive training, because our gradients are set to zero.
And we have to learn very simple things like the overconfidence of the softmax in the beginning.
And we're spending cycles just like squashing down the weight matrix. So this is illustrating
basically initialization and its impacts on performance, just by being aware of the
internals of these neural nets and their activations, their gradients. Now, we're working with a very
small network. This is just one layer, multi layer perception. So because the network is so shallow,
the optimization problem is actually quite easy and very forgiving. So even though our
initialization was terrible, the network still learned eventually, it just got a bit worse result.
This is not the case in general, though. Once we actually start working with much deeper networks
that have say 50 layers, things can get much more complicated. And these problems stack up.
And so you can actually get into a place where the network is basically not training at all,
if your initialization is bad enough. And the deeper your network is and the more complex it is,
the less forgiving it is to some of these errors. And so something to be definitely aware of.
And something to scrutinize, something to plot, and something to be careful with. And
yeah. Okay, so that's great that that worked for us. But what we have here now is all these
magic numbers like point two, like where do I come up with this? And how am I supposed to set
these if I have a large neural net with lots and lots of layers? And so obviously no one does this
by hand. There's actually some relatively principled ways of setting these scales that I would like
to introduce to you now. So let me paste some code here that I prepared just to motivate the
discussion of this. So what I'm doing here is we have some random input here, X, that is drawn from
a Gaussian. And there's 1000 examples that are 10 dimensional. And then we have a weight in layer
here that is also initialized using Gaussian just like we did here. And we hit these neurons in the
hidden layer, look at 10 inputs, and there are 200 neurons in this hidden layer. And then we have
here, just like here, in this case, the multiplication x multiplied by w to get the preactivations of
these neurons. And basically the analysis here looks at, okay, suppose these are uniform Gaussian,
and these weights are uniform Gaussian. If I do x times w, and we forget for now the bias and the
nonlinearity, then what is the mean and the standard deviation of these Gaussians? So in the beginning
here, the input is just a normal Gaussian distribution mean zero, and the standard deviation is one.
And the standard deviation again is just the measure of a spread of the Gaussian. But then once we
multiply here, and we look at the histogram of y, we see that the mean, of course, stays the same,
it's about zero, because this is a symmetric operation. But we see here that the standard
deviation has expanded to three. So the input standard deviation was one, but now we've grown
to three. And so what you're seeing in the histogram is that this Gaussian is expanding.
And so we're expanding this Gaussian from the input. And we don't want that, we want most of
the neural nets to have relatively similar activations. So unit Gaussian roughly throughout the neural
net. And so the question is, how do we scale these W's to preserve the, to preserve this distribution
to remain a Gaussian? And so intuitively, if I multiply here, these elements of W by a large
number, like say by five, then this Gaussian grows and grows in standard deviation. So now we're at
15. So basically these numbers here in the output y take on more and more extreme values. But if we
scale it down, like say, point two, then conversely, this Gaussian is getting smaller and smaller,
and it's shrinking. And you can see that the standard deviation is point six. And so the
question is, what do I multiply by here to exactly preserve the standard deviation to be one? And it
turns out that the correct answer mathematically, when you work out through the variance of this
multiplication here, is that you are supposed to divide by the square root of the fan in, the fan
in is the basically the number of input elements here 10. So we are supposed to divide by 10 square
root. And this is one way to do the square root, you raise it to a power of 0.5, that's the same
as doing a square root. So when you divide by the square root of 10, then we see that the output
Gaussian, it has exactly standard deviation of one. Now unsurprisingly, a number of papers have
looked into how, but to best initialize neural networks. And in the case of multiple perceptions,
we can have fairly deep networks that have these nonlinearities in between. And we want to make
sure that the activations are well behaved, and they don't expand to infinity or shrink all the
wages zero. And the question is how do we initialize the weights so that these activations take on
reasonable values throughout the network. Now one paper that has studied this in quite a bit
detail that is often referenced is this paper by Kaiming Hetal called delving deep interactifiers.
Now in this case, they actually study convolutional neural networks, and they study, especially the
relu nonlinearity and the p relu nonlinearity, instead of a 10 h nonlinearity. But the analysis
is very similar. And basically what happens here is for them, the relu nonlinearity that they care
about quite a bit here, is a squashing function, where all the negative numbers are simply clamped
to zero. So the positive numbers are a path through, but everything negative is just set to zero.
And because you are basically throwing away half of the distribution, they find in their analysis of
the forward activations in the neural net, that you have to compensate for that with a gain.
And so here, they find that basically when they initialize their weights, they have to do it with
a zero mean Gaussian, whose standard deviation is square root of two over the fan in. What we have
here is we are initialized in Gaussian with the square root of fan in this NL here is the fan in.
So what we have is square root of one over the fan in, because we have the division here.
Now they have to add this factor of two because of the relu, which basically discards half of the
distribution and clamps at a zero. And so that's where you get an initial factor. Now in addition to
that, this paper also studies not just the sort of behavior of the activations in the forward
pass of the neural net, but it also studies the back propagation. And we have to make sure that
the gradients also are well-behaved. And so because ultimately they end up updating our parameters.
And what they find here through a lot of the analysis that I am actually to read through,
but it's not exactly approachable. What they find is basically, if you properly initialize
the forward pass, the backward pass is also approximately initialized up to a constant factor
that has to do with the size of the number of hidden neurons in an early and late layer.
And but basically they find empirically that this is not a choice that matters too much.
Now this timing initialization is also implemented in PyTorch. So if you go to torch.nnt.init
documentation, you'll find timing normal. And in my opinion, this is probably the most common way
of initializing neural networks now. And it takes a few keyword arguments here. So number one,
it wants to know the mode. Would you like to normalize the activations or would you like to normalize
the gradients to be always Gaussian with zero mean and a unit or one standard deviation? And
because they find the paper that this doesn't matter too much, most of the people just leave it
as the default which is pen in. And then second, pass in the nonlinearity that you are using.
Because depending on the nonlinearity, we need to calculate a slightly different gain. And so if
you're not linearity is just linear. So there's no nonlinearity, then the gain here will be one.
And we have the exact same kind of formula that we've got here. But if the nonlinearity is something
else, we're going to get a slightly different gain. And so if we come up here to the top,
we see that for example, in the case of Ralu, this gain is a square root of two. And the reason it's
a square root because in this paper, you see how the two is inside of the square root. So the gain
is a square root of two. In a case of linear or identity, we just get a gain of one. In a case of
10H, which is what we're using here, the advised gain is a five over three. And intuitively, why do
we need a gain on top of the initialization is because 10H, just like Ralu, is a contractive
transformation. So what that means is you're taking the output distribution from this matrix
multiplication. And then you are squashing it in some way. Now Ralu squashes it by taking everything
below zero and clamping it to zero. 10H also squashes it because it's a contractive operation.
It will take the tails and it will squeeze them in. And so in order to fight the squeezing in,
we need to boost the weights a little bit so that we renormalize everything back to standard
unit standard deviation. So that's why there's a little bit of a gain that comes out. Now I'm skipping
through this section a little bit quickly and I'm doing that actually intentionally. And the reason
for that is because about seven years ago when this paper was written, you have to actually be
extremely careful with the activations and ingredients and their ranges and their histograms. And you
have to be very careful with the precise setting of gains and the scrutinizing of the null linearity
is used and so on. And everything was very finicky and very fragile and very properly arranged for
the neural network train, especially if your neural network was very deep. But there are a number of
modern innovations that have made everything significantly more stable and more well behaved.
And it's become less important to initialize these networks exactly right. And some of those
modern innovations for example are residual connections which we will cover in the future.
The use of a number of normalization layers like for example,
batch normalization layer normalization group normalization, we're going to go into a lot of
these as well. And number three much better optimizers, not just a cast ingredient scent,
the simple optimizer we're basically using here, but slightly more complex optimizers like RMS
prop and especially Adam. And so all of these modern innovations make it less important for
you to precisely calibrate the initialization of the neural net. All that being said in practice,
what should we do? In practice when I initialize these neural nets, I basically just normalize my
weights by the square root of the fan in. So basically, roughly what we did here is what I do.
Now if we want to be exactly accurate here, we can go back in it of kind of normal, this is how
good implemented. We want to set the standard deviation to be gained over the square root of
fan in, right? So to set the standard deviation of our weights, we will proceed as follows.
Basically, when we have a torch dot random, and let's say I just create a thousand numbers,
we can look at the standard deviation of this. And of course, that's one, that's the amount of
spread. Let's make this a bit bigger. So it's closer to one. So that's the spread of the Gaussian
of zero mean and unit standard deviation. Now basically, when you take these and you multiply
by say point two, that basically scales down the Gaussian, and that makes its standard deviation
point two. So basically, the number that you multiply by here ends up being the standard deviation
of this Gaussian. So here, this is a standard deviation point two Gaussian here, when we
sample our w one. But we want to set the standard deviation to gain over square root of fan mode,
which is fan in. So in other words, we want to multiply by gain, which for 10 h is five over three,
five over three is the gain. And then times, I guess sorry, divide
square root of the fan in. And in this example here, the fan in was 10. And I just noticed actually
here, the fan in for w one is actually an embed times block size, which as you all recall is
actually 30. And that's because each character is 10 dimensional, but then we have three of them,
and we concatenate them. So actually the fan in here was 30. And I should have used 30 here, probably.
But basically, we want 30 square root. So this is the number, this is what our standard
deviation we want to be. And this number turns out to be point three. Whereas here, just by
fiddling with it and looking at the distribution and making sure it looks okay, we came up with point
two. And so instead, what we want to do here is we want to make the standard deviation be
five over three, which is our gain divide. This amount times point two, square root. And these
brackets here are not that necessary, but I'll just put them here for clarity. This is basically
what we want. This is the timing in it, in our case, for 10 h nonlinearity. And this is how we would
initialize the neural mat. And so we're multiplying by point three, instead of multiplying by point
two. And so we can, we can initialize this way. And then we can train the neural mat and see what
we got. Okay, so I trained the neural mat, and we end up in roughly the same spot. So looking at
the value should loss, we now get 2.10. And previously, we also had 2.10. There's a little bit of a
difference, but that's just the randomness, the process I suspect. But the big deal, of course,
is we get to the same spot, but we did not have to introduce any magic numbers that we got from
just looking at histograms and guessing checking. We have something that is semi-principled and will
scale us to much bigger networks, and something that we can sort of use as a guide. So I mentioned
that the precise setting of these initializations is not as important today due to some modern
innovations. And I think now is a pretty good time to introduce one of those modern innovations,
and that is batch normalization. So batch normalization came out in 2015 from a team at Google. And it
was an extremely impactful paper because it made it possible to train very deep neural nets quite
reliably. And basically just worked. So here's what batch normalization does and what's implemented.
Basically, we have these hidden states, H preact, right? And we were talking about how we don't want
these preactivation states to be way too small because then the 10H is not doing anything.
But we don't want them to be too large because then the 10H is saturated. In fact, we want them
to be roughly, roughly Gaussian. So zero mean and a unit or a one standard deviation, at least at
initialization. So the insight from the batch normalization paper is, okay, you have these hidden states,
and you'd like them to be roughly Gaussian, then why not take the hidden states and just normalize
them to be Gaussian? And it sounds kind of crazy, but you can just do that because standardizing
hidden states so that their unit Gaussian is a perfectly differentiable operation, as we'll soon
see. And so that was kind of like the big insight in this paper. And when I first read it, my mind
was blown because you can just normalize these hidden states. And if you'd like unit Gaussian
states in your network, at least initialization, you can just normalize them to be unit Gaussian.
So let's see how that works. So we're going to scroll to our preactivations here,
just before they enter into the 10H. Now the idea again is remember, we're trying to make
these roughly Gaussian. And that's because if these are way too small numbers, then the 10H
here is kind of inactive. But if these are very large numbers, then the 10H is way to saturate
and gradients in the flow. So we'd like this to be roughly Gaussian. So the insight in
rationalization again is that we can just standardize these activations. So they are exactly Gaussian.
So here H preact has a shape of 32 by 200, 32 examples by 200 neurons in the end layer.
So basically what we can do is we can take H preact and we can just calculate the mean.
And the mean we want to calculate across the zero dimension. And we want to also keep them as true
so that we can easily broadcast this. So the shape of this is one by 200. In other words,
we are doing the mean over all the elements in the batch. And similarly, we can calculate the
standard deviation of these activations. And there will also be one by 200. Now in this paper,
they have the sort of prescription here. And see here we are calculating the mean, which is just
taking the average value of any neurons activation. And then the standard deviation is basically kind
of like the measure of the spread that we've been using, which is the distance of every one of
these values away from the mean and that squared and averaged. That's the variance. And then if
you want to take the standard deviation, you will square root the variance to get the standard deviation.
So these are the two that we're calculating. And now we're going to normalize or standardize
these x's by subtracting the mean and dividing by the standard deviation. So basically we're
taking an entry preact and we subtract the mean. And then we divide by the standard deviation.
This is exactly what these two STD and mean are calculating. Oops. Sorry, this is the mean and
this is the variance. You see how the sigma is the standard deviation usually. So this is sigma
square, which is the variance is the square of the standard deviation. So this is how you
standardize these values. And what this will do is that every single neuron now and its firing rate
will be exactly unit Gaussian on these 32 examples, at least, of this batch. That's why it's called
batch normalization. We are normalizing these batches. And then we could in principle train this.
Notice that calculating the mean and their standard deviation, these are just mathematical
formulas. They're perfectly differentiable. All this is perfectly differentiable. And we can just train
this. The problem is you actually won't achieve a very good result with this. And the reason for that
is we want these to be roughly Gaussian, but only at initialization. But we don't want these to be
to be forced to be Gaussian always. We would like to allow the neural net to move this around,
to potentially make it more diffuse, to make it more sharp, to make some 10-inch neurons,
maybe more trigger happy or less trigger happy. So we'd like this distribution to move around,
and we'd like the back propagation to tell us how the distribution should move around.
And so in addition to this idea of standardizing the activations at any point in the network,
we have to also introduce this additional component in the paper. Here, describe the scale and shift.
And so basically what we're doing is we're taking these normalized inputs, and we are
additionally scaling them by some gain, and offsetting them by some bias, to get our final output from
this layer. And so what that amounts to is the following. We are going to allow a batch
normalization gain to be initialized at just once. And the once will be in the shape of one by and
hidden. And then we also will have a B and bias, which will be torched at zeros. And it will also be
of the shape n by one by and hidden. And then here, the B and gain will multiply this,
and the B and bias will offset it here. So because this is initialized to one and this to zero,
at initialization, each neuron's firing values in this batch will be exactly unit Gaussian,
and will have nice numbers, no matter what the distribution of the H-preact is coming in,
coming out, it will be unit Gaussian for each neuron. And that's roughly what we want,
at least at initialization. And then during optimization, we'll be able to back propagate
to B and gain and B and bias and change them. So the network is given the full ability to
do with this whatever it wants internally. Here, we just have to make sure that we
include these in the parameters of the neural mat, because they will be trained with back
preparation. So let's initialize this. And then we should be able to train.
And then we're going to also copy this line, which is the best normalization layer,
here on the single line of code. And we're going to swing down here, and we're also going to
do the exact same thing at test time here.
So similar to train time, we're going to normalize, and then scale. And that's going to give us our
train and validation loss. And we'll see in a second that we're actually going to change this
a little bit, but for now I'm going to keep it this way. So I'm just going to wait for this to
converge. Okay, so I allowed the neural nets to converge here. And when we scroll down, we see
that our validation loss here is 2.10 roughly, which I wrote down here. And we see that this is
actually kind of comparable to some of the results that we've achieved previously. Now,
I'm not actually expecting an improvement in this case. And that's because we are dealing with a
very simple neural net that has just a single hidden layer. So in fact, in this very simple case,
I've just wanted a layer, we were able to actually calculate what the scale of W should be to make
these preactivations already have a roughly Gaussian shape. So the bastardization is not
doing much here. But you might imagine that once you have a much deeper neural net that has lots
of different types of operations. And there's also, for example, residual connections, which
will cover and so on, it will become basically very, very difficult to tune the scales of your
weight matrices such that all the activations throughout the neural net are roughly Gaussian.
And so that's going to become very quickly intractable. But compared to that, it's going to be much,
much easier to sprinkle batch normalization layers throughout the neural net. So in particular,
it's common to look at every single linear layer like this one. This is a linear layer
multiplying by weight matrix and adding the bias. Or for example, convolutions, which we'll cover
later and also perform basically a multiplication with weight matrix, but in a more spatially structured
format. It's customer, it's customary to take these linear layer or convolutional layer and
append a bastardization layer right after it to control the scale of these activations at every
point in the neural net. So we'd be adding these bathroom layers throughout the neural net,
and then this controls the scale of these activations throughout the neural net.
It doesn't require us to do perfect mathematics and care about the activation distributions
for all these different types of neural neural neural logal building blocks that you might want
to introduce into your neural net. And it significantly stabilizes the training. And that's why these
layers are quite popular. Now, the stability offered by batch normalization actually comes
at a terrible cost. And that cost is that if you think about what's happening here,
something terribly strange and unnatural is happening. It used to be that we have a single
example feeding into a neural net, and then we calculate this activations and its logits.
And this is a deterministic sort of process. So you arrive at some logits for this example.
And then because of efficiency of training, we suddenly started to use batches of examples.
But those batches of examples were processed independently, and it was just an efficiency thing.
But now suddenly in batch normalization, because of the normalization through the batch,
we are coupling these examples mathematically and in the forward pass and backward pass of the neural
net. So now the hidden state activations, HP Act and your logits for any one input example
are not just a function of that example and its input, but they're also a function of all the
other examples that happen to come for a ride in that batch. And these examples are sampled
randomly. And so what's happening is, for example, when you look at HP Act, that's going to feed into
H, the hidden state activations, for example, for any one of these input examples, is going to
actually change slightly, depending on what other examples there are in the batch. And depending on
what other examples happen to come for a ride, H is going to change suddenly and it's going to
like jitter, if you imagine sampling different examples, because the statistics of the mean
understanding deviation are going to be impacted. And so you'll get a jitter for H and you'll get
a jitter for logits. And you think that this would be a bug or something undesirable, but in a very
strange way, this actually turns out to be good in neural network training and as a side effect.
And the reason for that is that you can think of this as kind of like a regularizer, because
what's happening is you have your input and you get your H. And then depending on the other
examples, this is jittering a bit. And so what that does is that it's effectively padding out
any one of these input examples, and it's introducing a little bit of entropy. And because of the
padding out, it's actually kind of like a form of a data augmentation, which we'll cover in the
future. And it's kind of like augmenting the input a little bit and jittering it. And that
makes it harder for the neural nets to overfit these concrete specific examples. So by introducing
all this noise, it actually like pads out the examples, and it regularizes the neural net.
And that's one of the reasons why the seemingly as a second order effect, this is actually
a regularizer. And that has made it harder for us to remove the use of batch normalization.
Because basically no one likes this property that the examples in the batch are coupled
mathematically and in the forward pass. And at least all kinds of like strange results,
we'll go into some of that in a second as well. And at least do a lot of bugs and so on. And so
no one likes this property. And so people have tried to deprecate the use of batch normalization
and move to other normalization techniques that do not couple the examples of batch.
Examples are linear normalization, instance normalization, group normalization, and so on.
And we'll come, we'll come or some of these later. But basically long story short,
batch normalization was the first kind of normalization layer to be introduced. It worked extremely well.
It happens to have this regularizing effect. It stabilized training. And people have been
trying to remove it and moved to some of the other normalization techniques. But it's been hard
because it just works quite well. And some of the reason that it works quite well is again,
because of this regularizing effect and because of the because it is quite effective at controlling
the activations and their distributions. So that's kind of like the brief story of batch normalization.
And I'd like to show you one of the other weird sort of outcomes of this coupling.
So here's one of the strange outcomes that I only glossed over previously.
When I was valuing the loss on the validation set, basically once we've trained a neural nut,
we'd like to deploy it in some kind of a setting. And we'd like to be able to feed in a single
individual example and get a prediction out from our neural nut. But how do we do that when our
neural nut now in a forward pass estimates the statistics of the mean understanding deviation
of a batch, the neural nut expects batches as an input now. So how do we feed in a single
example and get sensible results out? And so the proposal in the batch normalization paper is
the following. What we would like to do here is we would like to basically have a step after
training that calculates and sets the batch room mean and standard deviation a single time
over the training set. And so I wrote this code here in interest of time. And we're going to call
what's called calibrate the batch room statistics. And basically what we do is torch nut no grad
telling by torch that none of this we will call the duck backward on. And it's going to be a bit
more efficient. We're going to take the training set, get the preactivations for every single
training example. And then one single time estimate the mean and standard deviation over the entire
training set. And then we're going to get B and mean and B and standard deviation. And now these
are fixed numbers, estimating of the entire training set. And here, instead of estimating it
dynamically, we are going to instead here use B and mean. And here, we're just going to use B
and standard deviation. And so at test time, we are going to fix these, clamp them and use them
during inference. And now you see that we get basically identical result. But the benefit that
we've gained is that we can now also forward a single example, because the mean and standard
deviation are now fixed, sort of tensors. That said, nobody actually wants to estimate this mean and
standard deviation as a second stage after neural network training, because everyone is lazy. And
so this batch normalization paper actually introduced one more idea, which is that we can
we can estimate the mean and standard deviation in a running matter, running manner during training
of the neural network. And then we can simply just have a single stage of training. And on the side
of that training, we are estimating the running mean and standard deviation. So let's see what
that would look like. Let me basically take the mean here that we are estimating on the batch. And
let me call this B and mean on the i-theoration. And then here, this is B and STD,
B and STD, if the i. And the mean comes here and the STD comes here. So far, I've done nothing.
I've just moved around and I created these extra variables for the mean and standard deviation.
And I put them here. So far, nothing has changed. But what we're going to do now is we're going to
keep a running mean of both of these values during training. So let me swing up here and let me
create a B and mean underscore running. And I'm going to initialize it at zeros. And then B and
STD running, which are initialized at once. Because in the beginning, because of the way we
initialized W1 and B1, H preact will be roughly unit Gaussian. So the mean will be roughly zero,
and the standard deviation roughly one. So I'm going to initialize these that way. But then here,
I'm going to update these. And in PyTorch, these mean and standard deviation that are running,
they're not actually part of the gradient based optimization. We're never going to derive gradients
with respect to them. They're updated on the side of training. And so what we're good to do here is
we're going to say with torch top no grad, telling PyTorch that the update here is not supposed to
be building out a graph because there will be no dot backward. But this running mean is basically
going to be 0.99, nine times the current value, plus 0.001 times the this value, this new mean.
And in the same way, B and STD running will be mostly what it used to be.
But it will receive a small update in the direction of what the current standard deviation is.
And as you're seeing here, this update is outside and on the side of the gradient based optimization.
And it's simply being updated not using gradient descent. It's just being updated using a janky
like smooth sort of running mean manner. And so while the network is training and these
preactivations are sort of changing and shifting around during back propagation,
we are keeping track of the typical mean and standard deviation and estimating them once.
And when I run this, now I'm keeping track of this in a running manner. And what we're hoping for,
of course, is that the mean mean underscore running and B and mean underscore STD are going to be
very similar to the ones that we calculated here before. And that way, we don't need a second stage
because we've sort of combined the two stages and we've put them on the side of each other,
if you want to look at it that way. And this is how this is also implemented in the batch
normalization layer in PyTorch. So during training, the exact same thing will happen.
And then later when you're using inference, it will use the estimated running mean of both the mean
estimation of those hidden states. So let's wait for the optimization to converge. And hopefully,
the running mean and standard deviation are roughly equal to these two. And then we can simply use
it here. And we don't need this stage of explicit calibration at the end. Okay, so the optimization
finished, I'll rerun the explicit estimation. And then the B and mean from the explicit estimation
is here, and B and mean from the running estimation, during the optimization, you can see it's very,
very similar. It's not identical, but it's pretty close. And in the same way B and STD is this,
and B and STD running is this. As you can see that once again, they are fairly similar values,
not identical, but pretty close. And so then here, instead of B and mean, we can use the B and mean
running, instead of D and STD, we can use B and STD running. And hopefully, the validation
loss will not be impacted too much. Okay, so basically identical. And this way, we've eliminated
the need for this explicit stage of calibration, because we are doing it in line over here. Okay,
so we're almost done with batch normalization. There are only two more notes that I'd like to make.
Number one, I've skipped a discussion over what is this plus, absolute undoing here. This epsilon
is usually like some small fixed number, for example, one in negative five by default. And what it's
doing is that it's basically preventing a division by zero. In the case that the variance over your
batch is exactly zero. In that case, here we normally have a division by zero, but because of the
plus epsilon, this is going to become a small number in the denominator instead, and things will be
more well behaved. So feel free to also add a plus epsilon here of a very small number. It
doesn't actually substantially change the result. I'm going to skip it in our case just because
this is unlikely to happen in our very simple example here. And the second thing I want you to
notice is that we're being wasteful here, and it's very subtle. But right here, where we are adding
the bias into each preact, these biases now are actually useless, because we're adding them to
the each preact. But then we are calculating the mean for every one of these neurons and subtracting
it. So whatever bias you add here is going to get subtracted right here. And so these biases are
not doing anything. In fact, they're being subtracted out and they don't impact the rest of the
calculation. So if you look at B one that grad, it's actually going to be zero, because being
subtracted out and doesn't actually have any effect. And so whenever you're using batch
normalization layers, then if you have any weight layers before, like a linear or a comp or something
like that, you're better off coming here and just like not using bias. So you don't want to use bias.
And then here, you don't want to add it because that's that spurious. Instead, we have this
batch normalization bias here. And that batch normalization bias is now in charge of the
biasing of this distribution, instead of this B one that we had here originally. And so basically,
the batch normalization layer has its own bias. And there's no needs to have a bias in the layer
before it, because that bias is going to be subtracted up anyway. So that's the other small
detail to be careful with sometimes it's not going to do anything catastrophic. This B one will just
be useless. It will never get any gradient. It will not learn it will stay constant and it's just
wasteful. But it doesn't actually really impact anything otherwise. Okay, so I rearranged the code
a little bit with comments. And I just wanted to give a very quick summary of the batch normalization
layer. We are using batch normalization to control the statistics of activations in
the neural net. It is common to sprinkle batch normalization layer across the neural net. And
usually we will place it after layers that have multiplications, like for example, a linear layer
or a convolutional layer, which we may cover in the future. Now, the batch normalization internally
has parameters for the gain and the bias. And these are trained using back propagation.
It also has two buffers. The buffers are the mean and the standard deviation, the running mean,
and the running mean of the standard deviation. And these are not trained using back propagation.
These are trained using this janky update of kind of like a running mean update. So
these are sort of the parameters and the buffers of batch room layer. And then really what it's
doing is it's calculating the mean and the standard deviation of the activations that are feeding into
the batch room layer over that batch. Then it's centering that batch to be unit Gaussian.
And then it's offsetting and scaling it by the learned bias and gain. And then on top of that,
it's keeping track of the mean and standard deviation of the inputs. And it's maintaining
this running mean and standard deviation. And this will later be used at inference so that we
don't have to re-estimate the mean and standard deviation all the time. And in addition, that
allows us to basically forward individual examples at test time. So that's the batch
normalization layer. It's a fairly complicated layer. But this is what it's doing internally.
Now I wanted to show you a little bit of a real example. So you can search resnet, which is a
residual neural network. And these are contacts of neural arcs used for image classification.
And of course, we haven't come in dress nets in detail. So I'm not going to explain all the
pieces of it. But for now, just note that the image feeds into a resnet on the top here. And
there's many, many layers with repeating structure, all the way to predictions of what's inside that
image. This repeating structure is made up of these blocks. And these blocks are just sequentially
stacked up in this deep neural network. Now the code for this, the block basically that's used
and repeated sequentially in series is called this bottleneck block, bottleneck block. And there's a
lot here. This is all pytorch. And of course, we haven't covered all of it, but I want to point
out some small pieces of it. Here in the init is where we initialize the neural net. So this code
of block here is basically the kind of stuff we're doing here. We're initializing all the layers.
And in the forward, we are specifying how the neural net acts once you actually have the input.
So this code here is along the lines of what we're doing here. And now these blocks are
replicated and stacked up serially. And that's what a residual network would be. And so notice
what's happening here, come one. These are convolutional layers. And these convolutional
layers, basically, they're the same thing as a linear layer, except convolutional layers don't
apply. Convolutional layers are used for images. And so they have spatial structure. And basically,
this linear multiplication and bias offset are done on patches, instead of a map, instead of the
full input. So because these images have structure spatial structure, convolutions just basically do
wx plus b, but they do it on overlapping patches of the input. But otherwise, it's wx plus b.
Then we have the normal layer, which by default here is initialized to be a bash norm in 2D. So
two dimensional bash normalization layer. And then we have a nonlinearity like relu. So instead of
here they use relu, we are using 10H in this case. But both both are just nonlinearities and you
can just use them relatively interchangeably for very deep networks relu typically empirically
work a bit better. So see the motif that's being repeated here. We have convolution,
bash normalization relu, convolution, bash normalization, et cetera. And then here, this is residual
connection that we haven't covered yet. But basically, that's the exact same pattern we have here. We
have a weight layer, like a convolution or like a linear layer, bash normalization, and then 10H,
which is a nonlinearity. But basically a weight layer, a normalization layer, and nonlinearity.
And that's the motif that you would be stacking up when you create these deep neural networks.
Exactly as it's done here. And one more thing I'd like you to notice is that here when they are
initializing the conv layers, like conv one by one, the depth for that is right here. And so it's
initializing an nn.conf2d, which is a convolutional layer in PyTorch. And there's much of keyword
arguments here that I'm not going to explain yet. But you see how there's bias equals false.
The bias equals false is exactly for the same reason as bias is not used in our case. You see how
I raised the use of bias. And the use of bias is spurious because after this weight layer,
there's a bash normalization. And the bash normalization subtracts that bias and that has its own bias.
So there's no need to introduce these spurious parameters. It wouldn't hurt performance,
it's just useless. And so because they have this motif of conv, bash, and relu, they don't need a
bias here, because there's a bias inside here. So by the way, this example here is very easy to
find, just do resnet PyTorch. And it's this example here. So this is kind of like the stock
implementation of a residual neural network in PyTorch. And you can find that here. But of course,
I haven't covered many of these parts yet. And I would also like to briefly descend into the
definitions of these PyTorch layers and the parameters that they take. Now, instead of a
convolutional layer, we're going to look at a linear layer, because that's the one that we're
using here. This is a linear layer, and I haven't covered convolutions yet. But as I'm
mentioned, convolutions are basically linear layers, except on patches. So a linear layer
performs a wx plus b, except here they're calling the w a transpose. So the call is wx plus b,
very much like we did here. To initialize this layer, you need to know the fan in the fan out.
And that's so that they can initialize this w. This is the fan in and the fan out. So they know
how big the weight matrix should be. You need to also pass in whether or not you want a bias.
And if you set it to false, then no bias will be inside this layer. And you may want to do that
exactly like in our case, if your layer is followed by a normalization layer, such as BatchNorm.
So this allows you to basically disable bias. In terms of the initialization, if we swing down
here, this is reporting the variables used inside this linear layer. And our linear layer here has
two parameters, the weight and the bias. In the same way, they have a weight and a bias.
And they're talking about how they initialize it by default. So by default, pytorch will initialize
your weights by taking the fan in and then doing one over fan in square root. And then
instead of a normal distribution, they are using a uniform distribution. So it's very much the same
thing. But they are using a one instead of five over three. So there's no gain being calculated here.
The gain is just one. But otherwise, it's exactly one over the square root of fan in exactly as we
have here. So one over the square root of k is the scale of the weights. But when they are drawing
the numbers, they're not using a Gaussian by default. They're using a uniform distribution
by default. And so they draw uniformly from negative squared of k to squared of k. But it's the exact
same thing and the same motivation from with respect to what we've seen in this lecture. And the
reason they're doing this is if you have a roughly Gaussian input, this will ensure that out of this
layer, you will have a roughly Gaussian output. And you basically achieve that by scaling the weights
by one over the square root of fan in. So that's what this is doing. And then the second thing is
the pasteurmalization layer. So let's look at what that looks like in pytorch. So here we have a
one dimensional pasteurmalization layer exactly as we are using here. And there are a number of keyword
arguments going into it as well. So we need to know the number of features for us that is 200.
And that is needed so that we can initialize these parameters here. The gain, the bias, and the buffers
for the running mean is their deviation. Then they need to know the value of epsilon here.
And by default, this is one negative five. You don't typically change this too much.
Then they need to know the momentum. And the momentum here, as they explain, is basically used
for these running mean and running standard deviation. So by default, the momentum here is
point one. The momentum we are using here in this example is 0.001. And basically, you may want to
change this sometimes. And roughly speaking, if you have a very large batch size, then typically,
what you'll see is that when you estimate the mean and standard deviation, for every single batch
size, if it's large enough, you're going to get roughly the same result. And so therefore,
you can use slightly higher momentum like point one. But for a batch size as small as 32,
the mean and standard deviation here might take on slightly different numbers, because there's
only 32 examples we are using to estimate the mean and standard deviation. So the value is
changing around a lot. And if your momentum is 0.1, that might not be good enough for this value to
settle and converge to the actual mean and standard deviation over the entire training set.
And so basically, if your batch size is very small, momentum of 0.1 is potentially dangerous,
and it might make it so that the running mean and standard deviation is thrashing too much
during training. And it's not actually converging properly.
Alpha equals true determines whether this batch normalization layer has these learnable
alpha parameters, the gain and the bias. And this is almost always kept to true. I'm not actually
sure why you would want to change this to false. Then track running stats is determining whether or
not batch normalization layer of PyTorch will be doing this. And one reason you may want to skip
the running stats is because you may want to, for example, estimate them at the end as a stage two
like this. And in that case, you don't want the batch normalization layer to be doing all
this extra compute that you're not going to use. And finally, we need to know which device we're
going to run this batch normalization on a CPU or a GPU. And what the data type should be,
half precision, single precision, double precision, and so on. So that's the batch normalization layer.
Otherwise, they link to the paper is the same formula we've implemented, and everything is the
same exactly as we've done here. Okay, so that's everything that I wanted to cover for this lecture.
Really, what I wanted to talk about is the importance of understanding the activations and
ingredients and their statistics in neural networks. And this becomes increasingly important,
especially as you make your neural works bigger, larger and deeper. We looked at the distributions
basically at the output layer, and we saw that if you have two confident mispredictions, because
the activations are too messed up at the last layer, you can end up with these hockey stick losses.
And if you fix this, you get a better loss at the end of training, because your training is not
doing wasteful work. Then we also saw that we need to control the activations. We don't want them to
squash to zero or explode to infinity. And because that you can run into a lot of trouble with all
of these nonlinearities in these neural nets. And basically, you want everything to be fairly
homogeneous throughout the neural net. You want roughly Gaussian activations throughout the neural
net. Let me talk about, okay, if we want roughly Gaussian activations, how do we scale these weight
matrices and biases during initialization of the neural net, so that we don't get, so everything is
as controlled as possible. So that gave us a large boost in improvement. And then I talked about how
that strategy is not actually possible for much, much deeper neural nets, because when you have
much deeper neural nets with lots of different types of layers, it becomes really, really hard
to precisely set the weights and the biases in such a way that the activations are roughly uniform
throughout the neural net. So then I introduced the notion of the normalization layer. Now, there
are many normalization layers that people use in practice. Bachelors normalization, layer normalization,
consistent normalization, group normalization. We haven't covered most of them, but I've introduced
the first one. And also, the one that I believe came out first, and that's called bachelors normalization.
And we saw how bachelors normalization works. This is a layer that you can sprinkle throughout your
deep neural net. And the basic idea is if you want roughly Gaussian activations,
well, then take your activations and take the mean and the standard deviation and center your
data. And you can do that because the centering operation is differentiable. But then on top of
that, we actually had to add a lot of bells and whistles. And that gave you a sense of the
complexities of the Bachelors normalization layer, because now we're centering the data, that's great.
But suddenly, we need the gain and the bias. And now those are trainable. And then because we are
coupling all the training examples, now suddenly the question is, how do you do the inference?
Or to do the inference, we need to now estimate these mean and standard deviation once,
or the entire training set, and then use those at inference. But then no one likes to do stage two.
So instead, we fold everything into the Bachelors normalization layer during training and try to
estimate these in the running manner so that everything is a bit simpler. And that gives us
the Bachelors normalization layer. And as I mentioned, no one likes this layer. It causes a huge amount
of bugs. And intuitively, it's because it is coupling examples in the forward pass of the neural
net. And I've shocked myself in the foot with this layer over and over again in my life. And I don't
want you to suffer the same. So basically try to avoid it as much as possible. Some of the other
alternatives to these layers are for example group normalization or layer normalization. And
those have become more common in more recent deep learning. But we haven't covered those yet.
But definitely, Bachelors normalization was very influential at the time when it came out in roughly
2015. Because it was kind of the first time that you could train reliably much deeper neural nets.
And fundamentally, the reason for that is because this layer was very effective at controlling the
statistics of the activations in a neural net. So that's the story so far. And that's all I wanted
to cover. And in the future lecture, so hopefully we can start going into recurrent neural nets. And
recurrent neural nets as we'll see are just very, very deep networks. Because you unroll the loop
and when you actually optimize these neural nets. And that's where a lot of this analysis around
the activation statistics and all these normalization layers will become very, very important for good
performance. So we'll see that next time. Okay, so I lied. I would like us to do one more summary
here as a bonus. And I think it's useful as to have one more summary of everything I've presented
in this lecture. But also, I would like us to start by torturing our code a little bit. So it looks
much more like what you would encounter in PyTorch. So you'll see that I will structure our code into
these modules, like a linear module and a batch room module. And I'm putting the code inside these
modules so that we can construct neural networks very much like we would construct the in PyTorch.
And I will go through this in detail. So we'll create our neural net. Then we will do the optimization
loop as we did before. And then the one more thing that I want to do here is I want to look at the
activation statistics both in the forward pass and in the backward pass. And then here we have the
evaluation and sampling just like before. So let me rewind all the way up here and go a little bit
slower. So here I am creating a linear layer. You'll notice that Torch.nn has lots of different
types of layers. And one of those layers is the linear layer. Torch.nn. That linear takes
number of input features, output features, whether or not we should have bias. And then the device
that we want to place this layer on and the data type. So I will omit these two. But otherwise we
have the exact same thing. We have the fan in, which is the number of inputs, fan out the number of
outputs. And whether or not we want to use a bias. And internally inside this layer, there's a weight
and a bias if you like it. It is typical to initialize the weight using say random numbers
drawn from Gaussian. And then here's the coming initialization that we discussed already in this
lecture. And that's a good default. And also the default that I believe PyTorch uses.
And by default, the bias is usually initialized to zeros. Now when you call this module,
this will basically calculate W times X plus B if you have N B. And then when you also call
the parameters on this module, it will return the tensors that are the parameters of this layer.
Now next we have the Bastram Realization layer. So I've written that here. And this is very similar
to PyTorch and then dot Bastram 1D layer as shown here. So I'm kind of taking these three
parameters here, the dimensionality, the epsilon that we'll use in the division, and the momentum
that we will use in keeping track of these running stats, the running mean and the running variance.
Now PyTorch actually takes quite a few more things, but I'm assuming some of their settings.
So for us, I'll find will be true. That means that we will be using a gamma beta after the normalization.
The track running stats will be true. So we will be keeping track of the running mean and the
running variance in the in the Bastram. Our device by default is the CPU and the data type by default
is float, float 32. So those are the defaults. Otherwise, we are taking all the same parameters
in this Bastram layer. So first, I'm just saving them. Now here's something new. There's a dot
training which by default is true. And PyTorch and N modules also have this attribute, that training.
And that's because many modules in Bastram is included in that have a different behavior,
whether you are training your own or whether you are running it in an evaluation mode,
and calculating your evaluation laws or using it for inference on some test examples.
And Bastram is an example of this, because when we are training, we are going to be using the mean
and the variance estimated from the current batch. But during inference, we are using the running
mean and running variance. And so also, if we are training, we are updating mean and variance.
But if we are testing, then these are not being updated. They're kept fixed. And so this flag is
necessary and by default true, just like in PyTorch. Now the parameters of Bastram 1D are the gamma
and the beta here. And then the running mean and running variance are called buffers in PyTorch
nomenclature. And these buffers are trained using exponential moving average here explicitly.
And they are not part of the back propagation is stochastic gradient descent. So they are not
sort of like parameters of this layer. And that's why when we have a parameters here,
we only return gamma and beta. We do not return the mean and the variance. This is trained
sort of like internally here, every forward pass using exponential moving average.
So that's the initialization. Now in a forward pass, if we are training, then we use the mean
and the variance estimated by the batch, we'll upload the paper here. We calculate the mean and
the variance. Now up above, I was estimating the standard deviation and keeping track of the
standard deviation here in the running standard deviation instead of running variance. But let's
follow the paper exactly. Here they calculate the variance, which is the standard deviation squared.
And that's what's kept track of in running variance instead of a running standard deviation.
But those two would be very, very similar, I believe. If we are not training, then we use
running mean and variance. We normalize. And then here, I'm calculating the output of this layer.
And I'm also assigning it to an attribute called dot out. Now dot out is something that I'm using
in our modules here. This is not what you would find in PyTorch. We are slightly deviating from it.
I'm creating a dot out because I would like to very easily maintain all those variables so that
we can create statistics of them and plot them. But PyTorch and modules will not have a dot out
attribute. And finally, here we are updating the buffers using, again, as I mentioned,
exponential moving average, given the provided momentum. And importantly, you'll notice that
I'm using the Torch.NoGrat context manager. And I'm doing this because if we don't use this,
then PyTorch will start building out an entire computational graph out of these tensors because
it is expecting that we will eventually call a dot backward. But we are never going to be calling
dot backward on anything that includes running mean and running variance. So that's why we need
to use this context manager so that we are not sort of maintaining them using all this additional
memory. So this will make it more efficient. And it's just telling PyTorch that there will be no
backward. We just have a bunch of tensors. We want to update them. That's it. And then we return.
Okay, now scrolling down, we have the 10H layer. This is very, very similar to Torch.10H. And it
doesn't do too much. It just calculates 10H, as you might expect. So that's Torch.10H. And there's
no parameters in this layer. But because these are layers, it now becomes very easy to sort of
like stack them up into basically just a list. And we can do all the initialization that we're used
to. So we have the initial sort of embedding matrix, we have our layers, and we can call them sequentially.
And then again, with Torch.not grad, there's some initialization here. So we want to make the
output softmax a bit less confident like we saw. And in addition to that, because we are using a
six layer multi layer perception here, so you see how I'm stacking linear 10H linear 10H etc.
I'm going to be using the game here. And I'm going to play with this in a second. So you'll see how
when we change this, what happens to the statistics. Finally, the parameters are basically the embedding
matrix and all the parameters in all the layers. And notice here, I'm using a double list comprehension,
if you want to call it that, but for every layer in layers, and for every parameter in each of those
layers, we are just stacking up all those piece, all those parameters. Now in total, we have 46,000
parameters. And I'm telling PyTorch that all of them require gradient. Then here, we have everything
here we are actually mostly used to. We are sampling batch, we are doing a forward pass.
The forward pass now is just the linear application of all the layers in order,
followed by the cross entropy. And then in the backward pass, you'll notice that for every single
layer, I now iterate over all the outputs, and I'm telling PyTorch to retain the gradient of them.
And then here we are already used to all the all the gradient sent to none,
do the backward to fill in the gradients, do an update using the cast gradient sent,
and then track some statistics. And then I am going to break after a single iteration.
Now here in this cell in this diagram, I'm visualizing the histogram, the histograms of the
four pass activations. And I'm specifically doing it at the 10 each layers. So iterating over all
the layers, except for the very last one, which is basically just the softmax layer.
If it is a 10 inch layer, and I'm using a 10 inch layer just because they have a finite output,
negative one to one. And so it's very easy to visualize here. So you see negative one to one,
it's a finite range, and it's easy to work with. I take the out tensor from that layer into t,
and then I'm calculating the mean, the standard deviation, and the percent saturation of t.
And the way I define the percent saturation is that t dot absolute value is greater than 0.97.
So that means we are here at the tails of the 10 h. And remember that when we are in the tails of
the 10 h, that will actually stop gradients. So we don't want this to be too high. Now,
here I'm calling Torstot histogram. And then I am plotting this histogram. So basically what
this is doing is that every different type of layer, and they all have a different color,
we are looking at how many values in these testers take on any of the values below on this axis here.
So the first layer is fairly saturated here at 20%. So you can see that it's got tails here.
But then everything sort of stabilizes. And if we had more layers here, it would actually just
stabilize at around the standard deviation of about 0.65. And the saturation would be roughly 5%.
And the reason that this stabilizes and gives us a nice distribution here is because gain is set
to 5 over 3. Now, here, this gain, you see that by default we initialize with one over square to
fan in. But then here during initialization, I come in and I iterate over all the layers. And
if it's a linear layer, I boost that by the gain. Now we saw that one. So basically if we just
do not use a gain, then what happens? If I redraw this, you will see that the standard deviation is
shrinking, and the saturation is coming to zero. And basically what's happening is the first layer is,
you know, pretty decent. But then further layers are just kind of like shrinking down to zero.
And it's happening slowly, but it's shrinking to zero. And the reason for that is when you just
have a sandwich of linear layers alone, then a then initializing our weights in this manner,
we saw previously would have conserved the standard deviation of one. But because we have this
interspersed 10 H layers in there, these 10 linear layers are squashing functions. And so they take
your distribution and they slightly squash it. And so some gain is necessary to keep expanding it,
to fight the squashing. So it just turns out that five over three is a good value. So if we have
something too small, like one, we saw that things will come towards zero. But if it's something too
high, let's do two. Then here we see that, well, let me do something a bit more extreme, because
so it's a bit more visible, let's try three. Okay, so we see here that the saturation is
are trying to be way too large. Okay, so three with create way too saturated activations.
So five over three is a good setting for a sandwich of linear layers with 10 H activations,
and it roughly stabilizes the standard deviation at a reasonable point. Now, honestly, I have no
idea where five over three came from in PyTorch. When we were looking at the coming initialization,
I see empirically that it stabilizes this sandwich of linear and 10 H, and that the saturation is in
a good range. But I didn't actually know if this came out of some math formula. I tried searching
briefly for where this comes from, but I wasn't able to find anything. But certainly we see that
empirically, these are very nice ranges, our saturation is roughly 5%, which is a pretty good number. And
this is a good setting of the gain in this context. Similarly, we can do the exact same thing with
the gradients. So here is a very same loop, if it's a 10 H, but instead of taking the layer
that out, I'm taking the grad. And then I'm also showing the mean and the standard deviation,
and I'm plotting the histogram of these values. And so you'll see that the gradient distribution
is fairly reasonable. And in particular, what we're looking for is that all the different
layers in this sandwich has roughly the same gradient. Things are not shrinking or exploding.
So we can, for example, come here, and we can take a look at what happens if this gain was way too
small. So this was 0.5. Then you see the, first of all, the activations are shrinking to zero,
but also the gradients are doing something weird. The gradients started out here, and then now they're
like expanding out. And similarly, if we, for example, have a too high of a gain, select three,
then we see that also the gradients have, there's some asymmetry going on where as you go into
deeper and deeper layers, the activations are also changing. And so that's not what we want. And in
this case, we saw that without the use of batch room, as we are going through right now, we have to
very carefully set those gains to get nice activations in both the forward pass and the backward pass.
And before we move on to batch normalization, I would also like to take a look at what happens
when we have no 10H units here. So erasing all the 10H nonlinearities, but keeping the gain at 5/3,
we now have just a giant linear sandwich. So let's see what happens to the activations.
As we saw before, the correct gain here is one, that is the standard deviation preserving gain.
So 1.667 is too high. And so what's going to happen now is the following. I have to change this to be
linear. So we are, because there's no more 10H players. And let me change this to linear as well.
So what we're seeing is the activations started out on the blue and have by layer 4 become very
diffuse. So what's happening to the activations is this. And with the gradients on the top layer,
the activation, the gradient statistics are the purple, and then they diminish as you go down
deeper than the layers. And so basically you have an asymmetry like in the neural net. And you might
imagine that if you have very deep neural networks, say like 50 layers or something like that,
this just, this is not a good place to be. So that's why before that normalization, this was
an incredibly tricky to set. In particular, if this is too large of a gain, this happens.
And if it's too little of a gain, then this happens. Also the opposite of that basically
happens. Here we have a shrinking and a diffusion, depending on which direction you look at it from.
And so certainly this is not what you want. And in this case, the correct setting of the gain is
exactly one, just like we're doing at initialization. And then we see that the statistics for the
forward and the backward pass are well-paid. And so the reason I want to show you this is
that basically like getting neural nets to train before these normalization layers,
and before the use of advanced optimizers like Adam, which we still have to cover,
and residual connections and so on, training neural nets basically look like this. It's like a
total balancing act. You have to make sure that everything is precisely orchestrated,
and you have to care about the activations and the gradients and their statistics,
and then maybe you can train something. But it was basically impossible to train very deep
networks. And this is fundamentally the reason for that. You'd have to be very, very careful
with your initialization. The other point here is you might be asking yourself, by the way,
I'm not sure if I covered this, why do we need these 10H layers at all? Why do we include them,
and then have to worry about the gain? And the reason for that, of course, is that if you just
have a stack of linear layers, then certainly we're getting very easily nice activations and so on.
But this is just a massive linear sandwich, and it turns out that it collapses to a single
linear layer in terms of its representation power. So if you were to plot the output as a
function of the input, you're just getting a linear function. No matter how many linear
layers you stack up, you still just end up with a linear transformation. All the Wx plus Bs
just collapse into a large Wx plus B with slightly different Ws, as likely different B.
But interestingly, even though the forward pass collapses to just a linear layer,
because of back propagation and the dynamics of the backward pass, the optimization is really
not identical. You actually end up with all kinds of interesting dynamics in the backward pass,
because of the way the chain rule is calculating it. And so optimizing a linear layer by itself,
and optimizing a sandwich of 10 linear layers, in both cases those are just a linear transformation
in the forward pass, but the training dynamics would be different. And there's entire papers
that analyze, in fact, like infinitely layered linear layers and so on. And so there's a lot of
things too that you can play with there. But basically the 10 H null linearities allow us to
turn this sandwich from just a linear function into a neural network that can, in principle,
approximate any arbitrary function. Okay, so now I've reset the code to use the linear
10 H sandwich like before. And I reset everything. So the gains five over three,
we can run a single step of optimization, and we can look at the activation statistics of the
forward pass and the backward pass. But I've added one more plot here that I think is really
important to look at when you're training your neural nets and to consider. And ultimately,
what we're doing is we're updating the parameters of the neural net. So we care about the parameters
and their values and their gradients. So here what I'm doing is I'm actually iterating over all
the parameters available, and then I'm only restricting it to the two dimensional parameters,
which are basically the weights of these linear layers. And I'm skipping the biases, and I'm skipping
the gammas and the betas in the bathroom just for simplicity. But you can also take a look at
those as well. But what's happening with the weights is instructive by itself. So here we have
all the different weights, their shapes. So this is the embedding layer, the first linear layer,
all the way to the very last linear layer. And then we have the mean, the standard deviation
of all these parameters, the histogram. And you can see that actually doesn't look that amazing.
So there's some trouble in paradise, even though these gradients looked okay,
there's something weird going on here. I'll get to that in a second. And the last thing here is the
gradient to data ratio. So sometimes I like to visualize this as well, because what this gets
you a sense of is what is the scale of the gradient compared to the scale of the actual values.
And this is important because we're going to end up taking a step update that is the learning rate
times the gradient onto the data. And so the gradient has too large of magnitude. If the numbers
in there are too large compared to the numbers in data, then you'd be in trouble. But in this case,
the gradient to data is our low numbers. So the values inside grad are 1000 times smaller than
the values inside data in these weights, most of them. Now, notably, that is not true about the last
layer. And so the last layer actually here, the output layer is a bit of a troublemaker in the
way that this is currently arranged, because you can see that the last layer here in pink takes
on values that are much larger than some of the values inside the neural net. So the standard
deviations are roughly one in negative three throughout, except for the last layer, which
actually has roughly one in negative two standard deviation gradients. And so the gradients on the
last layer are currently about 100 times greater, sorry, 10 times greater than all the other weights
inside the neural net. And so that's problematic, because in the simplest stochastic gradient in the
sense setup, you would be training this last layer about 10 times faster than you would be
training the other layers at initialization. Now this actually like kind of fixes itself a little
bit if you train for a bit longer. So for example, if I agree, then 1000, only then do a break. Let
me reinitialize. And then let me do it 1000 steps. And after 1000 steps, we can look at the forward
pass. Okay, so you see how the neurons are bit are saturating a bit. And we can also look at the
backward pass. But otherwise they look good, they're about equal. And there's no shrinking to zero
or exploding to infinity's. And you can see that here in the weights, things are also stabilizing
a little bit. So their tails of the last pink layer are actually coming down coming in during
the optimization. But certainly this is like a little bit troubling, especially if you are using
a very simple update rule likes stochastic gradient descent, instead of a modern optimizer like
Adam. Now I'd like to show you one more plot that I usually look at when I train your own networks.
And basically the gradient to data ratio is not actually that informative, because what matters
at the end is not the gradient data ratio, but the update to the data ratio, because that is the
amount by which we will actually change the data in these tensors. So coming up here, what I'd like
to do is I'd like to introduce a new update to data ratio. It's going to be less than we're going
to build it out every single iteration. And here I'd like to keep track of basically the ratio
every single iteration. So without any gradients, I'm comparing the update, which is learning
great times the times the gradient. That is the update that we're going to apply to every parameter.
So see I'm entering over all the parameters. And then I'm taking the basically standard deviation
of the update we're going to apply and divided by the actual content, the data of that parameter
and its standard deviation. So this is the ratio of basically how great are the updates to the
values in these tensors. Then we're going to take a log of it. And actually I'd like to take a log 10
just so it's a nicer visualization. So we're going to be basically looking at the exponents of the
of this division here. And then that item to pop out the float. And we're going to be keeping
track of this for all the parameters and adding it to this UD tensor. So now let me re-inertilize
and run 1000 iterations. We can look at the activations, the gradients, and the parameter
gradients as we did before. But now I have one more plot here to introduce. And what's happening
here is we're every interval of parameters. And I'm constraining it again, like I did here to just
two weights. So the number of dimensions in these sensors is two. And then I'm basically plotting
all of these update ratios over time. So when I plot this, I plot those ratios and you can see
that they evolve over time during initialization to take on certain values. And then these updates
are like start stabilizing usually during training. Then the other thing that I'm plotting here is
I'm plotting here like an approximate value that is a rough guide for what it roughly should be.
And it should be like roughly one in negative three. And so that means that basically there's
some values in this tensor and they take on certain values. And the updates to them at every single
iteration are no more than roughly 1000 of the actual like magnitude in those tensors.
If this was much larger, like for example, if this was if the log of this was like say
negative one, this is actually updating those values quite a lot. They're undergoing a lot of change.
But the reason that the final rate, the final layer here is an outlier is because this layer was
artificially shrunk down to keep the softmax incompetent. So here, you see how we multiply the
weight by point one in the initialization to make the last layer prediction less confident.
That made that artificially made the values inside that tensor way too low. And that's why we're
getting temporarily a very high ratio. But you see that that stabilizes over time once that
weight starts to learn, starts to learn. But basically, I like to look at the evolution of this
update ratio for all my parameters, usually. And I like to make sure that it's not too much
above one in negative three roughly. So around negative three on this log plot.
If it's below negative three, usually that means that parameters are not training fast enough.
So if our learning rate was very low, let's do that experiment. Let's initialize. And then let's
actually do a learning rate of say one in negative three here. So 0.001. If your learning rate is way too low,
this plot will typically reveal it. So you see how all of these updates are way too small. So the
size of the update is basically 10,000 times in magnitude to the size of the numbers in that
tensor in the first place. So this is a symptom of training way too slow. So this is another way to
sometimes start to learn rate and to get a sense of what that learning rate should be. And ultimately,
this is something that you would keep track of. If anything, the learning rate here is a little bit
on the higher side, because you see that we're above the black line of negative three, we're
somewhere around negative 2.5. It's like, okay, and but everything is like somewhat stabilizing.
And so this looks like a pretty decent setting of learning rates and so on. But this is something
to look at. And when things are miscalibrated, you will see very quickly. So for example,
everything looks pretty well behaved, right? But just as a comparison, when things are not
properly calibrated, what does that look like? Let me come up here and let's say that for example,
what do we do? Let's say that we forgot to apply this fan in normalization. So the weights inside
the linear layers are just a sample from a Gaussian in all those stages. What happens to our, how do
we notice that something's off? Well, the activation plot will tell you whoa, your neurons are way too
saturated. The gradients are going to be all messed up. The histogram for these weights are going to be
all messed up as well. And there's a lot of asymmetry. And then if we look here, I suspect it's all
going to be also a pretty messed up. So you see, there's a lot of discrepancy in how fast these
layers are learning. And some of them are learning way too fast. So negative one, negative 1.5,
those are very large numbers in terms of this ratio. Again, you should be somewhere around
negative three and not much more about that. So this is how miss calibrations of your neural
notes are going to manifest. And these kinds of plots here are a good way of sort of bringing
those miss calibrations sort of to your attention. And so you can address them. Okay, so so far,
we've seen that when we have this linear 10H sandwich, we can actually precisely calibrate the
gains and make the activations, the gradients and the parameters and the updates all look pretty
decent. But it definitely feels a little bit like balancing of a pencil on your finger. And that's
because this gain has to be very precisely calibrated. So now let's introduce Bachelors
and Shillers into the fix into the mix. Let's see how that pops fix the problem. So here,
I'm going to take the Bachelors and 1D class, and I'm going to start placing it inside. And as I
mentioned before, the standard typical place you would place it is between the linear layer. So
right after it, but before the nonlinearity. But people have definitely played with that. And
in fact, you can get very similar results, even if you place it after the nonlinearity.
And the other thing that I wanted to mention is this totally fine to also place it at the end
after the last linear layer and before the loss function. So this is potentially fine as well.
And in this case, this would be output, would be vocab size.
Now, because the last layer is a best room, we would not be changing to wait to make the
softmax less confident. We'd be changing the gamma. Because gamma, remember in the
best room is the variable that multiplicatively interacts with the output of that normalization.
So we can initialize this sandwich now, we can train, and we can see that the activations are
going to of course look very good. And they are going to necessarily look at because now
before every single 10H layer, there is a normalization in the bachelor. So this is
unsurprisingly all looks pretty good. It's going to be standard deviation of roughly 0.65,
2% and roughly equal standard deviation throughout the entire layers. So everything looks very
homogeneous. The gradients look good, the weights look good, and their distributions.
And then the updates also look pretty reasonable. We're going above -3 a little bit, but not by
too much. So all the parameters are training in roughly the same rate here.
But now what we've gained is we are going to be slightly less
brittle with respect to the gain of these. So for example, I can make the gain be say 0.2 here,
which is much slower than when we had with the 10H. But as we'll see, the activations will
actually be exactly unaffected. And that's because of again this explicit normalization.
The gradients are going to look okay, the weight gradients are going to look okay.
But actually the updates will change. And so even though the forward and backward pass to a very
large extent look okay, because of the backward pass of the batch norm and how the scale of the
incoming activations interacts in the batch norm and its backward pass, this is actually changing
the scale of the updates on these parameters. So the gradients of these weights are affected.
So we still don't get it completely free pass to pass in arbitrary weights here, but everything
else is significantly more robust in terms of the forward, backward, and the weight gradients.
It's just that you may have to retune your learning rate if you are changing sufficiently the scale
of the activations that are coming into the batch norms. So here for example, we changed
the gains of these linear layers to be greater. And we're seeing that the updates are coming out
lower as a result. And then finally, we can also if we are using batch norms, we don't actually
need to necessarily let me reset this to one. So there's no gain. We don't necessarily even have to
normalize back then in sometimes. So if I take out the fan in, so these are just now random Gaussian,
we'll see that because of batch norm, this will actually be relatively well behaved. So
this is a look of course in the forward pass look good. The gradients look good. The backward
weight updates look okay, a little bit of fat tails on some of the layers. And this looks
okay as well. But as you as you can see, we're significantly below negative three, so we'd have
to bump up the learning rate of this batch norm so that we are training more properly. And in
particular, looking at this roughly looks like we have to 10x the learning rate to get to about
one in negative three. So we come here and we would change this to be update of 1.0. And if
you're not really initialized, then we'll see that everything still of course looks good.
And now we are roughly here and we expect this to be an okay training run. So long story short,
we are significantly more robust to the gain of these linear layers, whether or not we have to
apply the fan in. And then we can change the gain, but we actually do have to worry a little bit
about the update scales and making sure that the learning rate is properly calibrated here.
But the activations of the forward backward pass and the updates are all are looking significantly
more well behaved, except for the global scale that is potentially being adjusted here.
Okay, so now let me summarize. There are three things I was hoping to achieve with this section.
Number one, I wanted to introduce you to Bachelors normalization, which is one of the first
modern innovations that we're looking into that helped stabilize very deep neural networks and
their training. And I hope you understand how the Bachelors organization works and how it would
be used in your own network. Number two, I was hoping to pytorchify some of our code and wrap it up
into these modules. So like linear, Bachelors 1D, 10H, etc. These are layers or modules and they
can be stacked up into neural nets like Lego building blocks. And these layers actually exist
in pytorch. And if you import torch and then then you can actually, the way I've constructed it,
you can simply just use pytorch by prepending an end dot to all these different layers.
And actually everything will just work because the API that I've developed here is identical to
the API that pytorch uses. And the implementation also is basically as far as I'm aware, identical
to the one in pytorch. And number three, I tried to introduce you to the diagnostic tools that you
would use to understand whether your neural network is in a good state dynamically. So we are looking
at the statistics and histograms and activation of the forward pass activation activations,
the backward pass gradients. And then also we're looking at the weights that are going to be
updated as part of stochastic gradient ascent. And we're looking at their means, standard deviations,
and also the ratio of gradients to data, or even better, the updates to data. And we saw that
typically we don't actually look at it as a single snapshot frozen in time at some particular
iteration. Typically, people look at this as a overtime, just like I've done here. And they look
at these updated data ratios and they make sure everything looks okay. And in particular, I said
that one in negative three, or basically negative three on the log scale is a good,
rough heuristic for what you want this ratio to be. And if it's way too high, then probably the
learning rate or the updates are a little too big. And if it's way too small, then the learning rate
is probably too small. So that's just some of the things that you may want to play with when you try
to get your neural network to work very well. Now, there's a number of things I did not try to
achieve. I did not try to beat our previous performance as an example by introducing the
bathroom layer. Actually, I did try. And I found that I used the learning rate finding mechanism
that I've described before. I tried to train the bachelor layer, a bachelor neural net. And I
actually ended up with results that are very, very similar to what we've obtained before.
And that's because our performance now is not bottlenecked by the optimization,
which is what Bachelorm is helping with. The performance at the stage is bottlenecked by
what I suspect is the context length of our context. So currently we are taking three
characters to predict the fourth one. And I think we need to go beyond that. And we need to look
at more powerful architectures, like recurrent neural networks and transformers in order to further
push the lock probabilities that we're achieving on this data set. And I also did not try to have a
full explanation of all of these activations, the gradients and the backward pass and the statistics
of all these gradients. And so you may have found some of the parts here unintuitive. And maybe you
were slightly confused about, okay, if I change the gain here, how come that we need a different
learning rate? And I didn't go into the full detail, because you'd have to actually look at the
backward pass of all these different layers and get an intuitive understanding of how all that works.
And I did not go into that in this lecture. The purpose really was just to introduce you to the
diagnostic tools and what they look like. But there's still a lot of work remaining on the intuitive
level to understand the initialization, the backward pass and how all of that interacts.
But you shouldn't feel too bad, because honestly, we are getting to the cutting edge of where the
field is. We certainly haven't, I would say, solved initialization. And we haven't solved
back propagation. And these are still very much an active area of research. People are still trying
to figure out where's the best way to initialize these networks? What is the best update rule to use?
And so on. So none of this is really solved. And we don't really have all the answers to all the,
to all these cases. But at least we're making progress. And at least we have some tools to tell
us whether or not things are on the right track for now. So I think we've made positive progress
in this lecture. And I hope you enjoyed that. And I will see you next time.