Hi everyone. So today we are once again continuing our implementation of make more.
Now so far we've come up to here multilial perceptrons and our neural net looked like this
and we were implementing this over the last few lectures. Now I'm sure everyone is very excited
to go into recurrent neural networks and all of their variants and how they work and the diagrams
look cool and it's very exciting and interesting and we're going to get a better result. But unfortunately
I think we have to remain here for one more lecture and the reason for that is we've already
trained this multilial perceptron right and we are getting pretty good loss and I think we have a
pretty decent understanding of the architecture and how it works but the line of code here that I
take an issue with is here, lost up backward. That is we are taking a pytorch autograph and using
it to calculate all of our gradients along the way and I would like to remove the use of lost up
backward and I would like us to write our backward pass manually on the level of tensors and I think
that this is a very useful exercise for the following reasons. I actually have an entire blog post on
this topic but I like to call backpropagation a leaky abstraction and what I mean by that is
backpropagation doesn't just make your neural networks just work magically. It's not the case
that you can just stack up arbitrary LEGO blocks of differentiable functions and just cross your
fingers and back propagate and everything is great. Things don't just work automatically. It is a
leaky abstraction in the sense that you can shoot yourself in a foot if you do not understanding
its internals. It will magically not work or not work optimally and you will need to understand
how it works under the hood if you're hoping to debug it and if you are hoping to address it in
your neural nut. So this blog post here from a while ago goes into some of those examples.
So for example we've already covered them some of them already. For example the flat tails of
these functions and how you do not want to saturate them too much because your gradients will die.
The case of dead neurons which I've already covered as well. The case of exploding or vanishing
gradients in the case of a current neural networks which we are about to cover. And then also you
will often come across some examples in the wild. This is a snippet that I found in a random code
based on the internet where they actually have like a very subtle but pretty major bug in their
implementation. And the bug points at the fact that the author of this code does not actually
understand back propagation. So what they're trying to do here is they're trying to clip the loss
at a certain maximum value. But actually what they're trying to do is they're trying to clip
the gradients to have a maximum value instead of trying to clip the loss at a maximum value.
And indirectly they're basically causing some of the outliers to be actually ignored. Because
when you clip a loss of an outlier you are setting its gradient to zero. And so have a look through
this and read through it. But there's basically a bunch of subtle issues that you're going to
avoid if you actually know what you're doing. And that's why I don't think it's the case that
because PyTorch or other frameworks offer autograd it is okay for us to ignore how it works.
Now we've actually already covered autograd and we wrote micrograd. But micrograd was an autograd
engine only on the level of individual scalars. So the atoms were single individual numbers.
And you know I don't think it's enough and I'd like us to basically think about back propagation
on level of tensors as well. And so in a summary I think it's a good exercise. I think it is very
very valuable. You're going to become better at debugging neural networks and making sure that
you understand what you're doing. It is going to make everything fully explicit so you're not
going to be nervous about what is hidden away from you. And basically in general we're going to
emerge stronger. And so let's get into it. A bit of a fun historical note here is that today
writing your backward pass by hand and manually is not recommended and no one does it except for
the purposes of exercise. But about 10 years ago in deep learning this was fairly standard and in
fact pervasive. So at the time everyone used to write their backward pass by hand manually,
including myself. And it's just what you would do. So we used to write backward pass by hand and
now everyone just called lost a backward. We've lost something. I wanted to give you a few examples
of this. So here's a 2006 paper from Jeff Hinton and Russell Select Enough in science that was
influential at the time. And this was training some architectures called restricted bolts and
machines. And basically it's an auto encoder trained here. And this is from roughly 2010.
I had a library for training restricted bolts and machines. And this was at the time written in
MATLAB. So Python was not used for deep learning pervasively. It was all MATLAB. And MATLAB was
this scientific computing package that everyone would use. So we would write MATLAB, which is
barely a programming language in a big as well. But it had a very convenient tensor class. And it
was this computing environment and you would run here, it would all run on the CPU of course,
but you would have very nice plots to go with it and a built-in debugger. And it was pretty nice.
Now the code in this package in 2010 that I wrote for fitting researchable machines,
to a large extent is recognizable. But I wanted to show you how you would,
well, I'm creating the data and the XY batches. I'm initializing the neural nut. So it's got weights
and biases just like we're used to. And then this is the training loop where we actually do the
forward pass. And then here, at this time, they didn't even necessarily use back propagation to
train neural networks. So this in particular implements contrastive divergence, which estimates
a gradient. And then here we take that gradient and use it for a parameter update along lines
that we're used to. Yeah, here. But you can see that basically people are meddling with these
gradients directly and inline and themselves. It wasn't that common to use an autograd engine.
Here's one more example from a paper of mine from 2014 called the fragment embeddings.
And here what I was doing is I was aligning images and text. And so it's kind of like a clip if
you're familiar with it. But instead of working on the level of entire images and entire sentences,
it was working on the level of individual objects and little pieces of sentences. And I was embedding
them and then calculating a very much like a clip like loss. And I dug up the code from 2014
of how I implemented this. And it was already in numpy and Python. And here I'm implementing the
cost function. And it was standards to implement not just the cost, but also the backward pass
manually. So here I'm calculating the image embeddings, sentence embeddings, the last function
I calculate this course. This is the last function. And then once I have the last function,
I do the backward pass right here. So I backward through the loss function and through the neural
net and I append regularization. So everything was done by hand manually. And you were just right
out the backward pass. And then you would use a gradient checker to make sure that your numerical
estimate of the gradient agrees with the one you calculated during back propagation. So this
was very standard for a long time. But today, of course, it is standard to use an autograph engine.
But it was definitely useful. And I think people sort of understood how these neural networks work
on a very intuitive level. And so I think it's a good exercise again. And this is where we want to
be. Okay, so just as a reminder from our previous lecture, this is the Jupyter Notebook that we
implemented at the time. And we're going to keep everything the same. So we're still going to have
a two layer multialing perception with a batch normalization layer. So the forward pass will be
basically identical to this lecture. But here we're going to get rid of loss.backward. And instead,
we're going to write the backward pass manually. Now here's the starter code for this lecture.
We are becoming a back prop ninja in this notebook. And the first few cells here are identical to
what we are used to. So we are doing some imports loading the data set and processing the data set.
None of this changed. Now here, I'm introducing a utility function that we're going to use later
to compare the gradients. So in particular, we are going to have the gradients that we estimate
manually ourselves. And we're going to have gradients that PyTorch calculates. And we're going to be
checking for correctness, assuming of course that PyTorch is correct. Then here, we have the
initialization that we are quite used to. So we have our embedding table for the characters,
the first layer, second layer, and a batch normalization in between. And here's where we create all the
parameters. Now you will note that I changed the initialization a little bit to be small numbers.
So normally you would set the biases to be all zero. Here I am setting them to be small random
numbers. And I'm doing this because if your variables are initialized to exactly zero,
sometimes what can happen is that can mask an incorrect implementation of a gradient.
Because when everything is zero, it sort of simplifies and gives you a much simpler expression
of the gradient than you would otherwise get. And so by making it small numbers, I'm trying to
unmask those potential errors in these calculations. You also notice that I'm using B1 in the first
layer. I'm using a bias despite batch normalization right afterwards. So this would typically not be
what you do because we talked about the fact that you don't need a bias. But I'm doing this here
just for fun, because we're going to have a gradient with respect to it. And we can check that we are
still calculating it correctly, even though this bias is asparious. So here I'm calculating a single
batch. And then here I am doing a forward pass. Now you'll notice that the forward pass is significantly
expanded from what we are used to. Here the forward pass was just here. Now the reason that the forward
pass is longer is for two reasons. Number one here, we just had an F dot cross entropy. But here I
am bringing back a explicit implementation the loss function. And number two, I've broken up the
implementation into manageable chunks. So we have a lot, a lot more intermediate tensors along the way
in the forward pass. And that's because we are about to go backwards and calculate the gradients
in this back propagation from the bottom to the top. So we're going to go upwards. And just like
we have, for example, the lock props tensor in a forward pass, in a backward pass, we're going to
have a D lock props, which is going to store the derivative of the loss with respect to the lock
props tensor. And so we're going to be pretending D to every one of these tensors and calculating it
along the way of this back propagation. So as an example, we have a B and raw here, we're going to
be calculating a DB and raw. So here I'm telling PyTorch that we want to retain the grad of all
these intermediate values, because here in exercise one, we're going to calculate the backward pass.
So we're going to calculate all these D variables and use the CMP function I've introduced above
to check our correctness with respect to what PyTorch is telling us. This is going to be
exercise one where we sort of back propagate through this entire graph. Now, just to give you a very
quick preview of what's going to happen in exercise two and below, here we have fully broken up the
loss and back propagated through it manually in all the little atomic pieces that make it up.
But here we're going to collapse the loss into a single cross entropy call. And instead,
we're going to analytically derive using math and paper and pencil, the gradient of the loss with
respect to the logits. And instead of back propagating through all of its little chunks one at a time,
we're just going to analytically drive what that gradient is. And we're going to implement that,
which is much more efficient, as we'll see in a bit. Then we're going to do the exact same thing
for batch normalization. So instead of breaking up batch norm into all the tiny components,
we're going to use a pen and paper and mathematics and calculus to derive the gradient through the
batch, the batch norm layer. So we're going to calculate the backward pass through batch
norm layer in a much more efficient expression, instead of back propagating through all of its
little pieces independently. So it's going to be exercise three. And then exercise four,
we're going to put it all together. And this is the full code of training, this two layer MLP.
And we're going to basically insert our manual backdrop. We're going to take out
loss the backward. And you will basically see that you can get all the same results using
fully your own code. And the only thing we're using from PyTorch is the torch.tensor to make
the calculations efficient. But otherwise, you will understand fully what needs to forward and
backward in your own and train it. And I think that'll be awesome. So let's get to it. Okay, so I ran
all the cells of this notebook all the way up to here. And I'm going to erase this. And I'm going
to start implementing backward pass, starting with the lock problems. So we want to understand
what should go here to calculate the gradient of the loss with respect to all the elements of the
lockprops tensor. Now, I'm going to give away the answer here. But I want to put a quick note here
that I think would be most pedagogically useful for you is to actually go into the description of
this video and find the link to this Jupyter notebook. You can find it both on GitHub, but you can
also find Google collab with it. So you don't have to install anything, you'll just go to a website
on Google collab. And you can try to implement these derivatives or gradients yourself. And then
if you are not able to come to my video and see me do it. And so work in tandem and try to first
yourself and then see me give away the answer. And I think that would be most valuable to you. And
that's how I recommend you go through this lecture. So we are starting here with the lockprops. Now,
the lockprops will hold the derivative of the loss with respect to all the elements of lockprops.
What is inside lockprops? The shape of this is 32 by 27. So it's not going to surprise you that
the lockprops should also be an array of size 32 by 27. Because we want the derivative of the loss
with respect to all of its elements. So the sizes of those are always going to be equal.
Now, how does lockprops influence the loss? Okay, loss is negative lockprops indexed
with range of n and yb and then the mean of that. Now, just as a reminder, yb is just basically an
array of all the correct indices. So what we're doing here is we're taking the lockprops array of
size 32 by 27. Right. And then we are going in every single row. And in each row, we are plugging
plugging out the index eight and then 14 and 15 and so on. So we're going down the rows,
that's the iterator range of n. And then we are always plugging out the index of the column
specified by this tensor yb. So in the zero throw, we are taking the eighth column. In the first row,
we're taking the 14th column, etc. And so lockprops at this plucks out all those
lock probabilities of the correct next character in a sequence. So that's what that does. And the
shape of this or the size of it is of course 32, because our batch size is 32. So these elements
get plucked out and then their mean and the negative of that becomes loss. So I always like to work
with simpler examples to understand the numerical form of derivative. What's going on here is once
we've plucked out these examples, we're taking the mean and then the negative. So the loss basically,
if I can write it this way is the negative of say a plus b plus c. And the mean of those three
numbers would be say negative with divide three. That would be how we achieve the mean of three
numbers a, b, c, although we actually have 32 numbers here. And so what is basically the loss
by say like dA, right? Well, if we simplify this expression mathematically, this is negative 1
over 3 of a and negative plus negative 1 over 3 of b plus negative 1 over 3 of c. And so what is
d loss by dA? It's just negative 1 over 3. And so you can see that if we don't just have a b and c,
but we have 32 numbers, then d loss by d, you know, every one of those numbers is going to be 1 over
n more generally, because n is the size of the batch 32 in this case. So d loss by d lockprobs
is negative 1 over n in all these places. Now, what about the other elements inside lockprobs?
Because lockprobs is large array. You see that lockprobs are checked is 32 by 27, but only 32 of
them participate in the loss calculation. So what's the derivative of all the other most of the
elements that do not get plucked out here? Well, their loss intuitively is zero. Sorry,
their gradient intuitively is zero. And that's because they did not participate in the loss.
So most of these numbers inside this tensor does not feed into the loss. And so if we were to change
these numbers, then the loss doesn't change, which is the equivalent of saying that the
rate of the loss with respect to them is zero. They don't impact it. So here's a way to implement
this derivative then. We start out with torched at zeros of shape 32 by 27, or let's just say,
instead of doing this, because we don't want to hardcode numbers, let's do torched at zeros
like lockprobs. So basically, this is going to create an array of zeros exactly in the shape of
lockprobs. And then we need to set the derivative of negative 1 over n inside exactly these locations.
So here's what we can do. The lockprobs indexed in the identical way
will be just set to negative 1 over 0 divide n,
right, just like we derived here. So now let me erase all of these reasoning. And then this is
the candidate derivative for the lockprobs. Let's uncomment the first line and check that this is correct.
Okay, so CMP ran and let's go back to CMP. And you see that what it's doing is it's calculating if
the calculated value by us, which is dt, is exactly equal to t dot grad as calculated by
pytorch. And then this is making sure that all the elements are exactly equal,
and then converting this to a single Boolean value, because we don't want to Boolean tensor,
we just want to Boolean value. And then here, we are making sure that, okay, if they're not
exactly equal, maybe they are approximately equal because of some floating point issues,
but they're very, very close. So here we are using torched at all close, which has a little bit of a
wiggle available, because sometimes you can get very, very close. But if you use a slightly
different calculation, because of floating point arithmetic, you can get a slightly different result.
So this is checking if you get an approximately close result. And then here we are checking the
maximum, basically the value that has the highest difference, and what is the difference, and the
absolute value difference between those two. And so we are printing whether we have an exact equality,
an approximate equality, and what is the largest difference. And so here, we see that we actually
have exact equality. And so therefore, of course, we also have an approximate equality. And the
maximum difference is exactly zero. So basically, our delock props is exactly equal to what pytorch
calculated to be log props dot grad in its back propagation. So so far, we're doing pretty well.
Okay, so let's now continue our back propagation. We have that log props depends on props through
a log. So all the elements of props are being element wise applied log two. Now if we want deep
props, then remember your micro graph training, we have like a log node, it takes in props and
creates log props. And deep props will be the local derivative of that individual operation log
times the derivative loss with respect to its output, which in this case is delock props.
So what is the local derivative of this operation? Well, we are taking log element wise,
and we can come here and we can see, well, from all five's your friend, that d by dx of log of x
is just simply one over x. So therefore, in this case, x is problems. So we have d by dx is one over
x, which is one of our problems. And then this is the local derivative. And then times, we want to
chain it. So this is chain rule, time to do log props. Then let me uncomment this and let me run
the cell in place. And we see that the derivative of props as we calculated here is exactly correct.
And so notice here how this works, props that are props is going to be inverted and then
element wise, multiplied here. So if your props is very, very close to one, that means your network
is currently predicting the character correctly, then this will become one over one and delock
props is just passed through. But if your probabilities are incorrectly assigned, so if the correct
character here is getting a very low probability, then 1.0 dividing by it will boost this and then
multiply by the all props. So basically, what this line is doing intuitively is it's taking the
examples that have a very low probability currently assigned, and it's boosting their gradient.
You can again look at it that way. Next up is count some imp. So we want the river of this.
Now let me just pause here and kind of introduce what's happening here in general, because I know
it's a little bit confusing. We have the logis that come out of the neural net. Here what I'm doing
is I'm finding the maximum in each row, and I'm subtracting it for the purpose of numerical stability.
And we talked about how if you do not do this, you run these numerical issues of some of the logits
take on two large values, because we end up exponentiating them. So this is done just for safety numerically.
Then here's the exponentiation of all the sort of like logits to create our counts.
And then we want to take the sum of these counts and normalize so that all the props sum to one.
Now here, instead of using one over count sum, I use raise to the power of negative one.
Mathematically, they are identical. I just found that there's something wrong with the
pytorch implementation of the backward pass of division. And it gives like a real result,
but that doesn't happen for star star negative one. So I'm using this formula instead. But basically,
all that's happening here is we got the logits, we want to exponentiate all of them, and we want
to normalize the counts to create our probabilities. It's just that it's happening across multiple lines.
So now here, we want to first take the derivative, we want to back propagate into counts a minute,
and then into counts as well. So what should be the count sum? Now we actually have to be careful
here, because we have to scrutinize and be careful with the shapes. So counts that shape,
and then counts some in that shape are different. So in particular, counts as 32 by 27, but this
counts some in is 32 by one. And so in this multiplication here, we also have an implicit
broadcasting that pytorch will do, because it needs to take this column tensor of 32 numbers
and replicate it horizontally 27 times to align these two tensors so it can do an element
twice multiply. So really what this looks like is the following using a toy example again.
What we really have here is just props is counts times consummables. So it's a equals a times b,
but a is three by three, and b is just three by one, a column tensor. And so pytorch internally
replicated this elements of b, and it did that across all the columns. So for example, b1,
which is a first element of b, would be replicated here across all the columns in this multiplication.
And now we're trying to back propagate through this operation to count some in.
So when we are calculating this derivative, it's important to realize that these two,
this looks like a single operation, but actually it's two operations applied sequentially. The first
operation that pytorch did is it took this column tensor and replicated it across all the,
across all the columns basically 27 times. So that's the first operation, it's a replication.
And then the second operation is the multiplication. So let's first back wrap through the multiplication.
If these two arrays were of the same size, and we just have a and b,
both of them three by three, then how do we, how do we back propagate through a multiplication?
So if you just have scalars and not tensors, then if you have c equals a times b, then what is
the root of the of c with respect to b? Well, it's just a. And so that's the local derivative.
So here in our case, I'm doing the multiplication and back propagate through just the multiplication
itself, which is element wise, is going to be the local derivative, which in this case is simply
counts, because counts is the a. So it's the local derivative, and then times because the chain rule
deprops. So this here is the derivative or the gradient, but with respect to replicated b.
But we don't have a replicated b, we just have a single b column. So how do we now back propagate
through the replication? And intuitively, this b one is the same variable, and it's just reused
multiple times. And so you can look at it as being equivalent to a case wave encountered in
micrograd. And so here, I'm just pulling out a random graph we used in micrograd. We had an
example where a single node has its output feeding into two branches of basically the graph.
Until the last function. And we're talking about how the correct thing to do in the backward pass
is we need to sum all the gradients that arrive at any one note. So across these different branches,
the gradients would sum. So if a note is used multiple times, the gradients for all of its uses
sum during back propagation. So here b one is used multiple times in all these columns. And
therefore, the right thing to do here is to sum horizontally across all the rows. So to sum
in dimension one, but we want to retain this dimension so that the so that counts them in,
and its gradient are going to be exactly the same shape. So we want to make sure that we keep them
is true. So we don't lose this dimension. And this will make the counts on him be exactly shape 32
by one. So revealing this comparison as well and running this, we see that we get an exact match.
So this derivative is exactly correct. And let me erase this. Now let's also back propagate into
counts, which is the other variable here to create props. So from props to count some
info, we just did that, let's go into counts as well. So the counts will be
decouces are a. So dc by d a is just b. So therefore it's count some info. And then times chain rule
d props. Now, count some info is 32 by one. D props is 32 by 27. So those will broadcast fine
and will give us decouces. There's no additional summation required here. There will be a broadcasting
that happens in this multiply here, because count some info needs to be replicated again
to correctly multiply d props. But that's going to give the correct result. So as far as this single
operation is concerned, so we've backed up here from props to counts, but we can't actually check
the derivative of counts. I have it much later on. And the reason for that is because count some info
depends on counts. And so there's a second branch here that we have to finish, because count some
info back propagates into count some and count some will back propagate into counts. And so counts
is a node that is being used twice. It's used right here into props, and it goes through this other
branch through count some info. So even though we've calculated the first contribution of it,
we still have to calculate the second contribution of it later. Okay, so we're continuing with this
branch. We have the derivative for count some info. Now we want the derivative counts some.
So decount some equals, what is the local derivative of this operation? So this is basically an element
wise one over counts some. So count some race to the power of negative one is the same as
one over count some. If we go to Wolfram alpha, we see that x is negative one d by d by d x of it
is basically negative x to the negative two, right? One negative one over square is the same as
negative x to the negative two. So decount some here will be local derivative is going to be negative
counts some to the negative two. That's the local derivative times chain rule, which is
decount some info. So that's the count some. Let's uncomment this and check that I am correct.
Okay, so we have perfect equality. And there's no sketching us going on here with any shapes
because these are of the same shape. Okay, next up we want to back propagate through this line.
We have that count some is counts that some along the rows. So I wrote out some help here.
We have to keep in mind that counts of course is 32 by 27 and count some is 32 by one.
So in this back propagation, we need to take this column of the rudeness and transform it into a
array of derivatives to the original array. So what is this operation doing? We're taking in
some kind of an input like say a three by three matrix A and we are summing up the rows into
column tensor B, B1 B2 B3. That is basically this. So now we have the derivatives of the loss
with respect to B, all the elements of B. And now we want to derivative loss with respect to all these
little a's. So how do the B's depend on the a's is basically what we're after? What is the local
derivative of this operation? Well, we can see here that B1 only depends on these elements here.
The derivative of B1 with respect to all of these elements down here is zero. But for these
elements here like a 1 1 a 1 2 etc, the local derivative is one. So Db1 by Da 1 1, for example,
is one. So it's one one and one. So when we have the derivative of the loss with respect to B1,
the local derivative of B1 with respect to these inputs is zeros here, but it's one on these guys.
So in the chain rule, we have the local derivative times sort of the derivative of B1. And so because
the local derivative is one on these three elements, the local derivative of multiplying the derivative
of B1 will just be the derivative of B1. And so you can look at it as a router. Basically,
an addition is a router of gradient. Whatever gradient comes from above, it just gets routed
equally to all the elements that participate in that addition. So in this case, the derivative of B1
will just flow equally to the derivative of a 1 1 a 1 2 and a 1 3. So if we have a derivative of
all the elements of B, and in this column tensor, which is D counts sum that we've calculated just now,
we basically see that what that amounts to is all of these are now flowing to all these elements of A,
and they're doing that horizontally. So basically what we want is we want to take the D counts sum
of size 32 by 1, and we just want to replicate it 27 times horizontally to create 32 by 27 array.
So there's many ways to implement this operation. You could of course just replicate the tensor.
But I think maybe one clean one is that D counts is simply torch dot once like
so just an two dimensional arrays of once in the shape of counts. So 32 by 27 times D counts sum.
So this way we're letting the broadcasting here basically implement the replication. You can look
at that way. But then we have to also be careful because D counts was all already calculated.
We calculated earlier here, and that was just the first branch and we're now finishing the second
branch. So we need to make sure that these gradients add so plus equals. And then here,
let's comment out the comparison and let's make sure crossing fingers that we have the correct
result. So pytorch agrees with us on this gradient as well. Okay, hopefully we're getting a hang
of this now counts as an element wise exp of norm logits. So now we want D norm logits.
And because it's an element has operation everything is very simple. What is the local
derivative of e to the x? It's famously just e to the x. So this is the local derivative.
That is the local derivative. Now we already calculated it and it's inside counts. So we
made as well potentially just reuse counts. That is the local derivative times D counts.
Funny as that looks, the counts time D counts is iterative on the normal logits.
And now let's erase this and let's verify and it looks good.
So that's norm logits. Okay, so we are here on this line now, D norm logits. We have that and
we're trying to calculate the logits and the logit maxes. So back propagating through this line.
Now we have to be careful here because the shapes again are not the same. And so there's an implicit
broadcasting happening here. So normal digits has this shape 32 by 27. Logits does as well.
But logit maxes is only 32 by one. So there's a broadcasting here in the minus. Now here I tried
to sort of write out a two example again. We basically have that this is our C equals A minus B.
And we see that because of the shape, these are three by three, but this one is just a column.
And so for example, every element of C, we have to look at how it came to be. And every element of
C is just the corresponding element of A minus basically that associated B. So it's very clear
now that the derivatives of every one of these C's with respect to their inputs are one for the
corresponding A. And it's a negative one for the corresponding B. And so therefore, the derivatives
on the C will flow equally to the corresponding A's. And then also to the corresponding B's.
But then in addition to that, the B's are broadcast. So we'll have to do the additional sum just like
we did before. And of course, derivatives for B's will undergo a minus because the local derivative
here is negative one. So DC 32 by D, B three is negative one. So let's just implement that.
Basically, D logits will be exactly copying the derivative on normal digits. So D logits equals
D normal logits, and I'll do a dot clone for safety. So we're just making a copy. And then we have
that D logit maxis will be the negative of D normal logits, because of the negative sign.
And then we have to be careful because logit maxis is a column. And so just like we saw before,
because we keep replicating the same elements across all the columns, then in the backward pass,
because we keep reusing this, these are all just like separate branches of use of that one variable.
And so therefore, we have to do a sum along one would keep them equals true, so that we don't
destroy this dimension. And then the logit maxis will be the same shape. Now we have to be careful
because this D logits is not the final D logits. And that's because not only do we get gradient
signal into logits through here, but the logit maxis is a function of logits. And that's a second
branch into logits. So this is not yet our final derivative for logits. We will come back later for
the second branch. For now, the logit maxis is the final derivative. So let me uncomment this
CMP here. And let's just run this and logit maxis if my torch agrees with us. So that was the
derivative into through this line. Now, before we move on, I want to pause here briefly, and I want
to look at these logit maxis and especially their gradients. We've talked previously in the previous
route lecture that the only reason we're doing this is for the numerical stability of the soft max
that we are implementing here. And we talked about how if you take these logits for any one of these
examples, so one row of this logits tensor, if you add or subtract any value equally to all the
elements, then the value of the problems will be unchanged. You're not changing the soft max.
The only thing that this is doing is it's making sure that X doesn't overflow. And the reason we're
using a max is because then we are guaranteed that each row of logits, the highest number is 0. And so
this will be safe. And so basically what that has repercussions. If it is the case that changing
logit maxis does not change the props and therefore there's not changed the loss, then the gradient
on logit maxis should be zero, right? Because saying those two things is the same. So indeed,
we hope that this is very, very small numbers. Indeed, we hope this is zero. Now, because of
floating point sort of wonkiness, this doesn't count exactly zero, only in some of the rows it does.
But we get extremely small values like one in negative nine or 10. And so this is telling us
that the values of logit maxis are not impacting the loss as they shouldn't. It feels kind of
weird to back propagate through this branch, honestly, because if you have any implementation of like
F dot cross entropy and pytorch and you you block together all these elements and you're not doing
the back propagation piece by piece, then you would probably assume that the derivative through here
is exactly zero. So you would be sort of skipping this branch because it's only done for numerical
stability. But it's interesting to see that even if you break up everything into the full atoms and
you still do the computation as you'd like with respect to numerical stability, the correct thing
happens and you still get a very, very small gradients here, basically reflecting the fact that the
values of these do not matter with respect to the final loss. Okay, so let's now continue
back propagation through this line here. We've just calculated the logit maxis and now we want to
back prop into logits through this second branch. Now here, of course, we took logits and we took
the max along all the rows. And then we looked at its values here. Now the way this works is that
in pytorch, this thing here, the max returns both the values and it returns the indices that we
wish those values to call them the maximum value. Now in the forward pass, we only used values
because that's all we needed. But in the backward pass, it's extremely useful to know about where
those maximum values occurred. And we have the indices at which they occurred. And this will,
of course, helps us to help us do the back propagation. Because what should the backward pass be here
in this case? We have the logit tensor, which is 32 by 27. And in each row, we find the maximum
value. And then that value gets plucked out into logit maxis. And so intuitively,
basically the derivative flowing through here then should be one times the local derivative is one
for the appropriate entry that was plucked out. And then times the global derivative of the logit
maxis. So really what we're doing here, if you think through it, is we need to take the delogit
maxis, and we need to scatter it to the correct positions in these logits from where the maximum
values came. And so I came up with one line of code, sort of that does that, let me just
erase a bunch of stuff here. So the line of, you could do it kind of very similar to what we done
here, where we create a zeros, and then we populate the correct elements. So we use the indices here,
and we would set them to be one. But you can also use one hat. So f dot one hat. And then I'm taking
the logit max over the first dimension dot indices. And I'm telling PyTorch that the
dimension of every one of these tensors should be 27. And so what this is going to do
is, okay, I apologize, this is crazy. Be guilty that I am show of this. It's really just an array
of where the maxis came from in each row. And that element is one, and the old, the other elements
are zero. So it's a one-hat vector in each row. And these indices are now populating a single one
in the proper place. And then what I'm doing here is I'm multiplying by the logit maxis.
And keep in mind that this is a column of 32 by one. And so when I'm doing this times the
logit maxis, the logit maxis will broadcast, and that column will get replicated. And then the
element wise multiply will ensure that each of these just gets routed to whichever one of these
bits is turned on. And so that's another way to implement this kind of an operation. And both of
these can be used. I just thought I would show an equivalent way to do it. And I'm using plus equals
because we already calculated the logits here. And this is now the second branch. So let's
look at logits and make sure that this is correct. And we see that we have exactly the correct answer.
Next up, we want to continue with logits here. That is an outcome of a matrix multiplication
and a bias offset in this linear layer. So I've printed out the shapes of all these intermediate
tensors. We see that logits is of course 32 by 27, as we've just seen. Then the age here is 32 by 64.
So these are 64 dimensional hidden states. And then this w matrix projects those 64 dimensional
vectors into 27 dimensions. And then there's a 27 dimensional offset, which is a one dimensional
vector. Now we should note that this plus here actually broadcasts, because h multiplied by w two
will give us a 32 by 27. And so then this plus b two is a 27 dimensional vector here.
Now in the rules of broadcasting, what's going to happen with this bias vector is that this one
dimensional vector of 27 will get aligned with an padded dimension of one on the left. And it will
basically become a row vector. And then it will get replicated vertically 32 times to make it 32
by 27. And then there's an element wise multiply. Now, the question is how do we back propagate from
logits to the hidden states, the weight matrix w two and the bias b two. And you might think that
we need to go to some matrix calculus. And then we have to look up the derivative for a matrix
multiplication. But actually you don't have to do any of that. And you can go back to first
principles and derive this yourself on a piece of paper. And specifically what I like to do and I
what I find works well for me is you find a specific small example that you then fully write out. And
then in process of analyzing how that individual small example works, you will understand a broader
pattern and you'll be able to generalize and write out the full general formula for how these
derivatives flow in an expression like this. So let's try that out. So pardon the low budget
production here, but what I've done here is I'm writing it out on a piece of paper. Really,
what we are interested in is we have a multiply B plus C. And that creates a D. And we have the
derivative of the loss with respect to D. And we'd like to know what the derivative of the loss is
with respect to a B and C. Now these here are a little two dimensional examples of a matrix
multiplication, two by two times a two by two, plus a two, a vector of just two elements, C one and C
two gives me a two by two. Now notice here that I have a bias vector here called C. And the bias
vector C one and C two. But as I described over here, that bias vector will become a row vector in
the broadcasting and will replicate vertically. So that's what's happening here as well. C one C
two is replicated vertically. And we see how we have two rows of C one C two as a result.
So now when I say write it out, I just mean like this, basically break up this matrix multiplication
into the actual thing that that's going on under the hood. So as a result of matrix multiplication
and how it works, D one one is the result of a dot product between the first row of A and the
first column of B. So a one B one one plus a one two B two one plus C one. And so on so forth for
all the other elements of D. And once you actually write it out, it becomes obvious this is just a
bunch of multiplies and ads. And we know from micro grad how to differentiate multiplies and ads.
And so this is not scary anymore. It's not just a matrix multiplication. It's just tedious
unfortunately. But this is completely tractable. We have DL by D for all of these. And we want
DL by all these little other variables. So how do we achieve that? And how do we actually get the
gradients? Okay, so the low budget production continues here. So let's for example derive the
derivative of the loss with respect to a one one. We see here that a one one occurs twice in our
simple expression right here right here. And influence is D one one and D one two. So this is so what
is DL by D a one one? Well, it's DL by D one one times the local derivative of D one one,
which in this case is just B one one, because that's what's multiplying a one one here. So,
and likewise here the local derivative of D one two with respect to a one one is just B one two.
And so B one two will in the chain rule therefore multiply D L by D one two. And then because a one
one is used both to produce D one one and D one two, we need to add up the contributions of both
of those sort of chains that are running in parallel. And that's why we get a plus just adding
up those two, those two contributions. And that gives us DL by D a one one. We can do the exact
same analysis for the other one for all the other elements of a. And when you simply write it out,
it's just super simple taking ingredients on, you know, expressions like this. You find that
this matrix DL by D a that we're after, right, if we just arrange all of them in the same shape as
A takes. So A is just two by two matrix. So DL by D a here will be also just the same shape
tensor with the derivatives now. So DL by D a one one, etc. And we see that actually we can
express what we've written out here as a matrix multiply. And so it just so happens that DL by
that all of these formulas that we've derived here by taking gradients can actually be expressed
as a matrix multiplication. And in particular, we see that it is the matrix multiplication of these
two matrices. So it is the DL by D. And then matrix multiplying B, but B transpose actually. So you
see that B two one and B one two have changed place. Whereas before we had of course B one one,
B one two, B two one, B two two. So you see that this other matrix B is transposed. And so basically
what we have on story short, just by doing very simple reasoning here, by breaking up the expression
in the case of a very simple example, is that DL by D a is which is this is simply equal to DL by
Dd matrix multiplied with B transpose. So that is what we have so far. Now we also want the derivative
with respect to B and C. Now, for B, I'm not actually doing the full derivation because honestly it's
not deep. It's just annoying. It's exhausting. You can actually do this analysis yourself.
You'll also find that if you take this these expressions and you differentiate with respect
to B instead of A, you will find that DL by Db is also a matrix multiplication. In this case,
you have to take the matrix A and transpose it. And matrix multiply that with DL by Dd.
And that's what gives you a DL by Db. And then here for the offsets C one and C two,
if you again just differentiate with respect to C one, you will find an expression like this.
And C two, an expression like this. And basically you'll find that DL by Dc is simply because they're
just offsetting these expressions. You just have to take the DL by Dd matrix of the derivatives of D
and you just have to sum across the columns. And that gives you the derivative for C.
So long story short, the backward pass of a matrix multiply is a matrix multiply. And instead of
just like we had D equals A times B plus C in a scalar case, we sort of like arrive at
something very, very similar, but now with a matrix multiplication instead of a scalar multiplication.
So the derivative of D with respect to A is DL by Dd matrix multiply B transpose. And here it's
a transpose multiply DL by Dd. But in both cases, it's a matrix multiplication with the derivative
and the other term in the multiplication. And for C it is a sum. Now I'll tell you a secret.
I can never remember the formulas that we just arrived for back propagating information
multiplication. And I can back propagate through these expressions just fine. And the reason this
works is because the dimensions have to work out. So let me give you an example. Say I want to
create DH, then what should DH be number one? I have to know that the shape of DH must be the same
as the shape of H. And the shape of H is three two by 64. And then the other piece of information I
know is that DH must be some kind of matrix multiplication of D logits with W two. And D logits is 32 by 27.
And W two is 64 by 27. There is only a single way to make the shape work out. In this case,
and it is indeed the correct result. In particular here, H needs to be 32 by 64. The only way to
achieve that is to take a D logits and matrix multiply it with, you see how I have to take W
two, but I have to transpose it to make the dimensions work out. So W to transpose. And it's
the only way to make these two matrix multiply those two pieces to make the shapes work out.
And that turns out to be the core formula. So if we come here, we want DH, which is DA. And we see
that DA is DL by DD matrix multiply B transpose. So that's D logits multiply and B is W two. So
W two transpose, which is exactly what we have here. So there's no need to remember these formulas.
Similarly, now if I want D W two, well, I know that it must be a matrix multiplication of D logits
and H. And maybe there's a few transpose, but there's one transpose in there as well. And I don't
know which way it is. So I have to come to W two. And I see that it's shape is 64 by 27.
And that has to come from some interest multiplication of these two. And so to get a 64 by 27, I need to
take H, I need to transpose it. And then I need to matrix multiply it. So that will become 64 by 32.
And then I need to make sure small by the 32 by 27. And that's going to give me a 64 by 27.
So I need to make sure small by this with the logits that shape, just like that. That's the only
way to make the dimensions work out and just use matrix multiplication. And if we come here,
we see that that's exactly what's here. So a transpose A for us is H, multiply with the logits.
So that's W two. And then DB two is just the vertical sum. And actually, in the same way,
there's only one way to make the shapes work out. I don't have to remember that it's a vertical sum
along the zero axis, because that's the only way that this makes sense, because B two shape is 27.
So in order to get a D logits here, it's 32 by 27. So knowing that it's just some over D logits in some
direction, that direction must be zero, because I need to eliminate this dimension. So it's this.
So this is, so that's kind of like the hacky way. Let me copy paste and delete that. And let me
swing over here. And this is our backward pass for the linear layer, hopefully. So now let's
uncomment these three, and we're checking that we got all the three derivatives correct, and run.
And we see that H, W two and B two are all exactly correct. So we back propagate it through a linear
layer. Now next up, we have derivative for the H already. And we need to back propagate through
10 H into H preact. So we want to derive D H preact. And here we have to back propagate through a
10 H. And we've already done this in micro grad. And we remember that 10 H is a very simple backward
formula. Now, unfortunately, if I just put in D by DX of 10 H of X into both from alpha, it lets
us down. It tells us that it's a hyperbolic secant function squared of X. It's not exactly
helpful. But luckily, Google image search does not let us down. And it gives us the simpler formula.
And in particular, if you have that A is equal to 10 H of Z, then D A by D Z,
back propagating through 10 H, is just one minus a square. And take note that one minus a square,
A here is the output of the 10 H, not the input to the 10 H Z. So the D A by D Z is here formulated
in terms of the output of that 10 H. And here also in Google image search, we have the full
derivation. If you want to actually take the actual definition of 10 H and work through the math to
figure out one minus 10 to the square of Z. So one minus a square is the local derivative.
In our case, that is one minus the output of 10 H square, which here is H. So it's H square.
And that is the local derivative. And then times the chain rule, DH. So that is going to be our
candidate implementation. So if we come here and then uncomment this, let's hope for the best.
And we have the right answer. Okay, next up, we have BHP Act, and we want to back propagate into
the gain, the B and raw and the B and bias. So here, this is the Bashtron parameters, B and
gain in bias inside the Bashtron that take the B and raw that is exact unit Gaussian,
and they scale it and shift it. And these are the parameters of the Bashtron. Now, here, we have
a multiplication, but it's worth noting that this multiply is very, very different from this
matrix multiply here. Matrix multiply our dark products between rows and columns of these matrices
involved. This is an element twice multiply. So things are quite a bit simpler. Now, we do have
to be careful with some of the broadcasting happening in this line of code, though. So you see how B and
gain and B and bias are one by 64, but HP react and B and raw are 32 by 64.
So we have to be careful with that and make sure that all the shapes work out fine and that the
broadcasting is correctly back propagated. So in particular, let's start with the B and gain.
So D, B and gain should be. And here, this is again, element twice multiply. And whenever we have
A times B equals C, we saw that the local derivative here is just if this is a local derivative is
just the B, the other one. So the local derivative is just B and raw, and then times chain rule.
So D, H, P, act. So this is the candidate gradient. Now again, we have to be careful because B and
gain is of size one by 64. But this here would be 32 by 64. And so the correct thing to do in this
case, of course, is that B and gain here is a rule vector of 64 numbers. It gets replicated vertically
in this operation. And so therefore, the correcting to do is to sum because it's being replicated.
And therefore, all the gradients in each of the rows that are now flowing backwards need to sum
up to that same tensor B and gain. So if to sum across all the zero, all the examples, basically,
which is the direction which this gets replicated. And now we have to be also careful because we
be in game is of shape one by 64. So in fact, I need to keep them as true. Otherwise, I will just
get 64. Now I don't actually really remember why the B and gain and the B and bias, I made them
be one by 64. But the biases be one and B two, I just made them be one dimensional vectors.
They're not two dimensional tensors. So I can't recall exactly why I left the gain and the bias
as two dimensional. But it doesn't really matter as long as you are consistent and you're keeping
it the same. So in this case, we want to keep the dimension so that the tensor shapes work.
Next up, we have B and raw. So D B and raw will be B and gain multiplying D H preact. That's our
chain rule. Now what about the dimensions of this? We have to be careful, right? So D H preact is
32 by 64. B and gain is one by 64. So we'll just get replicated and to create this multiplication,
which is the correct thing, because in a forward pass, it also gets replicated in just the same way.
So in fact, we don't need the brackets here, we're done. And the shapes are already correct.
And finally, for the bias, very similar, this bias here is very, very similar to the bias we saw in
the linear layer. And we see that the gradients from H preact will simply flow into the biases
and add up, because these are just these are just offsets. And so basically, we want this to be D
H preact, but it needs to sum along the right dimension. And in this case, similar to the gain,
we need to sum across the zero dimension, the examples, because of the way that the bias gets
replicated very quickly. And we also want to have keep them as true. And so this will basically take
this and sum it up and give us a one by 64. So this is the candidate implementation, it makes all
the shapes work. Let me bring it up down here. And then let me uncomment these three lines
to check that we are getting the correct result for all the three tensors. And indeed, we see that
all of that got back propagated correctly. So now we get to the batch norm layer. We see how here
being gained and being biased are the parameters. So the back propagation ends. But being raw now
is the output of the standardization. So here, what I'm doing, of course, is I'm breaking up the
batch norm into manageable pieces. So we can back propagate through each line individually. But
basically what's happening is B and mean I is the sum. So this is the B and mean I, I apologize for
the variable naming. B and diff is X minus mu. B and diff two is X minus mu squared here inside
the variance. B and var is the variance. So sigma square, this is B and var. And it's basically the
sum of squares. So this is the X minus mu squared, and then the sum. Now you'll notice one departure
here. Here it is normalized as one over M, which is number of examples. Here I'm normalizing as one
over N minus one instead of N. And this is deliberate. And I'll come back to that in a bit when we are
at this line. It is something called the bestial correction. But this is how I want it in our case.
B and var in then becomes basically B and var plus epsilon. Epsilon is one negative five. And
then it's one over square root is the same as raising to the power of negative point five.
Right? Because point five is squared. And then negative makes it one over square root.
So B and var M is a one over this denominator here. And then we can see that B and raw, which is the
X hat here, is equal to the B and diff, the numerator, multiplied by the B and var in.
And this line here that creates pre H pre act was the last piece we've already back propagated
through it. So now what we want to do is we are here and we have B and raw. And we have to
first back propagate into B and diff and B and var in. So now we're here and we have D B and raw.
And we need to back propagate through this line. Now I've written out the shapes here and indeed
B and var in is a shape one by 64. So there is a broadcasting happening here that we have to be
careful with. But it is just an element wise simple multiplication by now we should be pretty
comfortable with that to get D B and diff. We know that this is just B and var in multiplied with
D B and raw. And conversely, to get D B and var in, we need to take B and diff and multiply
that by D B and raw. So this is the candidate. But of course, we need to make sure that broadcasting
is obeyed. So in particular, B and var and multiplying with D B and raw will be okay and give us 32 by
64 as we expect. But D B and var in would be taking a 32 by 64, multiplying it by 32 by 64.
So this is 32 by 64. But of course, D B, this B and var in is only one by 64. So the second line
here needs a sum across the examples. And because there's this dimension here, we need to make sure
that keep them history. So this is the candidate. Let's erase this and let's swing down here
and implement it. And the let's comment out D B and var in and D B and diff. Now, we'll actually
notice that D B and diff, by the way, is going to be incorrect. So when I run this, B and
B and var in this correct, B and diff is not correct. And this is actually expected, because
we're not done with B and diff. So in particular, when we slide here, we see here that B and raw is
a function of B and diff. But actually B and var of is a function of B and var, which is a function
of B and D, which is a function of B and diff. So it comes here. So B, D and diff, these variable
names are crazy. I'm sorry, it branches out into two branches. And we've only done one branch of it.
We have to continue our back propagation and eventually come back to B and diff. And then we'll
be able to do a plus equals and get the actual current gradient. For now, it is good to verify
that CBMP also works. It doesn't just lie to us and tell us that everything is always correct.
It can in fact detect when your gradient is not correct. So it's that's good to see as well.
Okay, so now we have the derivative here, and we're trying to back propagate through this line.
And because we're raising to a power of negative point five, I brought up the power rule. And we
see that basically we have that the B and var will now be we bring down the exponent. So negative point
five times x, which is this. And now race to the power of negative point five minus one, which is
a negative one point five. Now, we would have to also apply a small chain rule here in our head,
because we need to take further derivative of B and var with respect to this expression here
inside the bracket. But because this is an element wise operation, and everything is fairly simple,
that's just one. And so there's nothing to do there. So this is the local derivative. And then
times the global derivative to create the chain rule. This is just times the B and var.
So this is our candidate. Let me bring this down. And uncommon to the check.
And we see that we have the correct result. Now, before we back propagate through the next line,
I want to briefly talk about the note here, where I'm using the vessels correction,
dividing by n minus one, instead of dividing by n, when I normalize here, the sum of squares.
Now, you'll notice that this is the departure from the paper, which uses one over n instead,
not one over n minus one. There m is rn. And so it turns out that there are two ways of estimating
variance of an array. One is the biased estimate, which is one over n. And the other one is the
unbiased estimate, which is one over n minus one. Now, confusingly, in the paper, this is
not very clearly described. And also it's a detail that kind of matters, I think.
They are using the biased version train time. But later, when they are talking about the inference,
they are mentioning that when they do the inference, they are using the unbiased estimate,
which is the n minus one version in basically for inference. And to calibrate the running mean
and running variance, basically. And so they actually introduce a train test mismatch,
where in training, they use the biased version. And in the test time, they use the unbiased version.
I find this extremely confusing. You can read more about the Bessel's correction and why
dividing by n minus one gives you a better estimate of the variance. In a case where you have population
size, or samples for a population, there are very small. And that is indeed the case for us,
because we are dealing with mini batches. And these mini matches are a small sample of a larger
population, which is the entire training set. And so it just turns out that if you just estimate
it using one over n, that actually almost always underestimates the variance. And it is a biased
estimator. And it is advised that you use the unbiased version and divide by n minus one. And
you can go through this article here that I liked that actually describes the full reasoning. And
I'll link it in the video description. Now, when you calculate the torture variance, you'll notice
that they take the unbiased flag, whether or not you want to divide by n or n minus one.
Confusingly, they do not mention what the default is for unbiased. But I believe unbiased by default
is true. I'm not sure why the docs here don't cite that. Now, in the batch number, 1D, the
documentation again is kind of wrong and confusing. It says that the standard deviation is calculated
via the biased estimator. But this is actually not exactly right. And people have pointed out that
it is not right in a number of issues since then, because actually the rabbit hole is deeper. And
they follow the paper exactly. And they use the biased version for training. But when they're
estimating the running standard deviation, we are using the unbiased version. So again,
there's the train test mismatch. So long story short, I'm not a fan of train test discrepancies.
I basically kind of consider the fact that we use the biased version, the training time, and
the unbiased test time, I basically consider this to be a bug. And I don't think that there's a good
reason for that. It's not really, they don't really go into the detail of the reasoning behind it
in this paper. So that's why I basically prefer to use the bestness correction in my own work.
Unfortunately, Batchnerone does not take a keyword argument that tells you whether or not
you want to use the unbiased version or the biased version in both training tests. And so
therefore anyone using batch normalization, basically in my view has a bit of a bug in the code.
And this turns out to be much less of a problem if your batch mini batch sizes are a bit larger.
But still, I just find it kind of unpodable. So maybe someone can explain why this is okay.
But for now, I prefer to use the unbiased version consistently both during training and at test time.
And that's why I'm using one over n minus one here. Okay, so let's now actually back propagate
through this line. So the first thing that I always like to do is I like to scrutinize the
shapes first. So in particular here, looking at the shapes of what's involved, I see that Bnvar
shape is one by 64. So it's a row vector and Bn if two dot shape is 32 by 64. So clearly here,
we're doing a sum over the zero axis to squash the first dimension of the shapes here using a sum.
So that right away actually hints to me that there will be some kind of a replication or
broadcasting in the backward pass. And maybe you're noticing the pattern here, but basically,
anytime you have a sum in the forward pass, that turns into a replication or broadcasting in the
backward pass along the same dimension. And conversely, when we have a replication or a
broadcasting in the forward pass, that indicates a variable reuse. And so in the backward pass,
that turns into a sum over the exact same dimension. And so hopefully you're noticing that duality
that those two are kind of like the opposite of each other in the forward and backward pass.
Now, once we understand the shapes, the next thing I like to do always is I like to look at a
two example in my head to sort of just like understand roughly how the variable dependencies
go in the mathematical formula. So here, we have a two dimensional array at the end of two,
which we are scaling by a constant. And then we are summing vertically over the columns.
So if we have a two by two matrix A, and then we sum over the columns and scale,
we would get a row vector B1 B2. And B1 depends on A in this way, where it's just some that are
scaled of A and B2 in this way, where it's the second column, sum and scale. And so looking at
this basically, what we want to do now is we have the derivatives on B1 and B2, and we want to
back propagate them into aase. And so it's clear that just differentiating in your head,
the local derivative here is 1 over n minus 1 times 1 for each one of these a's. And
basically, the derivative of B1 has to flow through the columns of A scaled by 1 over n minus 1.
And that's roughly what's happening here. So intuitively, the derivative flow tells us that
dB and F2 will be the local derivative of this operation. And there are many ways to do this,
by the way, but I like to do something like this. Torched out one slide of B and F2. So I'll create
a large array to the measure of ones. And then I will scale it. So 1.0 divided by n minus 1.
So this is a array of 1 over n minus 1. And that's sort of like the local derivative.
And now for the chain rule, I will simply just multiply it by dB and R.
And notice here what's going to happen. This is 32 by 64. And this is just 1 by 64. So I'm letting
the broadcasting do the replication, because internally in PyTorch, basically dB and R, which
is 1 by 64 row vector, well, in this multiplication, get copied vertically until the two are of the
same shape. And then there will be an element wise multiply. And so that the broadcasting is
basically doing the replication. And I will end up with the derivatives of dB and F2.
Here. So this is the kentexolution. Let's bring it down here. Let's uncomment this line,
where we check it. And let's hope for the best. And indeed, we see that this is the
correct formula. Next up, let's differentiate here into B and F. So here we have that B and F is
element wise squared to create B and F2. So this is a relatively simple derivative,
because it's a simple element wise operation. So it's kind of like the scalar case. And we have
that dB and F should be, if this is x squared, then derivative of this is 2x. Right? So it's simply
2 times B and F, that's the local derivative. And then times chain rule. And the shape of these
is the same, they are of the same shape. So times this. So that's the backward pass for this variable.
Let me bring them down here. And now we have to be careful, because we already calculated dB and
diff, right? So this is just the end of the other, you know, other branch coming back to B and F,
because B and F will already back propagate it to way over here, from B and raw. So we now
completed the second branch. And so that's why I have to do plus equals. And if you recall,
we had an incorrect derivative for B and F before. And I'm hoping that once we
append this last missing piece, we have the exact correctness. So let's run. And B and diff now
actually shows the exact correct derivative. So that's comforting. Okay, so let's now back
propagate through this line here. The first thing we do, of course, is we check the shapes.
And I wrote them out here. And basically the shape of this is 32 by 64. Hbbn is the same shape.
But B and me ny is a row vector one by 64. So this minus here will actually do broadcasting.
And so we have to be careful with that. And as a hint to us, again, because of the duality,
a broadcasting in the forward pass means a variable reuse. And therefore there will be a sum in the
backward pass. So let's write out the backward pass here now. Back propagate into the H pre Bn.
Because this is these are the same shape, then the local derivative for each one of the elements
here is just one for the corresponding element in here. So basically what this means is that the
gradient just simply copies is just a variable assignment, its quality. So I'm just going to
clone this tensor, just for safety to create an exact copy of D B and diff. And then here to
back propagate into this one, what I'm inclined to do here is D Bn, me ny will basically be
what is the local derivative? Well, it's negative torch dot one, like of the shape of B and diff.
And then times the derivative here, D Bn diff.
And this here is the back propagation for the replicated B and me ny. So I still have to
back propagate through the replication and broadcasting. And I do that by doing a sum. So I'm going to
take this whole thing and I'm going to do a sum over the zero dimension, which was the replication.
So if you scrutinize this, by the way, you'll notice that this is the same shape as that. And so
what I'm doing, what I'm doing here doesn't actually make that much sense because it's just a
array of ones multiplying D P and diff. So in fact, I can just do this. And there's a equivalent.
So this is the candidate backward pass. Let me copy it here. And then let me comment out this one
and this one. Enter. And it's wrong. Damn. Actually, sorry, this is supposed to be wrong.
And it's supposed to be wrong because we are back propagating from a B and diff into H
pre Bn. And but we're not done because B and me ny depends on H pre Bn. And there will be a second
portion of that derivative coming from this second branch. So we're not done yet. And we expect it
to be incorrect. So there you go. So let's not back propagate from B and me ny into H pre Bn.
And so here again, we have to be careful because there's a broadcasting along or there's a sum
along the zero dimension. So this will turn into broadcasting in the backward pass now.
And I'm going to go a little bit faster on this line because it is very similar to the line that
we had before and multiple eyes in the past. In fact, so D H pre Bn will be the gradient will
be scaled by one over n. And then basically this gradient here, D Bn, my mean, I is going to be
scaled by one over n. And then it's going to flow across all the columns and deposit itself into
D H pre Bn. So what we want is this thing scaled by one over n. We'll put the constant up front here.
So scaled on the gradient. And now we need to replicate it across all the across all the rows
here. So we I like to do that by torch dot ones like off basically H pre Bn.
And I will let broadcasting do the work of replication. So like that. So this is D H pre
Pn. And hopefully we can plus equals that.
So this here is broadcasting. And then this is the scaling. So this should be correct.
Okay. So that completes the back propagation of the bathroom layer. And we are now here.
Let's back propagate through the linear layer one here. Now, because everything is getting a
little vertically crazy, I copy pasted the line here. And let's just back propagate through this
one line. So first, of course, we inspect the shapes and we see that this is 3,2, by 64.
MCAT is 32 by 30. W1 is 30 30 by 64. And B1 is just 64. So as I mentioned, back propagating
through linear layers is fairly easy just by matching the shapes. So let's do that. We have that
D MCAT should be some matrix multiplication of D H pre Bn with W1 and one transpose thrown in there.
So to make MCAT be 32 by 30, I need to take D H pre Bn 32 by 64 and multiply it by W1.transpose.
To get D w1, I need to end up with 30 by 64. So to get that, I need to take MCAT transpose
and multiply that by D H pre Bn. And finally, to get D B1,
this is a addition. And we saw that basically, I need to just sum the elements in D H pre Bn
along some dimension. And to make the dimensions work out, I need to sum along the 0th axis here
to eliminate this dimension. And we do not keep them. So that we want to just get a single
1 dimensional lecture of 64. So these are the claimed derivatives. Let me put that here and
let me uncomment three lines and cross our fingers. Everything is great. Okay, so we now continue
almost there. We have the derivative of MCAT and we want to back propagate into M.
So I again copied this line over here. So this is the forward pass. And then this is the shapes.
So remember that the shape here was 32 by 30. And the original shape of M was 32 by 3 by 10.
So this layer in the forward pass, as you recall, did the concatenation of these three
10 dimensional character vectors. And so now we just want to undo that. So this is actually
relatively straightforward operation, because the backward pass of the, what is the view?
View is just a re-print representation of the array. It's just a logical form of how you interpret
the array. So let's just reinterpret it to be what it was before. So in other words, the M is not
32 by 30. It is basically the MCAT. But if you view it as the original shape, so just M.shape.
You can pass in tuples into view. And so this should just be, okay,
we just re-represent that view. And then we uncomment this line here. And hopefully,
yeah, so the derivative of M is correct. So in this case, we just have to re-represent the shape
of those derivatives into the original view. So now we are at the final line. And the only thing
that's left to back propagate through is this indexing operation here, M is C at XB. So as I did
before, I copy pasted this line here. And let's look at the shapes of everything that's involved
and remind ourselves how this worked. So M.shape was 32 by 3 by 10. So it's 32 examples. And then we
have three characters. Each one of them has a 10 dimensional embedding. And this was achieved
by taking the lookup table C, which have 27 possible characters, each of them 10 dimensional.
And we looked up at the rows that were specified inside this tensor XB. So XB is 32 by 3.
And it's basically giving us for each example the identity or the index of which character
is part of that example. And so here I'm showing the first five rows of three of this tensor XB.
And so we can see that for example, here it was the first example in this batch is that the
first character and the first character and the fourth character comes into the neural net.
And then we want to predict the next character in a sequence after the character is 114.
So basically what's happening here is there are integers inside XB. And each one of these
integers is specifying which row of C we want to pluck out. Right. And then we arrange those
rows that we've plucked out into three, two by three by 10 tensor. And we just package them
in, we just package them into this tensor. And now what's happening is that we have D.
So for every one of these basically plucked out rows, we have their gradients now,
but they're arranged inside this 32 by three by 10 tensor. So all we have to do now is we just
need to route this gradient backwards through this assignment. So we need to find which row of C
that every one of these tendimational embeddings come from. And then we need to deposit them into D.C.
So we just need to undo the indexing. And of course, if any of these rows of C was used multiple times,
which almost certainly is the case, like the row one and one was used multiple times,
then we have to remember that the gradients that arrive there have to add. So for each occurrence,
we have to have an addition. So let's now write this out. And I don't actually know of like a
much better way to do this than a for loop unfortunately in Python. So maybe someone can come up with a
factorized efficient operation. But for now, let's just use for loops. So let me create a torched
out zeros like C to initialize just 27 by 10 tensor of all zeros. And then honestly 4k in range
xb dot shape at zero. Maybe someone has a better way to do this, but for J in range,
xb dot shape at one. This is going to iterate over all the all the elements of xb, all these
integers. And then let's get the index at this position. So the index is basically xb at kj.
So that an example of that is 11 or 14 and so on. And now in the forward pass, we took,
we basically took the row of C at index, and we deposited it into m at k aj. That's what happened.
That's where they are packaged. So now we need to go backwards and we just need to route
dm at the position kj. We now have these derivatives for each position and it's 10
dimensional. And you just need to go into the correct row of C. So dC rather at ix is this,
but plus equals, because there could be multiple occurrences, like the same row could have been
used many, many times. And so all of those derivatives will just go backwards through the indexing
and they will add. So this is my candidate solution. Let's copy it here.
Let's uncomment this and cross our fingers. Hey, so that's it. We've back propagated through
this entire beast. So there we go. Totally makes sense. So now we come to exercise two.
It basically turns out that in this first exercise, we were doing way too much work.
We were back propagating way too much. And it was all good practice and so on,
but it's not what you would do in practice. And the reason for that is, for example,
here I separated out this loss calculation over multiple lines and I broke it up all,
all two, like its smallest atomic pieces and we back propagated through all of those individually.
But it turns out that if you just look at the mathematical expression for the loss,
then actually you can do the differentiation on pen and paper and a lot of terms cancel and
simplify. And the mathematical expression you end up with can be significantly shorter and
easier to implement than back propagating through all the little pieces of everything you've done.
So before we had this complicated forward pass, going from logits to the loss,
but in PyTorch, everything can just be glued together into a single call f dot cross entropy.
You just pass in logits and the labels and you get the exact same loss as I verify here.
So our previous loss and the fast loss coming from the chunk of operations as a single mathematical
expression is the same, but it's much, much faster and forward pass. It's also much, much faster
and backward pass. And the reason for that is if you just look at the mathematical form of this
and differentiate again, you will end up with a very small and short expression. So that's what
we want to do here. We want to in a single operation or in a single go, or like very quickly,
go directly into delogits. And we need to implement delogits as a function of
logits and YBs. But it will be significantly shorter than whatever we did here, where to get
to delogits, we had to go all the way here. So all of this work can be skipped in a much,
much simpler mathematical expression that you can implement here. So you can give it a shot
yourself, basically look at what exactly is the mathematical expression of loss
and differentiate with respect to the logits. So let me show you a hint. You can of course try
it fully yourself. But if not, I can give you some hint of how to get started mathematically.
So basically what's happening here is we have logits, then there's the softmax that takes the
logits and gives you probabilities. Then we are using the identity of the correct next character
to pluck out a row of probabilities, take the negative log of it to get our negative log probability.
And then we average up all the log probabilities or negative log probabilities to get our loss.
So basically what we have is for a single individual example, rather, we have that loss is equal to
negative log probability, where P here is kind of like thought of as a vector of all the probabilities.
So at the yth position, where y is the label. And we have that P here, of course, is the softmax.
So the i th component of P of this probability vector is just the softmax function. So raising
all the logits basically to the power of E and normalizing. So everything comes to one.
Now if you write out P of y here, you can just write out the softmax. And then basically what
we're interested in is we're interested in the derivative of the loss with respect to the i th
logit. And so basically it's a d by dli of this expression here, where we have l indexed with
the specific label y. And on the bottom, we have a sum over j of e to the lj and the negative
log of all that. So potentially give it a shot pen and paper and see if you can actually derive
the expression for the loss by dli. And then we're going to implement it here. Okay, so I am going
to give away the result here. So this is some of the math I did to derive the gradients
analytically. And so we see here that I'm just applying the rules of calculus from your first or
second year of bachelor's degree if you took it. And we see that the expression is actually
simplified quite a bit. You have to separate out the analysis in the case where the i th index
that you're interested in inside logits is either equal to the label or it's not equal to the label.
And then the expression is simplify and cancel in a slightly different way. And what we end up with
is something very, very simple. We either end up with basically p at i, where p is again this
vector of probabilities after a softmax or p at i minus one, where we just simply subtract one.
But in any case, we just need to calculate the softmax p and then in the correct dimension,
we need to subtract one. And that's the gradient, the form that it takes analytically. So let's
implement this basically. And we have to keep in mind that this is only done for a single example.
But here we are working with batches of examples. So we have to be careful of that. And then the
loss for a batch is the average loss over all the examples. So in other words, it's the example
for all the individual examples is the loss for each individual example summed up and then divided
by n. And we have to back propagate through that as well and be careful with it. So d logits is
going to be f dot softmax. Plattorch has a softmax function that you can call. And we want to apply
the softmax on the logits. And we want to go in the dimension that is one. So basically, we want to
do the softmax along the rows of these logits. Then at the correct positions, we need to subtract
a one. So d logits at iterating over all the rows and indexing into the columns provided by the
correct labels inside yb. We need to subtract one. And then finally, it's the average loss that is
the loss. And in the average, there's a one over n of all the losses added up. And so we need to
also back propagate through that division. So the gradient has to be scaled down by n as well,
because of the mean. But this otherwise should be the result. So now if we verify this,
we see that we don't get an exact match. But at the same time, the maximum difference from
logits from PyTorch and our d logits here is on the order of 5e negative nine. So it's a tiny,
tiny number. So because of floating point of emptiness, we don't get the exact bitwise result.
But we basically get the correct answer. Approximately. Now I'd like to pause here briefly before we
move on to the next exercise, because I'd like us to get an intuitive sense of what d logits is,
because it has a beautiful and very simple explanation, honestly. So here, I'm taking the logits and
I'm visualizing it. And we can see that we have a batch of 32 examples of 27 characters. And what
is the logits intuitively, right? The logits is the probabilities that the probabilities matrix
in a forward pass. But then here, these black squares are the positions of the correct indices
where we subtracted a one. And so what is this doing, right? These are the derivatives on
d logits. And so let's look at just the first row here. So that's what I'm doing here. I'm
calculating the probabilities of these logits, and then I'm taking just the first row. And this is the
probability row. And then the logits of the first row and multiplying by n just for us so that
we don't have the scaling by n in here, and everything is more interpretable. We see that it's
exactly equal to the probability, of course, but then the position of the correct index has a minus
equals one. So minus one on that position. And so notice that if you take the logits at zero,
and you sum it, it actually sums to zero. And so you should think of these gradients here at each
cell as like a force. We are going to be basically pulling down on the probabilities of the incorrect
characters. And we're going to be pulling up on the probability at the correct index. And that's
what's basically happening in each row. And the amount of push and pull is exactly equalized,
because the sum is zero. So the amount to which we pulled down on the probabilities and the demand
that we push up on the probability of the correct character is equal. So it's sort of the repulsion
and the attraction are equal. And think of the neural mat now as a, as a like a massive
pulley system or something like that, we're up here on top of the logits, and we're pulling up,
we're pulling down the probabilities of incorrect and pulling up the probability of the correct.
And in this complicated pulley system, because everything is mathematically just determined,
just think of it as sort of like this tension translating to this complicating pulley mechanism.
And then eventually we get a tug on the weights and the biases. And basically in each update,
we just kind of like tug in the direction that we like for each of these elements. And the
parameters are slowly given in to the tug. And that's what training in neural mat kind of like
looks like on a high level. And so I think the forces of push and pull in these gradients are
actually very intuitive here. We're pushing and pulling on the correct answer and the incorrect
answers. And the amount of force that we're applying is actually proportional to the probabilities
that came out in the forward pass. And so for example, if our probabilities came out exactly
correct, so they would have had zero everywhere except for one at the correct position, then the
the logits would be all row of zeros for that example, there would be no push and pull. So
the amount to which your prediction is incorrect is exactly the amount by which you're going to
get a pull or a push in that dimension. So if you have for example, a very confidently
mispredicted element here, then what's going to happen is that element is going to be pulled down
very heavily. And the correct answer is going to be pulled up to the same amount. And the other
characters are not going to be influenced too much. So the amount to which you mispredict is
then proportional to the strength of the pull. And that's happening independently in all the
dimensions of this of this tensor. And it's sort of very intuitive and very used to think through.
And that's basically the magic of the cross entropy loss and what is doing dynamically
in the backward pass of the neural mat. So now we get to exercise number three,
which is a very fun exercise, depending on your definition of fun. And we are going to do for
batch normalization exactly what we did for cross entropy loss in exercise number two. That is,
we are going to consider it as a glued single mathematical expression and back propagate through
it in a very efficient manner, because we are going to derive a much simpler formula for the
backward pass of batch normalization. And we're going to do that using pen and paper.
So previously, we've broken up batch normalization into all of the little intermediate pieces and
all the atomic operations inside it. And then we back propagate it through it one by one.
Now we just have a single sort of forward pass of a batch room. And it's all glued together.
And we see that we get the exact same result as before. Now for the batch backward pass,
we'd like to also implement a single formula basically for back propagating through this
entire operation that is the batch normalization. So in the forward pass previously,
we took H pre B and the hidden states of the pre-bacterialization and created H preact,
which is the hidden states just before the activation. In the batch normalization paper,
H pre B and is X and H preact is Y. So in the backward pass, what we'd like to do now is we have
DH preact and we'd like to produce DH pre-bien. And we'd like to do that in a very efficient
manner. So that's the name of the game calculate DH pre-bien given DH preact. And for the purposes
of this exercise, we're going to ignore gamma and beta and their derivatives because they take
on a very simple form in a very similar way to what we did up above. So let's calculate this,
given that right here. So to help you a little bit like I did before, I started off the implementation
here on pen and paper and I took two sheets of paper to derive the mathematical formulas for
the backward pass. And basically to set up the problem, just write out the mu sigma square variance,
X i hat and Y i exactly as in the paper except for the Bessel correction. And then
in the backward pass, we have the derivative of the loss with respect to all the elements of Y.
And remember that Y is a vector. There's there's multiple numbers here. So we have all the derivatives
with respect to all the Ys. And then there's a Dema and a Beta. And this is kind of like the
compute graph. The gamma and the Beta, there's the X hat. And then the mu and the sigma square
and the X. So we have DL by DYI and we won't DL by DXi for all the I's in these vectors.
So this is the compute graph and you have to be careful because I'm trying to note here that
these are vectors. There's many nodes here inside X, X hat and Y, but mu and sigma,
sorry, sigma square are just individual scalars, single numbers. So you have to be careful with
that. You have to imagine there's multiple nodes here or you're going to get your math wrong.
So as an example, I would suggest that you go in the following order, one, two, three,
four in terms of the back propagation. So back propagating to X hat, then to sigma square,
then into mu and then into X. Just like an anthropological sort in micro grad, we would
go from right to left. You're doing the exact same thing except you're doing it with symbols
and on a piece of paper. So for number one, I'm not giving away too much. If you want
DL of the XI hat, then we just take DL by D YI and multiply by gamma because of this expression
here, where any individual YI is just gamma times XI hat plus beta. So it doesn't help you too much
there, but this gives you basically the derivatives for all the accents. And so now try to go through
this computational graph and derive what is DL by D sigma square. And then what is DL by D mu?
And then what is DL by D X eventually? So give it a go and I'm going to be revealing the answer
one piece at a time. Okay, so to get DL by D sigma square, we have to remember again,
like I mentioned that there are many Xs, X hats here. And remember that sigma square is just a
single individual number here. So when we look at the expression for DL by D sigma square,
we have that we have to actually consider all the possible paths that we basically have that
there's many X hats and they all feed off from the all depend on sigma square. So sigma square
has a large fan out, there's lots of arrows coming out from sigma square into all the X hats.
And then there's a back propagating signal from each X hat into sigma square. And that's why we
actually need to sum over all those eyes from i equal to one to m of the DL by D X i hat, which
is the global gradient times the X i hat by D sigma square, which is the local gradient
of this operation here. And then mathematically, I'm just working it out here and I'm simplifying
and you get a certain expression for DL by D sigma square. We're going to be using this
expression when we back propagate into mu and then eventually into X. So now let's continue our
back propagation into mu. So what is DL by D mu? Now again, be careful that mu influences X hat
and X hat is actually lots of values. So for example, if our mini batch size is 32, as it is in our
example that we were working on, then this is 32 numbers and 32 arrows going back to mu.
And then mu going to sigma square is just a single arrow because sigma square is a scalar.
So in total, there are 33 arrows emanating from you. And then all of them have gradients coming
into mu and they all need to be summed up. And so that's why when we look at the expression for DL
by D mu, I am summing up over all the gradients of DL by D X i hat times the X i hat by D mu.
So that's this arrow and the 32 arrows here. And then plus the one arrow from here, which is DL by D
sigma square times the sigma square by D mu. So now we have to work out that expression.
And let me just reveal the rest of it. Simplifying here is not complicated, the first term, and you
just get an expression here. For the second term though, there's something really interesting that
happens. When we look at the sigma square by D mu and we simplify, at one point, if we assume
that in a special case where mu is actually the average of X i's, as it is in this case,
then if we plug that in, then actually the gradient vanishes and becomes exactly zero.
And that makes the entire second term cancel. And so these, if you just have a mathematical
expression like this, and you look at D sigma square by D mu, you would get some mathematical formula
for how mu impacts sigma square. But if it is the special case that mu is actually equal to
the average, as it is in the case of rationalization, that gradient will actually vanish and become zero.
So the whole term cancels, and we just get a fairly straightforward expression here for DL by D
mu. Okay, and now we get to the craziest part, which is deriving DL by D xi, which is ultimately
what we're after. Now, let's count. First of all, how many numbers are there inside X? As I
mentioned, there are 32 numbers. There are 32 little xi's. And let's count the number of arrows
emanating from each xi. There's an arrow going to mu, an arrow going to sigma square. And then
there's an arrow going to x hat. But this arrow here, let's group now that a little bit. Each xi hat
is just a function of xi and all the other scalars. So xi hat only depends on xi and none of the other
axis. And so therefore, there are actually in this single arrow, there are 32 arrows. But those 32
arrows are going exactly parallel. They don't interfere. They're just going parallel between x
and x hat. You can look at it that way. And so how many arrows are emanating from each xi? There
are three arrows, mu sigma square, and the associated x hat. And so in back propagation, we now need
to apply the chain rule. And we need to add up those three contributions. So here's what that
looks like if I just write that out. We're going through, we're changing through mu sigma square and
through x hat. And those three terms are just here. Now we already have three of these. We have
dl by d xi hat. We have dl by d mu, which we derived here. And we have dl by d sigma square,
which we derived here. But we need three other terms here. This one, this one, and this one.
So I invite you to try to derive them. It's not that complicated. You're just looking at
these expressions here and differentiating with respect to xi. So give it a shot, but here's the
result. Or at least what I got. Yeah, I'm just, I'm just differentiating with respect to xi for
all of these expressions. And honestly, I don't think there's anything too tricky here. It's
basic calculus. Now it gets a little bit more tricky is we are now going to plug everything
together. So all of these terms multiplied with all of these terms and added up according to this
formula. And that gets a little bit hairy. So what ends up happening is you get a large expression.
And the thing to be very careful with here, of course, is we are working with a dl by d xi for
specific by here. But when we are plugging in some of these terms, like say, this term here,
dl by d sigma squared, you see how deal by d sigma squared, I end up with an expression.
And I'm iterating over little eyes here. But I can't use i as the variable when I plug in here,
because this is a different i from this i. This i here is just a place or a local variable for
for a for loop in here. So here, when I plug that in, you notice that I rename the i to a j.
Because I need to make sure that this j is not that this j is not this i. This j is like like a
little local iterator over 32 terms. And so you have to be careful with that. When you're plugging
in the expressions from here to here, you may have to rename eyes into j's. You have to be very
careful what is actually an i with respect to dl by d xi. So some of these are j's. Some of these
are i's. And then we simplify this expression. And I guess like the big thing to notice here is
a bunch of terms just going to come out to the front and you can refactor them. There's a signal
square plus epsilon raised to the power of negative three over two. This sigma square plus epsilon
can be actually separated out into three terms. Each of them are sigma square plus epsilon to the
negative one over two. So the three of them multiplied is equal to this. And then those three terms can
go different places because of the multiplication. So one of them actually comes out to the front
and will end up here outside. One of them joins up with this term and one of them joins up with
this other term. And then when you simplify the expression, you'll notice that some of these terms
that are coming out are just the xi hats. So you can simplify just by rewriting that. And what we
end up with at the end is a fairly simple mathematical expression over here that I cannot simplify
further. But basically, you'll notice that it only uses the stuff we have and it derives the
thing we need. So we have dl by dy for all the i's. And those are used plenty of times here.
And also in the initial, what we're using is these xi hats and xj hats. And they just come from the
forward pass. And otherwise, this is a simple expression. And it gives us dl by d xi for all the
i's. And that's ultimately what we're interested in. So that's the end of a bachelor backward pass
analytically. Let's now implement this final result. Okay, so I implemented the expression
into a single line of code here. And you can see that the max diff is tiny. So this is the
correct implementation of this formula. Now, I'll just basically tell you that getting this formula
here from this mathematical expression was not trivial. And there's a lot going on packed into
this one formula. And this is all exercised by itself. Because you have to consider the fact
that this formula here is just for a single neuron and a batch of 32 examples. But what I'm doing
here is I'm actually, we actually have 64 neurons. And so this expression has to in parallel evaluate
the batch from backward pass for all those 64 neurons in parallel independently. So this has
to happen basically in every single column of the inputs here. And in addition to that,
you see how there are a bunch of sums here. And we need to make sure that when I do those
sums that they broadcast correctly onto everything else that's here. And so getting this expression
is just like highly non trivial. And I invite you to basically look through it and step through
it. And it's a whole exercise to make sure that this checks out. But once all the shapes agree,
and once you convince yourself that it's correct, you can also verify that PyTorch gets the exact
same answer as well. And so that gives you a lot of peace of mind that this mathematical formula is
correctly implemented here and broadcast it correctly and replicated in parallel for all the 64 neurons
inside this batch term layer. Okay, and finally exercise number four asks you to put it all together.
And here we have a redefinition of the entire problem. So you see that we re-enlistalize a neural
net from scratch and everything. And then here, instead of calling the loss that backward, we want
to have the manual back propagation here as we derived it up above. So go up, copy paste all the
chunks of code that we've already derived, put them here and derive your own gradients, and then
optimize this neural net, basically using your own gradients all the way to the calibration of the
batch norm and the evaluation of the loss. And I was able to achieve quite a good loss, basically
the same loss you would achieve before. And that shouldn't be surprising because all we've done is
we've really gotten into loss that backward and we've pulled out all the code and inserted it here.
But those gradients are identical and everything is identical and the results are identical. It's
just that we have full visibility on exactly what goes on under the hood of lot that backward in
this specific case. Okay, and this is all of our code. This is the full backward pass using basically
the simplified backward pass for the cross entropy loss and the best normalization. So back propagating
through cross entropy, the second layer, the 10 h null linearity, the best normalization
through the first layer and through the embedding. And so you see that this is only maybe what is
this 20 lines of code or something like that. And that's what gives us gradients. And now we can
potentially erase loss and backward. So the way I have the code set up is you should be able to run
this entire cell once you fill this in. And this will run for only 100 iterations and then break.
And it breaks because it gives you an opportunity to check your gradients against pytorch.
So here are gradients we see are not exactly equal. They are approximately equal. And the
differences are tiny, one in negative nine or so. And I don't exactly know where they're coming from,
to be honest. So once we have some confidence that the gradients are basically correct,
we can take out the gradient checking. We can disable this breaking statement.
And then we can basically disable loss the backward. We don't need it anymore.
Feels amazing to say that. And then here, when we are doing the update, we're not going to use
p.grad. This is the old way of pytorch. We don't have that anymore, because we're not doing backward.
We are going to use this update, where we you see that I'm iterating over,
I've arranged the grads to be in the same order as the parameters, and I'm zipping them up the
gradients and the parameters into p and grad. And then here, I'm going to step with just the
grad that we derived manually. So the last piece is that none of this now requires gradients from
pytorch. And so one thing you can do here, is you can do with torch.no.grad and offset this whole
code block. And really what you're saying is you're telling pytorch that, hey, I'm not going to
call backward on any of this. And this allows pytorch to be a bit more efficient with all of it.
And then we should be able to just run this. And it's running. And you see that loss of the
backward is commented out, and we're optimizing. So we're going to lead this run, and hopefully
we get a good result. Okay, so I allowed the neural out to finish optimization. Then here,
I calibrate the batch parameters, because I did not keep track of the running mean and very
variance in their training loop. Then here, I ran the loss, and you see that we actually obtained
a pretty good loss, very similar to what we've achieved before. And then here, I'm sampling from
the model, and we see some of the name like gibberish that we're sort of used to. So basically, the
model worked and samples, per decent results, compared to what we're used to. So everything is
the same. But of course, the big deal is that we did not use lots of backward, we did not use
pytorch autograd, and we estimated our gradients ourselves by hand. And so hopefully you're looking
at this, the backward pass of this neural net, and you're thinking to yourself, actually, that's not
too complicated. Each one of these layers is like three lines of code or something like that.
And most of it is fairly straightforward, potentially with the notable exception of the
batch normalization backward pass. Otherwise, it's pretty good. Okay, and that's everything I wanted
to cover for this lecture. So hopefully you found this interesting. And what I liked about it,
honestly, is that it gave us a very nice diversity of layers to back propagate through. And I think
it gives a pretty nice and comprehensive sense of how these backward passes are implemented and
how they work. And you'd be able to derive them yourself. But of course, in practice, you probably
don't want to, and you want to use the pytorch autograd. But hopefully you have some intuition
about how gradients flow backwards through the neural net, starting at the loss, and how they
flow through all the variables and all the intermediate results. And if you understood a good chunk of
it, and if you have a sense of that, then you can count yourself as one of these buff doggies on the
left, instead of the doies on the right here. Now, in the next lecture, we're actually going to go
to recurrent neural nets, LSTMs, and all the other variants of Arnas. And we're going to start to
complexify the architecture and start to achieve better log likelihoods. And so I'm really looking
forward to that. And I'll see you then.