Hi everyone. Today we are continuing our implementation of Makemore, our favorite
character level language model. Now you'll notice that the background behind me is different,
that's because I am in Kyoto and it is awesome. So I'm in a hotel room here.
Now over the last few lectures we've built up to this architecture that is a multi-layer
perceptron character level language model. So we see that it receives three previous characters
and tries to predict the fourth character in a sequence using a very simple multi-layer perceptron
using one hidden layer of neurons with tenational nearities. So what we'd like to do now in this
lecture is I'd like to complexify this architecture. In particular we would like to take more characters
in a sequence as an input, not just three. And in addition to that we don't just want to feed them
all into a single hidden layer because that squashes too much information too quickly. Instead we would
like to make a deeper model that progressively fuses this information to make its guess about
the next character in a sequence. And so we'll see that as we make this architecture more complex
we're actually going to arrive at something that looks very much like a weight net.
So weight net is this paper published by Define in 2016 and it is also a language model basically
but a try to predict audio sequences instead of character level sequences or word level sequences.
But fundamentally the modeling setup is identical. It is an autoregressive model
and it tries to predict the next character in a sequence and the architecture actually takes
this interesting hierarchical sort of approach to predicting the next character in a sequence
with this tree-like structure. And this is the architecture and we're going to implement it
in the course of this video. So let's get started. So the story code for part five is very similar
to where we ended up in part three. Recall that part four was the manual dot replication exercise
that is kind of an aside. So we are coming back to part three, copy-pasting chunks out of it
and that is our starter code for part five. I've changed very few things otherwise.
So a lot of this should look familiar to if you've gone through part three. So in particular,
very briefly we are doing imports, we are reading our data set of words and we are processing the
data set of words into individual examples and none of this data generation code has changed.
And basically we have lots and lots of examples. In particular, we have 182,000 examples of three
characters trying to predict the fourth one. And we've broken up every one of these words into
little problems of giving three characters predict the fourth one. So this is our data set and this
is where we're trying to get the neural lab to do. Now in part three, we started to develop our code
around these layer modules that are, for example, a class linear. And we're doing this because we
want to think of these modules as building blocks and like a Lego building block bricks that we can
sort of like stack up into neural networks. And we can feed data between these layers and stack
them up into sort of graphs. Now we also developed these layers to have APIs and signatures very
similar to those that are found in PyTorch. So we have Torched.nn and it's got all these layer
building blocks that you would use in practice. And we were developing all of these to mimic
APIs of these. So for example, we have linear. So there will also be a Torched.nn.linear
and its signature will be very similar to our signature. And the functionality will be also
quite identical as far as I'm aware. So we had the linear layer with the Batchroom 1D layer
and the 10H layer that we developed previously. And linear just does a matrix multiply in the
forward pass of this module. Batchroom, of course, is this crazy layer that we developed in the previous
lecture. And what's crazy about it is, well, there's many things. Number one, it has these running
mean and variances that are trained outside of back propagation. We are trained using exponential
moving average inside this layer when we called forward pass. In addition to that,
there's this training plug because the behavior of Batchroom is different during train time
and evaluation time. And so suddenly we have to be very careful that Batchroom is in its correct
state, that it's in the evaluation state or training state. So that's something to now keep track of
something that sometimes introduces bugs because you forget to put it into the right mode.
And finally, we saw that Batchroom couples the statistics or the activations across the examples
in the batch. So normally we thought of the batch as just an efficiency thing. But now we are
coupling the computation across batch elements. And it's done for the purposes of controlling
the activation statistics as we saw in the previous video. So it's a very weird layer,
at least a lot of bugs. Partly, for example, because you have to modulate the training in
eval phase and so on. In addition, for example, you have to wait for the mean and variance to
settle and to actually reach a steady state. And so you have to make sure that you basically
there's state in this layer and state is harmful, usually. Now, I brought out the generator object.
Previously, we had a generator equals g and so on inside these layers. I've discarded that in favor
of just initializing the torch RNG outside here just once globally, just for simplicity.
And then here we are starting to build out some of the neural elements. This should look very
familiar. We are we have our embedding table C, and then we have a list of players. And it's a
linear feeds to batch or feeds to 10H. And then a linear output layer and its weights are scaled
down. So we are not confidently wrong at initialization. We see that this is about 12,000 parameters.
We're telling pators that the parameters require gradients. The optimization is as far as I'm
aware, identical and should look very, very familiar. Nothing changed here. Last function looks very
crazy. We should probably fix this. And that's because 32 batch elements are too few. And so you
can get very lucky, lucky or unlucky in any one of these batches, and it creates a very thick
loss function. So we're going to fix that soon. Now, once we want to evaluate the trained neural
network, we need to remember because of the batch from layers to set all the layers to be training
equals false. So this only matters for the batch from layer so far. And then we evaluate.
We see that currently we have validation loss of 2.10, which is fairly good, but there's still
ways to go. But even at 2.10, we see that when we sample from the model, we actually get relatively
name like results that do not exist in a training set. So for example, a von, kilo, a pros, a liar,
etc. So certainly not reasonable, not unreasonable, I would say, but not amazing. And we can still
push this validation loss even lower and get much better samples that are even more name like.
So let's improve this model. Okay, first, let's fix this graph because it is daggers in my eyes,
and I just can't take it anymore. So last I, if you recall, is a Python list of floats. So for
example, the first 10 elements look like this. Now what we'd like to do basically is we need to
average up some of these values to get a more sort of representative value along the way. So one
way to do this is to follow him in pytorch. If I create, for example, a tensor of the first 10
numbers, then this is currently a one dimensional array. But recall that I can view this array
as two dimensional. So for example, I can view it as a two by five array. And this is a 2D tensor
now, two by five. And you see what pytorch has done is that the first row of this tensor is the
first five elements. And the second row is the second five elements. I can also view it as a
five by two as an example. And then recall that I can also use negative one in place of one of
these numbers in pytorch will calculate what that number must be in order to make the number
of elements work out. So this can be this or like that, both will work. Of course, this would not work.
Okay, so this allows it to spread out some of the consecutive values into rows. So that's very
helpful because what we can do now is first of all, we're going to create a torch.tensor
out of the list of floats. And then we're going to view it as whatever it is, but we're going to
stretch it out into rows of 1000 consecutive elements. So the shape of this now becomes 200 by 1000.
And each row is 1000 consecutive elements in this list. So that's very helpful because now we can do
a mean along the rows. And the shape of this will just be 200. And so we've taken basically the mean
on every row. So PLT dot plot of that should be something nicer. Much better. So we see that we've
basically made a live progress. And then here, this is the learning rate decay. So here we see that
the learning rate decay subtracted a ton of energy out of the system and allowed us to settle into
the local minimum in this optimization. So this is a much nicer plot. Let me come up and delete the
monster. And we're going to be using this going forward. Now next up, what I'm bothered by is that
you see our forward pass is a little bit gnarly and takes away too many lines of code. So in
particular, we see that we've organized some of the layers inside the layers list, but not all of them
for no reason. So in particular, we see that we still have the embedding table special case
outside of the layers. And in addition to that, the viewing operation here is also outside of our
layers. So let's create layers for these. And then we can add those layers to just our list.
So in particular, the two things that we need is here, we have this embedding table. And we are
indexing at the integers inside the batch exp inside the tensor exp. So that's an embedding table
lookup just done with indexing. And then here we see that we have this view operation, which if
you recall from the previous video, simply rearranges the character embeddings and stretches them out
into row. And effectively, what Bernat does is the concatenation operation, basically,
except it's free because viewing is very cheap in PyTorch. And no memory is being copied.
We're just re-representing how we view that tensor. So let's create
modules for both of these operations, the embedding operation and the flattening operation.
So I actually wrote the code in just to save some time. So we have a module embedding and a module
flatten. And both of them simply do the indexing operation in a forward pass and the flattening
operation here. And this C now will just become a soft dot wait inside an embedding module.
And I'm calling these layers specifically embedding and flatten because it turns out that both of
them actually exist in PyTorch. So in PyTorch, we have an end-out embedding. And it also takes
the number of embeddings and the dimensionality of the embedding, just like we have here. But in
addition PyTorch takes a lot of other keyword arguments that we are not using for our purposes
yet. And for flatten, that also exists in PyTorch. And it also takes additional keyword arguments
that we are not using. So we have a very simple flatten. But both of them exist in PyTorch
they're just a bit more simpler. And now that we have these, we can simply take out some of these
special case things. So instead of C, we're just going to have an embedding and have a look up size
and N embed. And then after the embedding, we are going to flatten. So let's construct those modules
and now I can take out this C. And here I don't have to special case it anymore because now C
is the embedding's weight and it's inside layers. So this should just work. And then here our
forward pass simplifies substantially because we don't need to do these now outside of these layer
outside and explicitly. They're now inside layers. So we can delete those. But now to kick things off,
we want this little x which in the beginning is just xb. The tensor of integers specifying the
identities of these characters at the input. And so these characters can now directly feed into
the first layer and this should just work. So let me come here and insert a break because I just
want to make sure that the first iteration of this runs and that there's no mistake. So that
ran properly. And basically we've substantially simplified the forward pass here. Okay, I'm sorry,
I changed my microphone. So hopefully the audio is a little bit better. Now one more thing that I
would like to do in order to pytorchify our code even further is that right now we are maintaining
all of our modules in a naked list of layers. And we can also simplify this because we can
introduce the concept of pytorch containers. So in torch dot and then which we are basically
rebuilding from scratch here, there's a concept of containers. And these containers are basically
a way of organizing layers into lists or dicks and so on. So in particular, there's a sequential
which maintains a list of layers and is a module class in pytorch. And it basically just passes
a given input through all the layers sequentially exactly as we are doing here. So let's write our
own sequential, I've written a code here. And basically the code for sequential is quite straightforward.
We pass in a list of layers, which we keep here, and then given any input in a forward pass,
we just call all the layers sequentially and return the result. In terms of the parameters,
it's just all the parameters of the child modules. So we can run this and we can again simplify
this substantially, because we don't maintain this naked list of layers, we now have a notion of a
model, which is a module. And in particular, is a sequential of all the layers. And now parameters
are simply just a model of parameters. And so that list comprehension now lives here.
And then here we are, press here we are doing all the things we used to do.
Now here, the code again simplifies substantially, because we don't have to do this forwarding here,
instead of just call the model on the input data. And the input data here are the integers inside
XB. So we can simply do logits, which are the outputs of our model, are simply the model called
on XB. And then the cross entropy here takes the logits and the targets. So this simplifies
substantially. And then this looks good. So let's just make sure this runs, that looks good.
Now here, we actually have some work to do still here, but I'm going to come back later. For now,
there's no more layers, there's a model that layers, but it's not a to access attributes of
these classes directly. So we'll come back and fix this later. And then here, of course,
this simplifies substantially as well, because logits are the model called on X.
And then these logits come here. So we can evaluate the train evaluation loss,
which currently is terrible, because we just initialized it in your own let. And then we can
also sample from the model. And this simplifies dramatically as well, because we just want to call
the model on to the context and outcome logits. And then these logits go into softmax and get the
probabilities, etc. So we can sample from this model. What did I screw up? Okay, so I fixed the
issue, and we now get the result that we expect, which is gibberish, because the model is not trained
because we reinitialize it from scratch. The problem was that when I fixed this cell to be
modeled out layers instead of just layers, I did not actually run the cell. And so our neural
net was in a training mode. And what caused the issue here is the batch room layer, as a batch
room layer often likes to do, because batch room was in the training mode. And here we are passing
in an input, which is a batch of just a single example made up of the context. And so if you are
trying to pass in a single example into a batch norm that is in the training mode, you're going to
end up estimating the variance using the input. And the variance of a single number is not a number,
because it is a measure of a spread. So for example, the variance of just a single number five,
you can see is not a number. And so that's what happened. And the batch room basically caused an
issue. And then that polluted all of the further processing. So all that we had to do was make
sure that this runs. And we basically made the issue of, again, we didn't actually see the issue
with the loss. We could have evaluated the loss, but we got the wrong result, because batch norm
was in the training mode. And so we still get a result is just the wrong result, because it's
using the sample statistics of the batch, whereas we want to use the running mean and running variance
inside the batch drawer. And so, again, an example of introducing a bug in line, because we did not
properly maintain the state of what is training or not. Okay, so I we're in everything. And here's
what we are. As a reminder, we have the training loss of 2.05 and validation 2.10. Now, because
these losses are very similar to each other, we have a sense that we are not overfitting too much
on this task. And we can make additional progress in our performance by scaling up the size of the
neural network and making everything bigger and deeper. Now, currently, we are using this architecture
here, where we are taking in some number of characters going into a single hidden layer,
and then going to the prediction of the next character. The problem here is we don't have
in the deep way of making this bigger in a productive way. We could, of course, use our layers,
sort of building blocks and materials to introduce additional layers here and make the network
deeper. But it is still the case that we are crushing all of the characters into a single
layer all the way at the beginning. And even if we make this a bigger layer and add neurons,
it's still kind of like silly to squash all that information so fast in a single step.
So what we'd like to do instead is we'd like our network to look a lot more like this in the
WaveNet case. So you see in the WaveNet, when we are trying to make the prediction for the next
character in a sequence, it is a function of the previous characters that feed in, but not
all of these different characters are not just crushed to a single layer, and then you have a
sandwich. They are crushed slowly. So in particular, we take two characters and we fuse them into
sort of like a diagram representation. And we do that for all these characters consecutively,
and then we take the diagrams and we fuse those into four characters all with chunks.
And then we fuse that again. And so we do that in this like tree-like, hierarchical manner.
So we fuse the information from the previous context slowly into the network as it gets deeper.
And so this is the kind of architecture that we want to implement. Now in the WaveNet case,
this is a visualization of a stack of dilated, causal convolution layers. And this makes it
sound very scary, but actually the idea is very simple. And the fact that it's a dilated,
causal convolution layer is really just an implementation detail to make everything fast.
We're going to see that later. But for now, let's just keep the basic idea of it,
which is this progressive fusion. So we want to make the network deeper, and at each level,
we want to fuse only two consecutive elements, two characters, then two bi-grams, then two
four-grams, and so on. So let's implant this. Okay, so first up, let me scroll to where we built
the dataset, and let's change the block size from three to eight. So we're going to be taking
eight characters of context to predict the ninth character. So the dataset now looks like this.
We have a lot more context feeding in to predict any next character in a sequence.
And these eight characters are going to be processed in this tree-like structure.
Now if we scroll here, everything here should just be able to work. So we should be able to
redefine the network. You see that the number of parameters has increased by 10,000, and that's
because the block size has grown. So this first linear layer is much, much bigger. Our linear
layer now takes eight characters into this middle layer. So there's a lot more parameters there.
But this should just run. Let me just break right after the very first iteration. So you see that
this runs just fine. It's just that this network doesn't make too much sense. We're crushing way
too much information way too fast. So let's now come in and see how we could try to
implement the hierarchical scheme. Now before we dive into the detail of the
re-implementation here, I was just curious to actually run it and see where we are in terms of the
baseline performance of just lazily scaling up the context length. So I'll let it run,
we get a nice loss curve, and then evaluating the loss, we actually see quite a bit of improvement
just from increasing the context length. So I started a little bit of a performance log here,
and previously where we were is we were getting performance of 2.10 on the validation loss.
And now simply scaling up the context length from 3 to 8 gives us a performance of 2.02.
So quite a bit of an improvement here. And also when you sample from the model, you see that the
names are definitely improving qualitatively as well. So we could of course spend a lot of time
here tuning things and making it even bigger and scaling up an network further, even with this simple
sort of setup here. But let's continue and let's implement here our model and treat this as just
a rough baseline performance. But there's a lot of optimization like left on the table in terms of
some of the hyper parameters that you're hopefully getting a sense of now. Okay, so let's scroll up now
and come back up. And what I've done here is I've created a bit of a scratch space for us to just
like look at the forward pass of the neural net and inspect the shape of the tensor along the way
as the neural net forwards. So here, I'm just temporarily for debugging, creating a batch of just say,
for examples. So for random integers, then I'm plucking out those rows from our training set.
And then I'm passing into the model the input XP. Now the shape of XP here, because we have only
four examples is four by eight. And this eight is now the current block size. So inspecting XP,
we just see that we have four examples. Each one of them is a row of XP. And we have eight
characters here. And this integer tensor just contains the identities of those characters.
So the first layer of our neural net is the embedding layer. So passing XP, this integer tensor
through the embedding layer creates an output that is four by eight by 10. So our embedding table
has for each character a 10 dimensional vector that we are trying to learn. And so with the
embedding layer does here is it plucks out the embedding vector for each one of these integers
and organizes it all in a four by eight by 10 tensor now. So all of these integers are
translated into 10 dimensional vectors inside this three dimensional tensor now. Now passing
that through the flatten layer, as you recall, what this does is it views this tensor as just a four
by eight tensor. And what that effectively does is that all these 10 dimensional embeddings for
all these eight characters just end up being stretched out into a long row. And that looks
kind of like a concatenation operation, basically. So by viewing the tensor differently, we now have
a four by 80. And inside this 80, it's all the 10 dimensional vectors just concatenating next to
each other. And the linear layer, of course, takes 80 and creates 200 channels just via matrix
multiplication. So so far, so good. Now I'd like to show you something surprising. Let's look at the
insights of the linear layer and remind ourselves how it works. The linear layer here in the
forward pass takes the input X multiplies it with a weight and then optionally adds bias.
And the weight here is two dimensional as defined here. And the bias is one dimensional here.
So effectively, in terms of the shapes involved, what's happening inside this linear layer looks
like this right now. And I'm using random numbers here, but I'm just illustrating the shapes and
what happens. Basically, a four by 80 input comes into the linear layer. It's multiplied by this
80 by 200 weight matrix inside. And there's a plus 200 bias. And the shape of the whole thing that
comes out of the linear layer is four by 200, as we see here. Now notice here, by the way, that this
here will create a four by 200 tensor and then plus 200, there's a broadcasting happening here,
but four by 200 broadcasts with 200. So everything works here. So now the surprising thing that I'd
like to show you that you may not expect is that this input here that is being multiplied,
doesn't actually have to be two dimensional. This matrix multiply operator and pie torch is
quite powerful. And in fact, you can actually pass in higher dimensional arrays or tensors and
everything works fine. So for example, this could be four by five by 80. And the result in that case
will become four by five by 200. You can add as many dimensions as you like on the left here.
And so effectively, what's happening is that the matrix multiplication only works on the last
dimension. And the dimensions before it in the input tensor are left unchanged.
So that is basically these, these dimensions on the left are all treated as just a batch dimension.
So we can have multiple batch dimensions. And then in parallel over all those dimensions,
we are doing the matrix multiplication on the last dimension. So this is quite convenient because
we can use that in our network now, because remember that we have these eight characters coming in.
And we don't want to now flatten all of it out into a large eight dimensional vector,
because we don't want to matrix multiply 80 into a weight matrix multiply immediately.
Instead, we want to group these like this. So every consecutive two elements, one, two, and three,
and four, and five, and six, and seven, and eight, all of these should be now basically flattened out
and multiplied by a weight matrix. But all of these four groups here, we'd like to process in parallel.
So it's kind of like a batch dimension that we can introduce. And then we can in parallel,
basically process all of these, uh, bygram groups in the four batch dimensions of an individual
example, and also over the actual batch dimension of the, you know, four examples in our example here.
So let's see how that works. Effectively, what we want is right now, we take a four by 80 and
multiply by 80 by 200 to in the linear layer. This is what happens. But instead of what we want is
we don't want 80 characters or 80 numbers to come in. We only want two characters to come in on the
very first layer. And those two characters should be fused. So in other words, we just want 20 to come
in, right? 20 numbers would come in. And here we don't want a four by 80 to feed into the linear
layer. We actually want these groups of two to feed in. So instead of four by 80, we want this to be a
four by four by 20. So these are the four groups of two, and each one of them is 10 dimensional
vector. So what we want is now is we need to change the flatten layer. So it doesn't output a
four by 80, but it outputs a four by four by 20, where basically these, um, every two consecutive
characters are packed in on the very last dimension. And then these four is the first batch dimension.
And this four is the second batch dimension referring to the four groups inside everyone of
these examples. And then this will just multiply like this. So this is what we want to get to.
So we're going to have to change the linear layer in terms of how many inputs it expects. It shouldn't
expect 80. It should just expect 20 numbers. And we have to change our flatten layer. So it
doesn't just fully flatten out this entire example. It needs to create a four by four by 20,
instead of a four by 80. So let's see how this could be implemented. Basically, right now we have
an input that is a four by eight by 10, that feeds into the flatten layer. And currently,
the flatten layer just stretches it out. So if you remember the implementation of flatten,
it takes our X and it just views it as whatever the batch dimension is, and then negative one.
So effectively, what it does right now is it does ew of four, negative one, and the shape of this,
of course, is four by eight. So that's what currently happens. And we instead want this to be a four
by four by 20, where these consecutive 10 dimensional vectors get concatenated. So you know how when
Python, you can take a list of range of 10. So we have numbers from zero to nine. And we can index
like this to get all the even parts. And we can also index like starting at one and going in steps
up to get all the odd parts. So one way to implement this, it would be as follows, we can take E,
and we can index into it for all the batch elements, and then just even elements in this
dimension. So at index zero, two, four, and eight. And then all the parts here from this last dimension.
And this gives us the even characters. And then here, this gives us all the odd characters.
And basically, what we want to do is we make sure we want to make sure that these get concatenated
impact work. And then we want to concatenate these two tensors along the second dimension.
So this and the shape of it would be four by four by 20. This is definitely the result we want.
We are explicitly grabbing the even parts and the odd parts. And we're arranging those four by four
by 10, right next to each other, and concatenate. So this works. But it turns out that what also works
is you can simply use a view again, and just request the right shape. And it just so happens
that in this case, those vectors will again end up being arranged in exactly the way we want.
So in particular, if we take E, and we just view it as a four by four by 20, which is what we want.
We can check that this is exactly equal to what let me call this, this is the explicit
concatenation, I suppose. So explicit dot shape is four by four by 20. If you just view it as
four by four by 20, you can check that when you compare it to explicit, you get a bit.
This is element wise operation. So making sure that all of them are true,
if that is the true. So basically long story short, we don't need to make an explicit call to
concatenate, etc. We can simply take this input tensor to flatten, and we can just view it in
whatever way we want. And in particular, we don't want to stretch things out with negative one.
We want to actually create a three dimensional array. And depending on how many vectors that
are consecutive, we want to fuse, like for example, two, then we can just simply ask for this the
measure to be 20. And using negative one here, and pytorch will figure out how many groups it needs
to pack into this additional batch dimension. So let's now go into flatten and implement this.
Okay, so I scroll up here to flatten. And what we'd like to do is we'd like to change it now.
So let me create a constructor and take the number of elements that are consecutive that we would
like to concatenate now in the last dimension of the output. So here, we're just going to remember
cell data and equals n. And then I want to be careful here, because pytorch actually has a
torched up flatten. And its keyword arguments are different. And they kind of like function
differently. So our flatten is going to start to depart from pytorch flatten. So let me call it
flat flatten consecutive or something like that, just to make sure that our APIs are about equal.
So this basically flattens only some and consecutive elements and puts them into the last dimension.
Now here, the shape of X is B by T by C. So let me pop those out into variables and recall that
in our example down below, B was four, T was eight, and C was 10. Now instead of doing X dot view of
B by negative one, right, this is what we had before. We want this to be B by negative one by
and basically here, we want C times n. That's how many consecutive elements we want.
And here instead of negative one, I don't super love to use up negative one, because
I like to be very explicit so that you get error messages when things don't go according to your
expectation. So what do we expect here? We expect this to become T divide and using integer division
here. So that's what I expect to happen. And then one more thing I want to do here is remember
previously, all the way in the beginning, n was three, and basically we're concatenating
all the three characters that existed there. So we basically concatenated everything.
And so sometimes that can create a spurious dimension of one here. So if it is the case that X dot
shape at one is one, then it's kind of like a spurious dimension. So we don't want to return a
three dimensional tensor with a one here, we just want to return a two dimensional tensor exactly as
we did before. So in this case, basically, we will just say X equals X dot squeeze. That is a
pytorch function. And squeeze takes a dimension that it either squeezes out all the dimensions of
a tensor that are one, or you can specify the exact dimension that you want to be squeezed.
And again, I like to be as explicit as possible always. So I expect to squeeze out the first dimension
only of this tensor, this three dimensional tensor. And if this dimension here is one,
then I just want to return B by C times n. And so self dot out will be X, and then we return self
dot out. So that's the candidate implementation. And of course, this should be self dot in instead
of just n. So let's run. And let's come here now, and take it for a spin. So flatten consecutive.
And in the beginning, let's just use eight. So this should recover the previous behavior. So
flatten consecutive of eight, which is the current block size. You can do this. That should recover
the previous behavior. So we should be able to run the model. And here we can inspect, I have a
or code snippet here, or I iterate over all the layers, I print the name of this class and the
shape. And so we see the shapes as we expect them after every single layer and it's output.
So now let's try to restructure it using our flatten consecutive and do it heroically. So in
particular, we want to flatten consecutive, not just not block size, but just to. And then we want
to process this with linear. Now, then the number of inputs to this linear will not be an embed
times block size. It will now only be an embed times two, 20. This goes through the first layer.
And now we can in principle, just copy paste this. Now the next linear layer should expect
and hidden times two. And the last piece of it should expect and hidden times two again.
So this is sort of like the naive version of it. So running this, we now have a much, much bigger
model. And we should be able to basically just forward the model. And now we can inspect the
numbers in between. So four by 20 was flatten consecutive, the link to four by four by 20.
This was projected into four by four by 200. And then bash arm just worked out of the box. And we
have to verify that bash arm does the correct thing, even though it takes a three dimensional
impedance that have two dimensional input. Then we have 10 H, which is element wise,
then we crushed it again. So flatten consecutively and ended up with a four by two by four hundred now.
Then linear brought it back down to 200, bash arm 10 H. And lastly, we get a four by 400. And we
see that the flatten consecutive for the last flatten here, it squeezed out that dimension of one.
So we only ended up with four by 400. And then linear bash arm 10 H and the last linear layer
to get our logits. And so the logits end up in the same shape as they were before. But now we
actually have a nice three layer neural net. And it basically corresponds to, whoops, sorry,
it basically corresponds exactly to this network now, except only this piece here,
because we only have three layers. Whereas here in this example, there's four layers
with a total receptive field size of 16 characters instead of just eight characters.
So the block size here is 16. So this piece of it is basically implemented here.
Now we just have to kind of figure out some good channel numbers to use here. Now in particular,
I changed the number of hidden units to be 68 in this architecture, because when I use 68,
the number of parameters comes out to be 22,000. So that's exactly the same that we had before.
And we have the same amount of capacity at this neural net in terms of the number of parameters.
But the question is whether we are utilizing those parameters in a more efficient architecture.
So what I did then is I got rid of a lot of the debugging cells here, and I rewind the optimization
and scrolling down to the result. We see that we get the identical performance roughly. So our
validation loss now is 2.029, and previously it was 2.027. So controlling for the number of parameters,
changing from the flat to here, or it was not giving us anything yet. That said, there are two things
to point out. Number one, we didn't really torture the architecture here very much. This is just my
first guess. And there's a bunch of hyperparameters searched that we could do in order in terms of
how we allocate our budget of parameters to what layers. Number two, we still may have a bug inside
the Bashram 1D layer. So let's take a look at that, because it runs, but does it do the right thing.
So I pulled up the layer inspector sort of that we have here, and printed out the shape
along the way. And currently it looks like the Bashram is receiving an input that is 32 by 4 by 68.
And here on the right, I have the current implementation of Bashram that we have right now.
Now this Bashram assumed in the way we wrote it, and at the time that X is two-dimensional.
So it was n by d, where n was the batch size. So that's why we only reduced the mean and
variance over the 0th dimension. But now X will basically become three-dimensional.
So what's happening inside the Bashram layer right now, and how come it's working at all,
and not giving any errors? The reason for that is basically because everything broadcasts
properly, but the Bashram is not doing what we wanted to do. So in particular, let's basically
think through what's happening inside the Bashram, looking at what's happening here.
I have the code here. So we're receiving an input of 32 by 4 by 68. And then we are doing
here, X dot mean, here I have E instead of X. But we're doing the mean over 0. And that's
actually given us one by four by 68. So we're doing the mean only over the very first dimension.
And it's given us a mean and a variance that still maintain this dimension here. So these
means are only taken over 32 numbers in the first dimension. And then when we perform this,
everything broadcasts correctly still. But basically what ends up happening is
when we also look at the running mean,
the shape of it. So I'm looking at the model that layers that's ready, which is the first
Bashram layer, and then looking at whatever the running mean became, and its shape.
The shape of this running mean now is one by four by 68. Right? Instead of it being,
you know, just size of dimension, because we have 68 channels, we expect to have 68 means
and variances that we're maintaining. But actually, we have an array of four by 68.
And so basically what this is telling us is this Bashram is only,
this Bashram is currently working in parallel over four times 68, instead of just 68 channels.
So basically we are maintaining statistics for every one of these four positions individually
and independently. And instead what we want to do is we want to treat this four as a Bash dimension
just like the zero dimension. So as far as the Bashram is concerned, it doesn't want to average,
we don't want to average over 32 numbers, we want to now average over 32 times four numbers
for every single one of these 68 channels. And so let me now remove this. It turns out that when
you look at the documentation of torch dot mean, so let's go to torch dot mean.
In one of its signatures, when we specify the dimension, we see that the dimension here is not
just it can be in or it can also be a tuple of ints. So we can reduce over multiple integers at
the same time over multiple dimensions at the same time. So instead of just reducing over zero,
we can pass in a tuple 01. And here 01 as well. And then what's going to happen is the output,
of course, is going to be the same. But now what's going to happen is because we reduce over 0 and 1,
if we look at in that shape, we see that now we've reduced, we took the mean over both the
zero and the first dimension. So we're just getting 68 numbers and a bunch of spurious
dimensions here. So now this becomes one by one by 68. And the running mean and the running
variance analogously will become one by one by 68. So even though there are these spurious
dimensions, the current the current the correct thing will happen in that we are only maintaining
means and variances for 64, sorry, for 68 channels. And we're not calculating the mean
variance across 32 times four dimensions. So that's exactly what we want. And let's change the
implementation of batch number one D that we have, so that it can take in two dimensional or
three dimensional inputs and perform accordingly. So at the end of the day, the fix is relatively
straightforward. Basically, the dimension we want to reduce over is either zero or the tuple zero
and one, depending on the dimensionality of acts. So if x dot and dim is two, so it's a two-dimensional
tensor, then dimension we want to reduce over is just the integer zero. L of x dot and dim is
three. So it's a three dimensional tensor, then the dims, we're going to assume are zero and one
that we want to reduce over. And then here we just pass in dim. And if the dimensionality
of acts is anything else, we'll now get an error, which is good. So that should be the fix. Now,
I want to point out one more thing. We're actually departing from the API of PyTorch here a little
bit, because when you come to batch room on D PyTorch, you can scroll down and you can see that the
input to this layer can either be n by C, where n is the batch size and C is the number of features
or channels, or it actually does accept three dimensional inputs, but it expects it to be n by
C by L, where L is say like the sequence length or something like that. So this is a problem because
you see how C is nested here in the middle. And so when it gets three dimensional inputs,
this batch room layer will reduce over zero and two instead of zero and one. So basically,
PyTorch batch number one D layer assumes that C will always be the first dimension. Whereas we
assume here that C is the last dimension, and there are some number of batch dimensionals beforehand.
And so it expects n by C or n by C by L, we expect n by C or n by L by C.
And so it's a deviation. I think it's okay. I prefer it this way, honestly. So this is the way
that we will keep it for our purposes. So I redefined the layers, re-initialized the neural
nut, and did a single forward pass with a break just for one step. Looking at the shapes along the
way, they're, of course, identical. All the shapes are the same. By the way, we see that things are
actually working as we want them to now, is that when we look at the batch room layer,
the running mean shape is now one by one by 68. So we're only maintaining 68 means for every one of
our channels, and we're treating both the 0th and the first dimension as a batch dimension,
which is exactly what we want. So let me retrain the neural nut now. Okay, so I retrained in your
alert with the bug fix, we get a nice curve. And when we look at the validation performance,
we do actually see a slight improvement. So it went from 2.0 to 9 to 2.0 to 2. So basically,
the bug inside the batch room was holding us back like a little bit, it looks like.
And we are getting a tiny improvement now, but it's not clear if this is statistically significant.
And the reason we slightly expect an improvement is because we're not maintaining so many different
means and variances that are only estimated using using 32 numbers effectively. Now we are
estimating them using 32 times four numbers. So you just have a lot more numbers that go into any
one estimate of the mean and variance. And it allows things to be a bit more stable and less wiggly
inside those estimates of those statistics. So pretty nice. With this more general architecture
in place, we are now set up to push the performance further by increasing the size of the network.
So for example, I bumped up the number of embeddings to 24 instead of 10, and also increased number
of hidden units. But using the exact same architecture, we now have 76,000 parameters.
And the training takes a lot longer, but we do get a nice curve. And then when you actually
evaluate the performance, we are now getting validation performance of 1.993. So we've crossed
over the 2.0 sort of territory. And we're at about 1.99, but we are starting to have to
wait quite a bit longer. And we're a little bit in the dark with respect to the correct setting
of the hyper parameters here and the learning rates and so on, because the experiments are
starting to take longer to train. And so we are missing sort of like an experimental harness
on which we could run a number of experiments and really tune this architecture very well.
So I'd like to conclude now with a few notes. We basically improved our performance from a
starting of 2.1 down to 1.9. But I don't want that to be the focus because honestly, we're kind of
in the dark. We have no experimental harness. We're just guessing and checking. And this whole
thing is terrible. We're just looking at the training loss. Normally you want to look at both the
training and the validation loss together. The whole thing looks different if you're actually
trying to squeeze out numbers. That said, we did implement this architecture from the WaitNet paper,
but we did not implement this specific forward pass-off it where you have a more complicated
linear layer sort of that is this gated linear layer kind of. And there's residual connections
and skip connections and so on. So we did not implement that. We just implemented this structure.
I would like to briefly hint or preview how what we've done here relates to convolutional neural
networks as used in the WaitNet paper. And basically the use of convolutions is strictly for efficiency.
It doesn't actually change the model we've implemented. So here, for example, let me look at a specific
name to work with an example. So there's a name in our training set and it's DeAndre. And it has
seven letters. So that is eight independent examples in our model. So all these rows here are independent
examples of DeAndre. Now you can forward of course any one of these rows independently. So I can
take my model and call it on any individual index. Notice by the way here, I'm being a little bit
tricky. The reason for this is that extra at seven dot shape is just one dimensional array of eight.
So you can't actually call the model on it. You're going to get an error because there's no batch
dimension. So when you do extra at list of seven, then the shape of this becomes one by eight. So I get
an extra batch dimension of one, and then we can forward the model. So that forwards a single example.
And you might imagine that you actually may well know forward all of these eight at the same time.
So preallocating some memory and then doing a for loop H times and forwarding all of those eight
here will give us all the logits in all these different cases. Now for us with the model as
we've implemented it right now, this is eight independent calls to our model. But what convolutions
allow you to do is it allow you to basically slide this model efficiently over the input sequence.
And so this for loop can be done not outside in Python, but inside of kernels in CUDA. And so
this for loop gets hidden into the convolution. So the convolution basically you can cover this
it's a for loop applying a little linear filter over space of some input sequence. And in our case,
the space we're interested in is one dimensional, and we're interested in sliding these filters
over the input data. So this diagram actually is fairly good as well. Basically what we've done
is here they are highlighting in black one individual one single sort of like tree of this
calculation. So just calculating the single output example here. And so this is basically what we've
implemented here. We've implemented a single this black structure. We've implemented that and
calculated a single output like a single example. But what convolutions allow you to do is it
allows you to take this black structure and kind of like slide it over the input sequence
here and calculate all of these orange outputs at the same time. Or here that corresponds to
calculating all of these outputs of at all the positions of the Andra at the same time.
And the reason that this is much more efficient is because number one as I mentioned the for loop
is inside the CUDA kernels in the sliding. So that makes it efficient. But number two,
notice the variable reuse here. For example, if we look at this circle, this node here, this node
here is the right child of this node, but it's also the left child of the node here. And so basically
this node and its value is used twice. And so right now in this naive way, we'd have to recalculate it.
But here we are allowed to reuse it. So in the convolutional neural network, you think of these
linear layers that we have it up above as filters. And we take these filters and their linear filters
and you slide them over input sequence. And we calculate the first layer and then the second layer
and then third layer and then the output layer of the sandwich. And it's all done very efficiently
using these convolutions. So we're going to cover that in a future video. The second thing I hope
you took away from this video is you've seen me basically implement all of these layer
Lego building blocks or module building blocks. And I'm implementing them over here. And we've
implemented a number of layers together. And we've also implementing these containers. And we've
overall pytorchified our code quite a bit more. Now basically what we're doing here is we're
re-implementing Torched.nn, which is the neural networks library on top of Torched.tensor. And it
looks very much like this, except it is much better because it's in pytorch instead of a
jinkling my jinkling notebook. So I think going forward, I will probably have considered us having
unlocked Torched.nn. We understand roughly what's in there, how these modules work, how they're
nested, and what they're doing on top of Torched.tensor. So hopefully we'll just switch over and
continue and start using Torched.nn directly. The next thing I hope you got a bit of a sense of
is what the development process of building deep neural networks looks like, which I think was
relatively representative to some extent. So number one, we are spending a lot of time in the
documentation page of pytorch. And we're reading through all the layers, looking at the documentations,
where are the shapes of the inputs, what can they be, what does the layer do, and so on.
Unfortunately, I have to say the pytorch documentation is not very good. They spend a ton of time on
hardcore engineering of all kinds of distributed primitives, etc. But as far as I can tell,
no one is maintaining documentation. It will lie to you, it will be wrong, it will be incomplete,
it will be unclear. So unfortunately, it is what it is, and you just kind of do your best
with what they've given us. Number two, the other thing that I hope you got a sense of is
there's a ton of trying to make the shapes work. And there's a lot of gymnastics around these
multi-dimensional arrays. And are they two-dimensional, three-dimensional, four-dimensional? What layers
take what shapes? Is it NCL or NLC? And you're permuting and viewing, and it just can get pretty
messy. And so that brings me to number three. I very often prototype these layers and implementations
in Jupyter Notebooks and make sure that all the shapes work out. And I'm spending a lot of time,
basically, babysitting the shapes and making sure everything is correct. And then once I'm satisfied
with the functionality in a Jupyter Notebook, I will take that code and copy paste it into my
repository of actual code that I'm training with. And so then I'm working with VS code on a side.
So I usually have Jupyter Notebook and VS code. I develop in Jupyter Notebook, I paste into VS code,
and then I kick off experiments from the repo, of course, from the code repository.
So that's roughly some notes on the development process of working with neural ones.
Lastly, I think this lecture unlocks a lot of potential further lectures, because number one,
we have to convert our neural network to actually use these dilated causal convolutional layers
to implement in the comment. Number two, I potentially started to get into what this means,
where our residual connections and skip connections and why are they useful. Number three, as I mentioned,
we don't have any experimental harness. So right now I'm just guessing, checking everything.
This is not representative of typical deep learning workflows. You have to set up your
evaluation harness. You can kick off experiments. You have lots of arguments that your script can
take. You're kicking off a lot of experimentation. You're looking at a lot of plots of training
evaluation losses, and you're looking at what is working and what is not working.
And you're working on this population level, and you're doing all these hyperparameters searches.
And so we've done none of that so far. So how to set that up and how to make it good,
I think is a whole another topic. And number three, we should probably cover recurrent neural
networks, our NENS, LSTMs, grooves, and of course, transformers. So many places to go,
and we'll cover that in the future. For now, sorry, I forgot to say that. If you are interested,
I think it is kind of interesting to try to beat this number 1.993, because I really haven't
tried a lot of experimentation here, and there's quite a bit of long-engue fruit potentially,
to still purchase further. So I haven't tried any other ways of allocating these channels in this
neural net. Maybe the number of dimensions for the embedding is all wrong. Maybe it's possible
to actually take the original network with just one-handed layer and make it big enough and
actually beat my fancy hierarchical network. It's not obvious. It'll be kind of embarrassing if this
did not do better, even once you torture it a little bit. Maybe you can read the weight net paper and
try to figure out how some of these layers work and implement them yourselves using what we have.
And of course, you can always tune some of the initialization or some of the optimization
and see if we can improve it that way. So I'd be curious if people can come up with some ways to
beat this and yeah that's it for now. Bye.