Hi everyone. So by now you have probably heard of chat GPT. It has taken the world and AI community
by storm and it is a system that allows you to interact with an AI and give it text-based tasks.
So for example, we can ask chat GPT to write us a small haiku about how important it is that people
understand AI and then they can use it to improve the world and make it more prosperous. So when we
run this, AI knowledge brings prosperity for all to see embraces power. Okay, not bad. And so you
could see that chat GPT went from left to right and generated all these words sequentially.
Now I asked it already the exact same prompt a little bit earlier and it generated a slightly
different outcome. AI's power to grow, ignore insults us back, learn, prosperity, weights.
So pretty good in both cases and slightly different. So you can see that chat GPT is a probabilistic
system and for any one prompt it can give us multiple answers sort of replying to it.
Now this is just one example of a prompt. People have come up with many, many examples and there
are entire websites that index interactions with chat GPT. And so many of them are quite humorous,
explain HTML to me like I'm a dog, write release notes for chess too, write a note about Elon Musk
buying a Twitter and so on. So as an example, please write a breaking news article about a leaf
falling from a tree and a shocking turn of events. A leaf has fallen from a tree in the local
park. Witnesses report that the leaf which was previously attached to a branch of a tree
detached itself and fell to the ground. Very dramatic. So you can see that this is a pretty
remarkable system and it is what we call a language model because it models the sequence of words
or characters or tokens more generally and it knows how sort of words follow each other in
English language. And so from its perspective what it is doing is it is completing the sequence.
So I give it the start of a sequence and it completes the sequence with the outcome.
And so it's a language model in that sense. Now I would like to focus on the under the hood of
under the hood components of what makes chat GPT work. So what is the neural network under the
hood that models the sequence of these words. And that comes from this paper called Attention is
All You Need. In 2017 a landmark paper a landmark paper in AI that proposed the transformer architecture.
So GPT is short for generatively pre-trained transformer. So transformer is the neural
nut that actually does all the heavy lifting under the hood. It comes from this paper in 2017.
Now if you read this paper this reads like a pretty random machine translation paper and that's
because I think the authors didn't fully anticipate the impact that the transformer would have on the
field. And this architecture that they produced in the context of machine translation in their case
actually ended up taking over the rest of AI in the next five years after. And so this architecture
with minor changes was copy-pasted into a huge amount of applications in AI in more recent years.
And that includes at the core of chat GPT. Now we are not going to what I'd like to do now is
I'd like to build out something like chat GPT. But we're not going to be able to of course
reproduce chat GPT. This is a very serious production grade system. It is trained on
a good chunk of internet. And then there's a lot of pre-training and fine-tuning stages to it.
And so it's very complicated. What I'd like to focus on is just to train a transformer based
language model. And in our case it's going to be a character level language model. I still think
that is a very educational with respect to how these systems work. So I don't want to train on
the chunk of internet. We need a smaller data set. In this case I propose that we work with my
favorite toy data set. It's called tiny Shakespeare. And what it is is basically it's a concatenation
of all of the works of Shakespeare in my understanding. And so this is all of Shakespeare in a single
file. This file is about one megabyte. And it's just all of Shakespeare. And what we are going to do
now is we're going to basically model how these characters follow each other. So for example,
given a chunk of these characters like this, given some context of characters in the past,
the transformer neural network will look at the characters that I've highlighted and it's going
to predict that G is likely to come next in the sequence. And it's going to do that because we're
going to train that transformer on Shakespeare. And it's just going to try to produce character
sequences that look like this. And in that process is going to model all the patterns inside this
data. So once we've trained the system, I just like to give you a preview, we can generate infinite
Shakespeare. And of course it's a fake thing that looks kind of like Shakespeare. Apologies for
there's some jank that I'm not able to resolve in here. But you can see how this is going character
by character. And it's kind of like predicting Shakespeare-like language. So verily my lord,
the sights have left the again, the king coming with my curses with precious pale. And then
Tranios says something else, etc. And this is just coming out of the transformer in a very similar
manner, as it would come out in chat GPT. In our case, character by character in chat GPT,
it's coming out on the token by token level. And tokens are these sort of like little subword
pieces. So they're not word level, they're kind of like work chunk level. And now I've already
written this entire code to train these transformers. And it is in a GitHub repository that you can
find. And it's called nano GPT. So nano GPT is a repository that you can find on my GitHub.
And it's a repository for training transformers on any given text. And what I think is interesting
about it, because there's many ways to train transformers, but this is a very simple implementation.
So it's just two files of 300 lines of code, each one file defiles the GPT model, the transformer,
and one file trains it on some given text data set. And here I'm showing that if you train it on
the open WebText data set, which is a fairly large data set of web pages, then I reproduce the
the performance of GPT two. So GPT two is an early version of open AI's GPT from 2017,
if I recall correctly. And I've only so far reproduced the smallest one 24 million parameter model.
But basically, this is just proving that the code base is correctly arranged. And I'm able to load
the neural network weights that open AI has released later. So you can take a look at the
finished code here in an GPT, but what I would like to do in this lecture is I would like to
basically write this repository from scratch. So we're going to begin with an empty file,
and we're going to define a transformer piece by piece. We're going to train it on the tiny
Shakespeare data set. And we'll see how we can then generate infinite Shakespeare. And of course,
this can copy paste to any arbitrary text data set that you like. But my goal really here is to
just make you understand and appreciate how under the chat GPT works. And really, all that's required
is a proficiency in Python, and some basic understanding of copula statistics. And it would help if you
also see my previous videos on the same YouTube channel, in particular, my Make More series,
where I define smaller and simpler neural network language models. So multi-lil perceptions and so
on, it really introduces the language modeling framework. And then here in this video, we're
going to focus on the transformer neural network itself. Okay, so I created a new Google collab
Jupyter notebook here. And this will allow me to later easily share this code that we're going to
develop together with you so you can follow along. So this will be in a video description later.
Now here, I've just done some preliminarys. I downloaded the data set, the tiny Shakespeare
data set at this URL. And you can see that it's about a one megabyte file. Then here, I open the
input dot txt file and just read in all the text of the string. And we see that we are working with
one million characters roughly. And the first 1000 characters, if we just print them out,
are basically what you would expect. This is the first 1000 characters of the tiny Shakespeare
data set roughly up to here. So so far, so good. Next, we're going to take this text. And the text
is a sequence of characters in Python. So when I call the set constructor on it, I'm just going to
get the set of all the characters that occur in this text. And then I call list on that to create
a list of those characters instead of just a set so that I have an ordering an arbitrary
ordering. And then I sort that. So basically, we get just all the characters that occur in the
entire data set and they're sorted. Now the number of them is going to be our vocabulary size. These
are the possible elements of our sequences. And we see that when I print here, the characters,
there's 65 of them in total. There's a space character, and then all kinds of special characters.
And then capitals and lowercase letters. So that's our vocabulary. And that's the sort of like
possible characters that the model can see or emit. Okay, so next, we would like to develop some
strategy to tokenize the input text. Now, when people say tokenize, they mean convert the raw
text as a string to some sequence of integers, according to some note, according to some vocabulary
of possible elements. So as an example, here, we are going to be building a character level
language model. So we're simply going to be translating individual characters into integers.
So let me show you a chunk of code that sort of does that for us. So we're building both the
encoder and the decoder. And let me just talk through what's happening here. When we encode an
arbitrary text, like hi there, we're going to receive a list of integers that represents that
string. So for example, 46 47, etc. And then we also have the reverse mapping. So we can take
this list and decode it to get back the exact same string. So it's really just like a translation
to integers and back for arbitrary string. And for us, it is done on a character level.
Now the way this was achieved is we just iterate over all the characters here and create a lookup
table from the character to the integer and vice versa. And then to encode some string,
we simply translate all the characters individually and to decode it back, we use the reverse mapping
and concatenate all of it. Now this is only one of many possible encodings or many possible sort
of tokenizers. And it's a very simple one. But there's many other schemas that people have come up with
in practice. So for example, Google uses a sentence piece. So sentence piece will also encode text into
integers, but in a different schema, and using a different vocabulary. And sentence piece is a
sub word sort of tokenizer. And what that means is that you're not encoding entire words, but you're
not also encoding individual characters. It's it's a sub word unit level. And that's usually what's
adopted in practice. For example, also OpenAI has this library called tick token that uses a
byte pair encoding tokenizer. And that's what GPT uses. And you can also just encode words into
like hell world into lists of integers. So as an example, I'm using the tick token library here.
I'm getting the encoding from GPT two, or that was used for GPT two, instead of just having 65
possible characters or tokens, they have 50,000 tokens. And so when they encode the exact same
string, hi there, we only get a list of three integers. But those integers are not between zero
and 64, they are between zero and 5000 50,256. So basically, you can trade off the codebook size
and the sequence lengths. So you can have very long sequences of integers with very small
vocabularies, or we can have short sequences of integers with very large vocabularies. And so
typically people use in practice these sub word encodings. But I'd like to keep our tokenizer very
simple. So we're using character level tokenizer. And that means that we have very small codebooks.
We have very simple encode and decode functions. But we do get very long sequences as a result.
But that's the level at which we're going to stick with this lecture, because it's the simplest
thing. Okay, so now that we have an encoder and a decoder, effectively tokenizer, we can
tokenize the entire training set of Shakespeare. So here's a chunk of code that does that.
And I'm going to start to use the pytorch library, and specifically the tork.tensor from the pytorch
library. So we're going to take all of the text in tiny Shakespeare, encode it, and then wrap it
into a torch.tensor to get the data tensor. So here's what the data tensor looks like when I look at
just the first 1000 characters or the 1000 elements of it. So we see that we have a massive sequence
of integers. And this sequence of integers here is basically an identical translation of the first
1000 characters here. So I believe, for example, that zero is a new line character. And maybe one
is a space, not 100% sure. But from now on, the entire data set of text is rerepresented as just
it just stretched out is a single very large sequence of integers. Let me do one more thing
before we move on here. I'd like to separate out our data set into a train and a validation split.
So in particular, we're going to take the first 90% of the data set and consider that to be the
training data for the transformer. And we're going to withhold the last 10% at the end of it
to be the validation data. And this will help us understand to what extent our model is overfitting.
So we're going to basically hide and keep the validation data on the side, because we don't
want just a perfect memorization of this exact Shakespeare, we want a neural network that sort of
creates Shakespeare like text. And so it should be fairly likely for it to produce the actual like
stowed away, true Shakespeare text. And so we're going to use this to get a sense of the overfitting.
Okay, so now we would like to start plugging these text sequences or integer sequences into
the transformer so that it can train and learn those patterns. Now, the important thing to realize
is we're never going to actually feed entire text into your transformer all at once. That
would be computationally very expensive and prohibitive. So when we actually train a
transformer on a lot of these data sets, we only work with chunks of the data set. And when we train
the transformer, we basically sample random little chunks out of the training set and train on
just chunks at a time. And these chunks have basically some kind of a length and some maximum length.
Now the maximum length typically, at least in the code, I usually write, is called block size.
You can you can find it on the different names, like context length or something like that.
Let's start with the block size of just eight. And let me look at the first train data characters.
The first block size plus one characters. I'll explain why plus one in a second.
So this is the first nine characters in the sequence in the training set.
Now what I'd like to point out is that when you sample a chunk of data like this,
so say if these nine characters out of the training set, this actually has multiple
examples packed into it. And that's because all of these characters follow each other.
And so what this thing is going to say when we plug it into a transformer is we're going to
actually simultaneously train it to make prediction at every one of these positions.
Now in the in a chunk of nine characters, there's actually eight individual examples packed in there.
So there's the example that when 18 when in the context of 18, 47 luckily comes next.
In a context of 18 and 47 56 comes next. In a context of 18, 47, 56, 57 can come next and so on.
So that's the eight individual examples. Let me actually spell it out with code.
So here's a chunk of code to illustrate. X are the inputs to the transformer.
It will just be the first block size characters. Y will be the next block size characters. So it's
offset by one. And that's because Y are the targets for each position in the input.
And then here I'm iterating over all the block size of eight. And the context is always all
the characters in X up to T and including T. And the target is always the teeth character,
but in the targets array Y. So let me just run this. And basically it spells out what I said in words.
These are the eight examples hidden in a chunk of nine characters that we sampled from the training
set. I want to mention one more thing. We train on all the eight examples here with context between
one all the way up to context of block size. And we train on that not just for computational
reasons because we happen to have the sequence already or something like that. It's not just
done for efficiency. It's also done to make the transformer network be used to seeing contexts
all the way from as little as one all the way to block size. And we'd like the transformer to be
used to seeing everything in between. And that's going to be useful later during inference because
while we're sampling, we can start to set sampling generation with as level as one character of context.
And the transformer knows how to predict next character with all the way up to just context of
one. And so then it can predict everything up to block size. And after block size, we have to start
truncating because the transformer will never receive more than block size inputs when it's
predicting the next character. Okay, so we've looked at the time dimension of the tensors that
are going to be feeding into the transformer. There's one more dimension to care about and that is the
batch dimension. And so as we're sampling these chunks of text, we're going to be actually, every
time we're going to feed them into a transformer, we're going to have many batches of multiple chunks
of text that are always like stacked up in a single tensor. And that's just done for efficiency,
just so that we can keep the GPUs busy, because they are very good at parallel processing of data.
And so we just want to process multiple chunks all at the same time. But those chunks are
processed completely independently. They don't talk to each other, and so on. So let me basically
just generalize this and introduce a batch dimension. Here's a chunk of code. Let me just run it, and
then I'm going to explain what it does. So here, because we're going to start sampling random
locations in the data sets to pull chunks from, I am setting the seed so that in the random number
generator, so that the numbers I see here are going to be the same numbers you see later,
if you try to reproduce this. Now the batch size here is how many independent sequences
we are processing every forward, backward pass of the transformer. The block size, as I explained,
is the maximum context length to make those predictions. So let's say by size four, block size eight,
and then here's how we get batch for any arbitrary split. If the split is a training split, then we're
going to look at train data, otherwise, and val data. That gives us the data array. And then
when I generate random positions to grab a chunk out of, I actually grab, I actually generate batch
size number of random offsets. So because this is four, we are, I X is going to be a four numbers
that are randomly generated between zero and len of data minus block size. So it's just random
offsets into the training set. And then X is, as I explained, are the first block size characters
starting at I, the Y's are the offset by one of that. So just add plus one. And then we're going to
get those chunks for every one of integers I in I X, and use a torch dot stack to take all those
one dimensional tensors as we saw here. And we're going to stack them up at rows. And so they all
become a row in a four by eight tensor. So here's where I'm printing them. When I sample a batch
XB and YB, the inputs the transformer now are the input X is the four by eight tensor, four
rows of eight columns. And each one of these is a chunk of the training set. And then the targets
here are in the associated array Y, and they will come in to the transformer all the way at the end
to create the loss function. So they will give us the correct answer for every single position
inside X. And then these are the four independent rows. So spelled out as we did before,
this four by eight array contains a total of 32 examples. And they're completely independent
as far as the transformer is concerned. So when the input is 24, the target is 43,
or rather 43 here in the Y array, when the input is 2443, the target is 58. When the input is 2443
58, the target is five, etc. Or like when it is a 5258 one, the target is 58.
Right. So you can sort of see this spelled out. These are the 32 independent examples
packed in to a single batch of the input X. And then the desired targets are in Y. And so now this
integer tensor of X is going to feed into the transformer. And that transformer is going to
simultaneously process all these examples, and then look up the correct integers to predict in
every one of these positions in the tensor Y. Okay, so now that we have our batch of input that we'd
like to feed into a transformer, let's start basically feeding this into neural networks.
Now we're going to start off with the simplest possible neural network, which in the case of
language modeling, in my opinion, is the by Graham language model. And we've covered the
by Graham language model in my make more series in a lot of depth. And so here I'm going to
sort of go faster and let's just implement PyTorch module directly that implements the
by Graham language model. So I'm importing the pytorch and in module for reproducibility.
And then here I'm constructing a by Graham language model, which is a subclass of an end module.
And then I'm calling it and I'm passing in the inputs and the targets. And I'm just printing.
Now when the inputs and targets come here, you see that I'm just taking the index,
the inputs X here, which I renamed to ID X. And I'm just passing them into this token embedding table.
So what's going on here is that here in the constructor, we are creating a token embedding table.
And it is of size vocab size by vocab size. And we're using an end up embedding, which is a
very thin wrapper around basically a tensor of shape vocab size by vocab size. And what's happening
here is that when we pass ID X here, every single integer in our input is going to refer to this
embedding table, and is going to block out a row of that embedding table corresponding to its index.
So 24 here, we'll go to the embedding table and we'll pluck out the 24th row. And then 43 will go
here and block out the 43rd row, etc. And then pytorch is going to arrange all of this into a
batch by time by channel tensor. In this case, batch is four, time is eight, and C, which is the
channels is vocab size or 65. And so we're just going to block out all those rows, arrange them in a
B by T by C. And now we're going to interpret this as the logits, which are basically the scores
for the next character in a sequence. And so what's happening here is we are predicting what
comes next based on just the individual identity of a single token. And you can do that because,
I mean, currently, the tokens are not talking to each other. And they're not seeing any context,
except for they're just seeing themselves. So I'm a fat, I'm a token number five. And then I can
actually make pretty decent predictions about what comes next just by knowing that I'm token five,
because some characters know, sir, follow other characters in technical scenarios. So we saw a
lot of this in a lot more depth in the make more series. And here if I just run this, then we currently
get the predictions, the scores, the logits for every one of the four by eight positions. Now that
we've made predictions about what comes next, we'd like to evaluate the loss function. And so in
make more series, we saw that a good way to measure a loss or like a quality of the predictions
is to use the negative log likelihood loss, which is also implemented in PyTorch under the name
cross entropy. So what we'd like to do here is loss is the cross entropy on the predictions
and the targets. And so this measures the quality of the logits with respect to the targets. In other
words, we have the identity of the next character. So how well are we predicting the next character
based on the logits? And intuitively, the correct, the correct dimension of logits,
depending on whatever the target is, should have a very high number. And all the other
dimensions should be very low number. Right? Now the issue is that this won't actually,
this is what we want. We want to basically output the logits and the loss.
This is what we want. But unfortunately, this won't actually run. We get an error message.
But intuitively, we want to measure this. Now, when we go to the PyTorch cross entropy
documentation here, we're trying to call the cross entropy in its functional form. So that
means we don't have to create like a module for it. But here, we go to the documentation.
You have to look into the details of how PyTorch expects these inputs. And basically, the issue
here is PyTorch expects, if you have multi dimensional input, which we do, because we have a B by T
by C tensor, then it actually really wants the channels to be the second dimension here. So if
so basically, it wants a B by C by T, instead of a B by T by C. And so it's just the details of how
PyTorch treats these kinds of inputs. And so we don't actually want to deal with that. So
what we're going to do is that is we need to basically reshape our logits. So here's what I
like to do. I like to take basically give names to the dimensions. So logits that shape is B by T
by C and unpack those numbers. And then let's say that logits equals logits dot view. And we want
it to be a B times C, B times T by C. So just a two dimensional array. Right, so we're going to take
all the, we're going to take all of these positions here, and we're going to stretch them out in a
one dimensional sequence, and preserve the channel dimension as the second dimension.
So we're just kind of like stretching out the array. So it's two dimensional. And in that case,
it's going to better conform to what PyTorch sort of expects in its dimensions. Now we have to do
the same two targets, because currently targets are of shape B by T. And we want it to be just B
times T. So one dimensional. Now, alternatively, you could always still just do minus one,
because PyTorch will guess what this should be if you want to lay it out. But let me just be
explicit and say few times T. Once we reshape this, it will match the cross entropy case.
And then we should be able to evaluate our loss. Okay, so at that right now, and we can
do loss. And so currently we see that the loss is 4.87. Now, because our, we have 65 possible
vocabulary elements, we can actually guess at what the loss should be. And in particular,
we covered negative log likelihood in a lot of detail, we are expecting log or long of
one over 65, and negative of that. So we're expecting the loss to be about 4.17. But we're
getting 4.87. And so that's telling us that the initial predictions are not super diffuse.
They've got a little bit of entropy. And so we're guessing wrong. So yes, but actually we are
able to evaluate the loss. Okay, so now that we can evaluate the quality of the model on some data,
we'd like to also be able to generate from the model. So let's do the generation. Now I'm going
to go again a little bit faster here, because I covered all this already in previous videos.
So here's a generate function for the model. So we take some, we take the same kind of input
IDX here. And basically, this is the current context of some characters in a batch, in some batch.
So it's also B by T. And the job of generate is to basically take this B by T and extend it to
be B by T plus one plus two plus three. And so it's just basically, it continues the generation
in all the batch dimensions in the time dimension. So that's its job. And we'll do that for max
new tokens. So you can see here on the bottom, there's going to be some stuff here. But on the
bottom, whatever is predicted is concatenated on top of the previous IDX along the first dimension,
which is the time dimension to create a B by T plus one. So that becomes a new IDX. So the job
of generate is to take a B by T and make it a B by T plus one plus two plus three, as many as we
want maximum tokens. So this is the generation from the model. Now inside the generation, what
are we doing? We're taking the current indices, we're getting the predictions. So we get those
are in the logits. And then the loss here is going to be ignored, because we're not, we're not
using that. And we have no targets that are sort of ground truth targets that we're going to be
comparing with. Then once we get the logits, we are only focusing on the last step. So instead
of a B by T by C, we're going to pluck out the negative one, the last element in the time dimension,
because those are the predictions for what comes next. So that gives us the logits,
which we then cover to probabilities via softmax. And then we use towards that multinomial to sample
from those probabilities. And we ask PyTorch to give us one sample. And so idx next will become a B by
one, because in each one of the batch dimensions, we're going to have a single prediction for what
comes next. So this num samples equals one, we'll make this be a one. And then we're going to take
those integers that come from the sampling process, according to the probability distribution given
here. And those integers can just concatenate it on top of the current sort of like running stream
of integers. And this gives us a P by T plus one. And then we can return that. Now one thing here is,
you see how I'm calling self of idx, which will end up going to the forward function. I'm not
providing any targets. So currently this would give an error because targets is sort of like not
given. So targets has to be optional. So targets is none by default. And then if targets is none,
then there's no loss to create. So it's just losses, none. But else, all of this happens,
and we can create a loss. So this will make it so if we have the targets, we provide them and get
a loss, if we have no targets, we'll just get the logits. So this here will generate from the model.
And let's take that for a ride now. Oops. So I have another coach on here, which will generate
for the model from the model. And okay, this is kind of crazy. So maybe let me let me break this
down. So these are the idx, right? I'm creating a batch will be just one time will be just one.
So I'm creating a little one by one tensor, and it's holding a zero. And the D type, the data type
is integer. So zero is going to be how we kick off the generation. And remember that zero is
is the element standing for a new line character. So it's kind of like a reasonable thing to to
feed in as the very first character in a sequence to be the new line. So it's going to be idx,
which we're going to feed in here. Then we're going to ask for 100 tokens. And then end that
generate will continue that. Now, because generate works on the level of batches, we then have to
index into the zero throw to basically unplug the the single batch dimension that exists. And then
that gives us a time steps is just a one dimensional array of all the indices, which we will convert
to simple Python list from PyTorch tensor, so that that can feed into our decode function and
convert those integers into text. So let me bring this back. And we're generating 100 tokens
let's run. And here's the generation that we achieved. So obviously, as garbage, and the reason it's
garbage is because this is totally random model. So next up, we're going to want to train this model.
Now, one more thing I wanted to point out here is this function is written to be general, but it's
kind of like ridiculous right now because we're feeding in all this, we're building out this context,
and we're concatenating it all. And we're always feeding it all into the model. But that's kind of
ridiculous, because this is just a simple by-gram model. So to make, for example, this prediction
about K, we only needed this w. But actually, what we fed into the model is we fed the entire
sequence. And then we only looked at the very last piece and predicted K. So the only reason I'm
writing it in this way is because right now this is a by-gram model. But I'd like to keep this
function fixed. And I like it to work later when our characters actually basically look further in
the history. And so right now the history is not used. So this looks silly. But eventually,
the history will be used. And so that's why we want to do it this way. So just a quick comment on that.
So now we see that this is random. So let's train the model. So it becomes a bit less random.
Okay, let's now train the model. So first, what I'm going to do is I'm going to create a pytorch
optimization object. So here we are using the optimizer, Adam W. Now in a make more series,
we've only ever used the cast gradient descent, the simplest possible optimizer, which you can get
using the SGD instead. But I want to use Adam, which is a much more advanced and popular optimizer.
And it works extremely well for typical good setting for the learning rate is roughly three
in negative four. But for very, very small networks, like the case here, you can get away with much,
much higher learning rates, running negative three, or even higher, probably. But let me create the
optimizer object, which will basically take the gradients and update the parameters using the
gradients. And then here, our batch size up above was only four. So let me actually use something
bigger, let's say 32. And then for some number of steps, we are sampling a new batch of data.
We're evaluating the loss. We're zeroing out all the gradients from the previous step,
getting the gradients for all the parameters, and then using those gradients to update our
parameters. So typical training loop, as we saw in the make more series. So let me now run this
for say 100 iterations, and let's see what kind of losses we're going to get.
So we started around 4.7. And now we're going to down to like 4.6, 4.5, etc. So the optimization
is definitely happening. But let's sort of try to increase number of iterations and only print at
the end, because we probably will not train for a hundred. Okay, so we're down to 3.6 roughly.
Roughly down to three.
This is the most janky optimization.
Okay, it's working. Let's just do 10,000. And then from here, we want to copy this.
And hopefully we're going to get something reasonable. And of course, it's not going to be
Shakespeare from a background model. But at least we see that the loss is improving. And
hopefully we're expecting something a bit more reasonable. Okay, so we're down at about 2.5
ish. Let's see what we get. Okay, dramatic improvement certainly on what we had here.
So let me just increase the number of tokens. Okay, so we see that we're starting to get something
at least like reasonable ish. Certainly not Shakespeare, but the model is making progress.
So that is the simplest possible model. So now what I'd like to do is,
obviously, this is a very simple model because the tokens are not talking to each other.
So given the previous context of whatever was generated, we're only looking at the very last
character to make the predictions about what comes next. So now these, now these tokens have
to start talking to each other and figuring out what is in the context so that they can make
better predictions for what comes next. And this is how we're going to kick off the transformer.
Okay, so next, I took the code that we developed in this Jupyter notebook and I converted it to
be a script. And I'm doing this because I just want to simplify our intermediate work into just
the final product that we have at this point. So in the top here, I put all the
parameters that we defined. I introduced a few and I'm going to speak to that in a little bit.
Otherwise, a lot of this should be recognizable. Reproducibility, read data, get the encoder and
the decoder, create the train and test splits, use the kind of like data loader that gets a batch
of the inputs and targets. This is new and I'll talk about it in a second. Now this is the
background language model that we developed and it can forward and give us a logits and loss and
it can generate. And then here we are creating the optimizer and this is the training loop.
So everything here should look pretty familiar. Now some of the small things that I added,
number one, I added the ability to run on a GPU if you have it. So if you have a GPU, then you can,
this will use CUDA instead of just CPU and everything will be a lot more faster.
Now when device becomes CUDA, then we need to make sure that when we load the data, we move it to
device. When we create the model, we want to move the model parameters to device. So as an example,
here we have the in an embedding table and it's got a dot weight inside it, which stores the
sort of lookup table. So that would be moved to the GPU so that all the calculations here
happen on the GPU and they can be a lot faster. And then finally here when I'm creating the
context that feeds it to generate, I have to make sure that I create on the device.
Number two, what I introduced is the fact that here in the training loop,
here I was just printing the loss dot item inside the training loop. But this is a very noisy
measurement of the current loss because every batch will be more or less lucky. And so what I
want to do usually is I have an estimate loss function. And the estimate loss basically then
goes up here. And it averages up the loss over multiple batches. So in particular, we're going
to iterate eval iter times. And we're going to basically get our loss. And then we're going to
get the average loss for both splits. And so this will be a lot less noisy. So here, what we call
the estimate loss, we're going to report the pre accurate train and validation loss.
Now, when we come back up, you'll notice a few things here. I'm setting the model to a valuation
phase. And down here, I'm resetting it back to training phase. Now right now for our model,
as is, this doesn't actually do anything. Because the only thing inside this model is this, and then
dot embedding. And this, this network would behave both would behave the same in both
evaluation mode and training mode. We have no dropout layers, we have no bathroom layers, etc.
But it is a good practice to think through what mode your neural network is in, because some layers
will have different behavior at inference time or training time. And there's also this context
manager torched up no grad. And this is just telling PyTorch that everything that happens inside
this function, we will not call dot backward on. And so PyTorch can be a lot more efficient with
its memory use, because it doesn't have to store all the intermediate variables, because we're
never going to call backward. And so it can, it can be a lot more memory efficient in that way.
So also a good practice to tell PyTorch when we don't intend to do back propagation.
So right now, this script is about 120 lines of code of, and that's kind of our starter code.
I'm calling it by gram.py, and I'm going to release it later. Now running this script
gives us output in the terminal, and it looks something like this. It basically, as I ran this
code, it was giving me the train loss and val loss. And we see that we convert to somewhere around
2.5 with the by-gram model. And then here's the sample that we produced at the end.
And so we have everything packaged up in the script, and we're in a good position now to iterate on
this. Okay, so we are almost ready to start writing our very first self-attention block
for processing these tokens. Now, before we actually get there, I want to get you used to
a mathematical trick that is used in the self-attention inside a transformer. And it's really just like
at the heart of an efficient implementation of self-attention. And so I want to work with this
toy example to just get used to this operation. And then it's going to make it much more clear
once we actually get to it in the script again. So let's create a b by t by c, where b, t, and c
are just 48 and two in the story example. And these are basically channels, and we have batches,
and we have the time component, and we have some information at each point in the sequence. So c.
Now, what we would like to do is we would like these tokens. So we have up to eight tokens here
in a batch, and these eight tokens are currently not talking to each other, and we would like them
to talk to each other. We'd like to couple them. And in particular, we don't we we want to couple
them in a very specific way. So the token, for example, at the fifth location, it should not
communicate with tokens in the sixth, seventh, and eighth location, because those are future
tokens in the sequence. The token on the fifth location should only talk to the one in the fourth,
third, second, and first. So it's only so information only flows from previous context to the current
timestamp. And we cannot get any information from the future, because we are about to try to
predict the future. So what is the easiest way from tokens to communicate? Okay, the easiest way I
would say is, okay, if we're up to if we're a fifth token, and I'd like to communicate with my past,
the simplest way we can do that is to just do a way is to just do an average of all the of
all the preceding elements. So for example, if I'm the fifth token, I would like to take the channels
that make up that our information at my step, but then also the channels from the four step,
third step, second step, and the first step, I'd like to average those up. And then that would
become sort of like a feature vector that summarizes me in the context of my history. Now, of course,
just doing a sum or like an average is an extremely weak form of interaction, like this communication
is extremely lossy. We've lost a ton of information about spatial arrangements of all those tokens.
But that's okay for now. We'll see how we can bring that information back later. For now,
what we would like to do is for every single batch element independently, for every teeth token
in that sequence, we'd like to now calculate the average of all the vectors in all the previous
tokens and also at this token. So let's write that out. I have a small snippet here. And instead
of just fumbling around, let me just copy paste it and talk to it. So in other words, we're going
to create X and BOW is short for bag of words, because bag of words is kind of like a term that
people use when you are just averaging up things. So this is just a bag of words. Basically, there's
a word stored on every one of these eight locations, and we're doing a bag of words, which is averaging.
So in the beginning, we're going to say that it's just initialized at zero. And then I'm doing
a for loop here. So we're not being efficient yet. That's coming. But for now, we're just iterating
over all the batch dimensions independently, iterating over time. And then the previous tokens
are at this batch, a dimension, and then everything up to and including the teeth token. Okay.
So when we slice out X in this way, X prep becomes of shape, how many elements there were in the past,
and then of course, C. So all the two dimensional information from these little tokens.
So that's the previous sort of chunk of tokens from my current sequence. And then I'm just doing
the average or the mean over the zero dimension. So I'm averaging out the time here. And I'm just
going to get a little C one dimensional vector, which I'm going to store in X back of words.
So I can run this. And this is not going to be very informative, because
let's see. So this is X of zero. So this is the zero batch element. And then Expo at zero.
Now, you see how the at the first location here, you see that the two are equal. And that's because
it's we're just doing an average of this one token. But here, this one is now an average of these two.
And now this one is an average of these three. And so on. So and this last one is the average
of all of these elements. So vertical average, just averaging up all the tokens, now gives this
outcome here. So this is all well and good. But this is very inefficient. Now the trick is that we
can be very, very efficient about doing this using matrix multiplication. So that's the mathematical
trick. And let me show you what I mean. Let's work with the toy example here. Let me run it and I'll
explain. I have a simple matrix here that is three by three of all ones, a matrix B of just random
numbers. And it's a three by two, and a matrix C, which will be three by three multiply three by two,
which will give out a three by two. So here we're just using a matrix multiplication. So a multiply
B gives us C. Okay, so how are these numbers in C achieved? Right, so this number in the top left
is the first row of a dot product with the first column of B. And since all the row of A right now
is all just once, then the dot product here with with this column of B is just going to do a sum
of these of this column. So two plus six plus six is 14. The element here in the output of C is
also the first column here, the first row of a multiply now with the second column of B. So seven
plus four plus five is 16. Now you see that there's repeating elements here. So this 14 again is
because this row is again all once, and it's multiplying the first column of B. So you get 14.
And this one is, and so on. So this last number here is the last row dot product last column.
Now the trick here is the following. This is just a boring number of, it's just a boring
array of all ones. But torch has this function called trail, which is short for a triangular,
something like that. And you can wrap it in torch that once, and it will just return the lower triangular
portion of this. Okay. So now it will basically zero out these guys here. So we just get the
lower triangular part. Well, what happens if we do that? So now we'll have a like this and B like
this. And now what are we getting here and C? Well, what is this number? Well, this is the first row
times the first column. And because this is zeros, these elements here are now ignored. So we just
get it to. And then this number here is the first row times the second column. And because these
are zeros, they get ignored. And it's just seven. The seven multiplies this one. But look what happened
here, because this is one and then zeros, we what ended up happening is we're just plucking out the
row of this row of B. And that's what we got. Now here, we have 110. So here, 110 dot product with
these two columns will now give us two plus six, which is eight, and seven plus four, which is 11.
And because this is one one one, we ended up with the addition of all of them. And so basically,
depending on how many ones and zeros we have here, we are basically doing a sum currently of the
variable number of these rows, and that gets deposited into C. So currently, we're doing sums,
because these are ones, but we can also do average, right? And you can start to see how we could do
average of the rows of B, sort of incremental fashion, because we don't have to, we can basically
normalize these rows, so that they sum to one, and then we're gonna get an average. So if we took a,
and then we did a equals a divide, torch dot sum in the, of a, in the one dimension. And then
let's keep them as true. So therefore, the broadcasting will work out. So if I rerun this,
you see now that these rows now sum to one. So this row is one, this row is 0.5, 0.5, 0. And here
we get one thirds. And now when we do a multiply B, what are we getting? Here we are just getting
the first row, first row. Here now we are getting the average of the first two rows.
Okay, so two and six average is four, and four and seven averages five and five. And on the bottom
here, we're now getting the average of these three rows. So the average of all of elements of B are
now deposited here. And so you can see that by manipulating these elements of this multiplying
matrix, and then multiplying it with any given matrix, we can do these averages in this incremental
fashion, because we just get, and we can manipulate that based on the elements of A. Okay, so that's
very convenient. So let's swing back up here and see how we can vectorize this and make it much
more efficient using what we've learned. So in particular, we are going to produce an array A,
but here I'm going to call it way short for weights. But this is our A. And this is how much of every
row we want to average up, and it's going to be an average because you can see that these rows sum
to one. So this is our A, and then our B in this example, of course, is X. So what's going to happen
here now is that we are going to have an expo to. And this expo to is going to be way multiplying
our X. So let's think this through way is T by T. And this is matrix multiplying in pytorch,
a B by T by C. And it's giving us the what shape. So pytorch will come here and it will see that
these shapes are not the same. So it will create a batch dimension here. And this is a batch
matrix multiply. And so it will apply this matrix multiplication in all the batch elements
in parallel and individually. And then for each batch element, there will be a T by T multiplying
T by C exactly as we had below. So this will now create B by T by C. And X bow two will now
become identical to expo. So we can see that torch dot all close of expo and expo two should be true.
Now, so this kind of like commisses us that these are in fact the same. So expo and expo two,
if I just print them, okay, we're not going to be able to, okay, we're not going to be able to
just stare it down. But well, let me try expo basically just at the zero element and expo
two at the zero element. So just the first batch. And we should see that this, that should be
identical, which they are. Right. So what happened here, the trick is we were able to use batch
matrix multiply to do this aggregation really. And it's a weighted aggregation. And the weights
are specified in this T by T array. And we're basically doing weighted sums. And these weighted
sums are according to the weights inside here, the take on sort of this triangular form. And so
that means that a token at the T dimension will only get sort of information from the
tokens preceding it. So that's exactly what we want. And finally, I would like to rewrite it in one
more way. And we're going to see why that's useful. So this is the third version. And it's also
identical to the first and second. But let me talk through it, it uses softmax. So trill here
is this matrix, lower triangular ones. Way begins as all zero. Okay, so if I just print way in the
beginning, it's all zero. Then I use masked fill. So what this is doing is weight that masked fill,
it's all zeros. And I'm saying, for all the elements where trill is equal to equal zero,
make them be negative infinity. So all the elements where trill is zero will become
negative infinity. Now, so this is what we get. And then the final one here is softmax.
So if I take a softmax along every single, so dim is negative one, so long every single row,
if I do a softmax, what is that going to do? Well, softmax is, it's also like a normalization
operation, right? And so spoiler alert, you get the exact same matrix. Let me bring back the softmax.
And recall that in softmax, we're going to exponentiate every single one of these. And then
we're going to divide by the sum. And so if we exponentiate every single element here, we're going to get a
one. And here we're going to get basically zero, zero, zero, zero, everywhere else. And then when
we normalize, we just get one. Here we're going to get one one, and then zeros. And then softmax
will again divide, and this will give us 0.5 and so on. And so this is also the same way to produce
this mask. Now the reason that this is a bit more interesting, and the reason we're going to end
up using it in self attention, is that these weights here begin with zero. And you can think of this
as like an interaction strength, or like an affinity. So basically, it's telling us how much of each
token from the past do we want to aggregate an average up. And then this line is saying,
tokens from the past cannot communicate by setting them to negative infinity. We're saying that we
will not aggregate anything from those tokens. And so basically, this then goes through softmax,
and through the weighted, and this is the aggregation through matrix multiplication.
And so what this is now is you can think of these as these zeros are currently just set by us to be
zero. But a quick preview is that these affinities between the tokens are not going to be just constant
at zero. They're going to be data dependent. These tokens are going to start looking at each other.
And some tokens will find other tokens more or less interesting. And depending on what their
values are, they're going to find each other interesting to different amounts. And I'm going to call
those affinities, I think. And then here we are saying the future cannot communicate with the past.
We're going to clamp them. And then when we normalize and some, we're going to aggregate
sort of their values, depending on how interestingly they find each other. And so that's the preview
for self attention. And basically, long story short from this entire section is that you can do
weighted aggregations of your past elements by having by using matrix multiplication of a lower
triangular fashion. And then the elements here in the lower triangular part are telling you how
much of each element fuses into this position. So we're going to use this trick now to develop
the self attention block. So first, let's get some quick preliminaries out of the way.
First, the thing I'm kind of bothered by is that you see how we're passing them vocab size into
the constructor. There's no need to do that because vocab size is already defined up top as a global
variable. So there's no need to pass this stuff around. Next, what I want to do is I don't want
to actually create, I want to create like a level of interaction here, where we don't directly go to
the embedding for the logits. But instead, we go through this intermediate phase, because we're
going to start making that bigger. So let me introduce a new variable and embed a short for
number of embedding dimensions. So an embed here will be say 32. That was the suggestion from
GitHub Copiled by the way. It also suggests 32, which is a good number. So this is an embedding
table and only 32 dimensional embeddings. So then here, this is not going to give us logits directly.
Instead, this is going to give us token embeddings. That's what I'm going to call it. And then to go
from the token embeddings to the logits, we're going to need a linear layer. So self.lmhead,
let's call it short for language modeling head, is an linear from an embed up to vocab size.
And then when we swing over here, we're actually going to get the logits by exactly what the
copilot says. Now we have to be careful here, because this C and this C are not equal.
This is an embed C and this is vocab size. So let's just say that an embed is equal to C.
And then this just creates one spurious layer of interaction through a linear layer. But this
should basically run. So we see that this runs and this currently looks kind of spurious,
but we're going to build on top of this. Now next up, so far, we've taken these in in the
seas and we've encoded them based on the identity of the tokens inside ID X. The next thing that
people very often do is that we're not just encoding the identity of these tokens, but also
their position. So we're going to have a second position embedding table here. So self that position
embedding table is an embedding of block size by an embed. And so each position from zero to
block size minus one will also get its own embedding vector. And then here, first let me decode
b by t from ID X dot shape. And then here, we're also going to have a positive bedding,
which is the positional embedding. And these are this is tortoise arrange. So this will be
basically just integers from zero to t minus one. And all of those integers from zero to t
minus one get embedded through the table to create a T by C. And then here, this gets renamed to
just say X and X will be the addition of the token embedding with the positional embeddings.
And here the broadcasting note will work out. So B by T by C plus T by C, this gets right aligned
a new dimension of one gets added, and it gets broadcasted across batch. So at this point,
X holds not just the token identities, but the positions at which these tokens occur.
And this is currently not that useful, because of course, we just have a simple
binary model. So it doesn't matter if you're on the fifth position, the second position,
or wherever, it's all translation invariant at this stage. So this information currently
wouldn't help. But as we work on the self attention block, we'll see that this starts to matter.
Okay, so now we get the crux of self attention. So this is probably the most important part of
this video to understand. We're going to implement a small self attention for a single individual
head as they're called. So we start off with where we were. So all of this code is familiar.
So right now I'm working with an example where I change the number of channels from two to 32. So
we have a four by eight arrangement of tokens. And each token and the information that each token
is currently 32 dimensional, but we just are working with random numbers. Now we saw here that
the code as we had it before does a simple weight, simple average of all the past tokens
and the current token. So it's just the previous information and current information is just being
mixed together in an average. And that's what this code currently achieves. And it does so
by creating this lower triangular structure, which allows us to mask out this way matrix that we
create. So we mask it out and then we normalize it. And currently, when we initialize the
affinities between all the different sort of tokens or nodes, I'm going to use those terms
interchangeably. So when we initialize the affinities between all the different tokens to be zero,
then we see that way gives us this structure where every single row has these uniform numbers.
And so that's what that's what then in this matrix multiply makes it so that we're doing a
simple average. Now, we don't actually want this to be all uniform, because different
tokens will find different other tokens more or less interesting. And we want that to be data
dependent. So for example, if I'm a vowel, then maybe I'm looking for consonants in my past. And
maybe I want to know what those consonants are. And I want that information to flow to me. And so
I want to now gather information from the past. But I want to do it in a data dependent way. And
this is the problem that self attention solves. Now the way self attention solves this is the
following. Every single node or every single token at each position will emit two vectors.
It will emit a query and it will emit a key. Now the query vector, roughly speaking, is
what am I looking for? And the key vector, roughly speaking, is what do I contain?
And then the way we get affinities between these tokens now in a sequence is we basically just
do a dot product between the keys and the queries. So my query dot products with all the keys of
all the other tokens. And that dot product now becomes way. And so if the key and the query are
sort of aligned, they will interact to a very high amount. And then I will get to learn more
about that specific token, as opposed to any other token in the sequence. So let's implement this now.
We're going to implement a single what's called head of self attention. So this is just one head.
There's a hyper parameter involved with these heads, which is the head size. And then here I'm
initializing linear modules, and I'm using bias equals false. So these are just going to apply
matrix multiply with some fixed weights. And now let me produce a key and Q k and Q by forwarding
these modules on X. So the size of this will now become B by T by 16, because that is the head size.
And the same here B by T by 16. So this being that size. So you see here that when I forward
this linear on top of my X, all the tokens in all the positions in the B by T arrangement,
all of them in parallel and independently produce a key and a query. So no communication has happened
yet. But the communication comes now, all the queries will dart product with all the keys.
So basically what we want is we want way now or the affinities between these to be query multiplying
key. But we have to be careful with we can't make sure it's multiplied this we actually need to
transpose k, but we have to be also careful because these are when you have the batch dimension. So
in particular, we want to transpose the last two dimensions, dimension negative one and dimension
negative two. So negative two, negative one. And so this matrix multiply now will basically do the
following B by T by 16. Matrix multiplies B by 16 by T to give us B by T by T. Right.
So for every row of B, we're not going to have a T square matrix given us the affinities. And
these are now the way. So they're not zeros. They are now coming from this dart product between
the keys and the queries. So this can now run, I can I can run this. And the weighted aggregation
now is a function in a data band and manner between the keys and queries of these nodes. So
just inspecting what happened here, the way takes on this form. And you see that before way was
just a constant. So it was applied in the same way to all the batch elements. But now every single
batch elements will have different sort of way, because every single batch element contains different
tokens at different positions. And so this is not a data dependent. So when we look at just the
zero row, for example, in the input, these are the weights that came out. And so you can see now
that they're not just exactly uniform. And in particular, as an example here for the last row,
this was the eighth token. And the eighth token knows what content it has and it knows at what
position it's in. And now the eight token based on that creates a query. Hey, I'm looking for this
kind of stuff. I'm a vowel, I'm on the eight position, I'm looking for any consonants at positions up to
four. And then all the nodes get to emit keys. And maybe one of the channels could be I am a
I am a consonant and I am in the position up to four. And that key would have a high number in that
specific channel. And that's how the query and the key when they dark product, they can find each other
and create a high affinity. And when they have a high affinity, like say, this token was pretty
interesting to to this eighth token. When they have a high affinity, then through the softmax,
I will end up aggregating a lot of its information into my position. And so I'll get to learn a lot
about it. Now, just this we're looking at way after this has already happened. Let me erase this
operation as well. So let me erase the masking and the softmax just to show you the under the hood
internals and how that works. So without the masking and the softmax way comes out like this,
right? This is the outputs of the dot products. And these are the raw outputs and they take on values
from negative, you know, two to positive two, etc. So that's the raw interactions and raw
affinities between all the nodes. But now if I'm a, if I'm a fifth node, I will not want to
aggregate anything from the sixth node seventh node and the eighth node. So actually, we use the
upper triangular masking. So those are not allowed to communicate. And now we actually want to have
a nice distribution. So we don't want to aggregate negative point one one of this node that's crazy.
So instead we exponentiate and normalize, and now we get a nice distribution that seems to want.
And this is telling us now in the data, depending on manner, how much of information to aggregate
from any of these tokens in the past. So that's way, and it's not zeros anymore, but it's calculated
in this way. Now there's one more part to a single self attention head. And that is that when we
do the aggregation, we don't actually aggregate the tokens exactly. We aggregate, we produce one
more value here. And we call that the value. So in the same way that we produce t and query,
we're also going to create a value. And then here, we don't aggregate x, we calculate a v,
which is just achieved by propagating this linear on top of x again. And then we output
way multiplied by v. So v is the elements that we aggregate, or the vector that we aggregate,
instead of the raw x. And now of course, this will make it so that the output here of this single
head will be 16 dimensional, because that is the head size. So you can think of x as kind of like
private information to this token, if you think about it that way. So x is kind of private to this
token. So I'm a fifth token at some, and I have some identity. And my information is kept in vector
x. And now for the purposes of the single head, here's what I'm interested in. Here's what I have.
And if you find me interesting, here's what I will communicate to you. And that's stored in v.
And so v is the thing that gets aggregated for the purposes of this single head between the
different nodes. And that's basically the self attention mechanism. This is, this is what it does.
There are a few notes that I would like to make about attention. Number one, attention is a
communication mechanism. You can really think about it as a communication mechanism, where you
have a number of nodes in a directed graph, where basically you have edges pointed between nodes
like this. And what happens is every node has some vector of information, and it gets to aggregate
information via a weighted sum from all the nodes that point to it. And this is done in a data
dependent manner. So depending on whatever data is actually stored at each node at any point in time.
Now, our graph doesn't look like this. Our graph has a different structure. We have eight nodes,
because the block size is eight, and there's always eight tokens. And the first node is only
pointed to by itself. The second node is pointed to by the first node and itself,
all the way up to the eighth node, which is pointed to by all the previous nodes and itself.
And so that's the structure that our directed graph has, or happens to have, in an autoregressive
sort of scenario like language modeling. But in principle, attention can be applied to any
arbitrary directed graph, and it's just a communication mechanism between the nodes.
The second note is that, notice that there's no notion of space. So attention simply acts over
like a set of vectors in this graph. And so by default, these nodes have no idea where they
are positioned in the space. And that's why we need to encode them positionally and sort of give
them some information that is anchored to a specific position so that they sort of know where they
are. And this is different than, for example, from convolution, because if you run, for example,
a convolution operation over some input, there is a very specific sort of layout of the information
in space and the convolutional filters sort of act in space. And so it's not like an attention.
An attention is just a set of vectors out there in space. They communicate. And if you want them
to have a notion of space, you need to specifically add it, which is what we've done when we
calculated the relative the positional encodings and added that information to the vectors.
The next thing that I hope is very clear is that the elements across the batch dimension,
which are independent examples, never talk to each other. They're always processed independently.
And this is a bashed matrix multiply that applies basically a matrix multiplication,
kind of imperil across the batch dimension. So maybe it would be more accurate to say that
in this analogy of a directed graph, we really have, because the batch size is four, we really have
four separate pools of eight nodes, and those eight nodes only talk to each other. But in total,
there's like 32 nodes that are being processed. But there's sort of four separate pools of eight,
you can look at it that way. The next note is that here in the case of language modeling,
we have this specific structure of directed graph where the future tokens will not communicate
to the past tokens. But this doesn't necessarily have to be the constraint in the general case.
And in fact, in many cases, you may want to have all of the nodes talk to each other fully. So as
an example, if you're doing sentiment analysis or something like that with a transformer, you might
have a number of tokens, and you may want to have them all talk to each other fully, because later,
you are predicting, for example, the sentiment of the sentence. And so it's okay for these
nodes to talk to each other. And so in those cases, you will use an encoder block of self attention.
And all it means that it's an encoder block is that you will delete this line of code,
allowing all the nodes to completely talk to each other. What we're implementing here is
sometimes called a decoder block. And it's called a decoder, because it is sort of like
decoding language. And it's got this autoregressive format, where you have to mask with the triangle
and matrix, so that nodes from the future never talk to the past, because they would give away
the answer. And so basically, an encoder blocks, you would delete this, allow all the nodes to talk.
In decoder blocks, this will always be present, so that you have this triangular structure.
But both are allowed and attention doesn't care. Attention supports arbitrary connectivity
between nodes. The next thing I wanted to comment on is you keep me, you keep hearing me say
attention, self attention, etc. There's actually also something called cross attention. What is
the difference? So basically, the reason this attention is self attention, is because the keys,
queries, and the values are all coming from the same source from X. So the same source X produces
keys, queries, and values. So these nodes are self attending. But in principle, attention is
much more general than that. So for example, an encoder decoder transformers, you can have a case
where the queries are produced from X. But the keys and the values come from a whole separate
external source, and sometimes from encoder blocks that encode some context that we'd like to
condition on. And so the keys and the values will actually come from a whole separate source.
Those are nodes on the side. And here we're just producing queries. And we're reading off
information from the side. So cross attention is used when there's a separate source of nodes,
we'd like to pull information from into our nodes. And it's self attention if we just have nodes
that would like to look at each other and talk to each other. So this attention here happens to be
self attention. But in principle, attention is a lot more general. Okay, and the last note at this
stage is if we come to the attention is only need paper here, we've already implemented attention.
So given query key and value, we've multiplied the query on a key, we've soft maxed it, and then
we are aggregating the values. There's one more thing that we're missing here, which is the dividing
by one over square root of the head size, the decay here is the head size. Why aren't they doing
this one is important. So they call it a scaled attention. And it's kind of like an important
normalization to basically have the problem is if you have unit Gaussian inputs, so zero mean unit
variance, k and q are unit Gaussian. And if you just do way naively, then you see that your way
actually will be the variance will be on the order of head size, which in our case is 16.
But if you multiply by one over head size square root, so this is square root, and this is one over,
then the variance of way will be one. So we'll be preserved. Now, why is this important? You'll
notice that way here will feed into softmax. And so it's really important, especially at
initialization, that way be fairly diffuse. So in our case here, we sort of locked out here,
and way at a fairly diffuse numbers here. So like this. Now the problem is that because of
softmax, if weight takes on very positive and very negative numbers inside it, softmax will
actually converge towards one hot vectors. And so I can illustrate that here. Say we are
applying softmax to a tensor of values that are very close to zero, then we're going to get a
diffuse thing out of softmax. But the moment I take the exact same thing and I start sharpening it,
making it bigger by multiplying these numbers by eight, for example, you'll see that the softmax
will start to sharpen. And in fact, it will sharpen towards the max. So it will sharpen towards
whatever number here is the highest. And so basically, we don't want these values to be too
extreme, especially at initialization. Otherwise, softmax will be way too peaky. And you're basically
aggregating information from like a single node, every node just aggregates information from a
single other node. That's not what we want, especially at initialization. And so the scaling is used
just to control the variance at initialization. Okay, so having said all that, let's now take our
self attention knowledge and let's take it for a spin. So here in the code, I created this head
module and implements a single head of self attention. So you give it a head size. And then here it
creates the key query and the value linear layers, typically people who use biases in these.
So those are the linear projections that we're going to apply to all of our nodes.
Now here, I'm creating this trill variable. Trill is not a parameter of the module. So in sort of
pytorch naming conventions, this is called a buffer. It's not a parameter. And you have to call it,
you have to assign it to the module using a register buffer. So that creates the trill,
the trying lower triangular matrix. And over given the input X, this should look very familiar now.
We calculate the keys, the queries, we calling pocket the attention scores in sideways. We normalize
it. So we're using scaled attention here. Then we make sure that sure doesn't communicate with the
past. So this makes it a decoder block. And then softmax and then aggregate the value and output.
Then here in the language model, I'm creating a head in the constructor and I'm calling it
self attention head. And the head size, I'm going to keep as the same and embed just for now.
And then here, once we've encoded the information with the token embeddings and the position embeddings,
we're simply going to feed it into the self attention head. And then the output of that is going to go
into the decoder language modeling head and create the logits. So this is sort of the simplest way
to plug in a self attention component into our network right now. I had to make one more change,
which is that here in the generate, we have to make sure that our ID X that we feed into the model.
Because now we're using positional embeddings, we can never have more than block size coming in,
because if ID X is more than block size, then our position embedding table is going to run out of
scope, because it only has embeddings for up to block size. And so therefore, I added some code
here to crop the context that we're going to feed into self, so that we never pass in more
block size elements. So those are the changes. And let's now train the network. Okay, so I also
came up to the script here, and I decreased the learning rate, because the self attention
can't tolerate very, very high learning rates. And then I also increased number of iterations
because the learning rate is lower. And then I trained it. And previously, we were only able to
get to up to 2.5. And now we are down to 2.4. So we definitely see a little bit of improvement
from 2.5 to 2.4 roughly. But the text is still not amazing. So clearly, the self attention had
is doing some useful communication. But we still have a long way to go. Okay, so now we've implemented
the scale dot product attention. Now next up, and the attention is all you need paper. There's
something called multi head attention. And what is multi head attention? It's just applying
multiple attentions in parallel and concatenating the results. So they have a little bit of diagram
here. I don't know if this is super clear. It's really just multiple attentions in parallel.
So let's implement that fairly straightforward. If we want a multi head attention, then we want
multiple heads of self attention running in parallel. So in PyTorch, we can do this by simply
creating multiple heads. So however, how many heads you want, and then what is the head size
of each? And then we run all of them in parallel into a list, and simply concatenate all of the
outputs. And we're concatenating over the channel dimension. So the way this looks now is we don't
have just a single attention that has a head size of 32, because remember, an embed is 32.
Instead of having one communication channel, we now have four communication channels in parallel.
And each one of these communication channels typically will be smaller correspondingly.
So because we have four communication channels, we want eight dimensional self attention. And so
from each communication channel, we're getting together eight dimensional vectors. And then we
have four of them. And that concatenates to give us 32, which is the original, an embed.
And so this is kind of similar to if you're familiar with convolutions, this is kind of like a group
convolution, because basically, instead of having one large convolution, we do convolution in groups.
And that's multi headed self attention. And so then here, we just use SA heads, self attention
heads instead. Now I actually ran it and scrolling down. I ran the same thing, and then we now get
it down to 2.28 roughly. And the upper distal, the generation is still not amazing. But clearly,
the validation loss is improving, because we were at 2.4 just now. And so it helps to have multiple
communication channels, because obviously these tokens have a lot to talk about. They want to
find the constants, the vowels, they want to find the vowels just from certain positions.
They want to find any kinds of different things. And so it helps to create multiple independent
channels of communication, gather lots of different types of data, and then decode the output. Now,
going back to the paper for a second, of course, I didn't explain this figure in full detail, but
we are starting to see some components of what we've already implemented. We have the positional
encodings, token encodings that add, we have the masked multi headed attention implemented.
Now, here's another multi headed attention, which is a cross attention to an encoder,
which we haven't we're not going to implement in this case. I'm going to come back to that later.
But I want you to notice that there's a feed forward part here, and then this is grouped into a block
that gets repeated again and again. Now, the feed forward part here is just a simple multi layer
projection. So the multi headed so here position wise feed forward networks is just a simple little
MLP. So I want to start basically in a similar fashion also adding computation into the network.
And this computation is on a per node level. So I've already implemented it, and you can see
the diff highlighted on the left here when I've added or changed things. Now, before we had the
multi headed self attention that did the communication, but we went way too fast to calculate the
logits. So the tokens looked at each other, but didn't really have a lot of time to think on
what they found from the other tokens. And so what I've implemented here is a little feed forward
single layer, and this little layer is just a linear followed by a row nonlinearity. And that's
that's it. So it's just a little layer. And then I call it feed forward, and embed. And then this
feed forward is just called sequentially right after the self attention. So we self attend,
then we feed forward. And you'll notice that the feed forward here, when it's applying linear,
this is on a per token level. All the tokens do this independently. So the self attention is the
communication. And then once they gathered all the data, now they need to think on that data
individually. And so that's what feed forward is doing. And that's why I've added it here.
Now when I train this, the validation loss actually continues to go down now to 2.24,
which is down from 2.28. The outputs still look kind of terrible, but at least we've improved
the situation. And so as a preview, we're going to now start to interspers the communication
with the computation. And that's also what the transformer does, when it has blocks that communicate
and then compute, and it groups them and replicates them. Okay, so let me show you what we like to do.
We'd like to do something like this. We have a block. And this block is basically this part here,
except for the cross attention. Now the block basically intersperses communication and the
computation. The computation, the communication is done using multi headed self attention. And
then the computation is done using a feed forward network on all the tokens independently.
Now what I've added here also is you'll notice this takes the number of embeddings in the
embedding dimension and number of heads that we would like, which is kind of like group sizing,
group convolution. And I'm saying that number of heads we'd like is four. And so because this is
32, we calculate that because this 32, the number of heads should be four, the head size should be
eight, so that everything sort of works out channel wise. So this is how the transformer
structures sort of the sizes typically. So the head size will become eight. And then this is
how we want to interspers them. And then here, I'm trying to create blocks, which is just a
sequential application of block block block. So that we're interspersing communication feed
forward many, many times. And then finally, we decode. Now actually try to run this. And the
problem is this doesn't actually give a very good answer. And we're very good result. And the
reason for that is we're starting to actually get like a pretty deep neural net. And deep neural
nets suffer from optimization issues. And I think that's what we're kind of like slightly
starting to run into. So we need one more idea that we can borrow from the transfer of paper to
resolve those difficulties. Now there are two optimizations that dramatically help with the
depth of these networks, and make sure that the networks remain optimizable. Let's talk about the
first one. The first one in this diagram is you see this arrow here. And then this arrow and this
arrow, those are skip connections, or sometimes called residual connections. They come from this
paper, the procedural learning from a direct mission from about 2015, that introduced the concept.
Now, these are basically what it means is you transform data, but then you have a skip connection
with addition from the previous features. Now the way I like to visualize it, that I prefer,
is the following. Here the computation happens from the top to bottom. And basically you have this
residual pathway, and you are free to fork off from the residual pathway, perform some computation,
and then project back to the residual pathway via addition. And so you go from the
inputs to the targets, only the plus and plus and plus. And the reason this is useful is because
during that propagation, remember from our micro grad video earlier, addition distributes
gradients equally to both of its branches, that that fat is the input. And so the supervision or
the gradients from the loss basically hop through every addition node all the way to the input,
and then also fork off into the residual blocks. But basically have this gradient superhighway
that goes directly from the supervision all the way to the input, unimpeded. And then these
residual blocks are usually initialized in the beginning, so they contribute very, very little,
if anything, to the residual pathway. They are initialized that way. So in the beginning,
they are almost kind of like not there. But then during the optimization, they come online over time,
and they start to contribute. But at least at the initialization, you can go from directly
supervision to the input gradient, this unimpeded and just flows, and then the blocks over time
kick in. And so that dramatically helps with the optimization. So let's implement this. So
coming back to our block here, basically what we want to do is we want to do x equals x plus
self attention and x equals x plus solve that feed forward. So this is x, and then we fork off
and do some communication and come back, and we fork off and we do some computation and come back.
So those are residual connections. And then swinging back up here, we also have to introduce
this projection. So an end that linear. And this is going to be from after we concatenate this,
this is the size and embed. So this is the output of the self tension itself. But then we actually
want the to apply the projection. And that's the result. So the projection is just a linear
transformation of the outcome of this layer. So that's the projection back into the residual pathway.
And then here in a feed forward, it's going to be the same thing. I could have a self that projection
here as well. But let me just simplify it. And let me couple it inside the same sequential
container. And so this is the projection layer going back into the residual pathway. And so
that's, well, that's it. So now we can train this. So I'm putting within one more small change.
When you look into the paper again, you see that the dimensionality of input and output is 512
for them. And they're saying that the inner layer here in the feed forward has dimensionality of 2048.
So there's a multiplier of four. And so the inner layer of the feed forward network
should be multiplied by four in terms of channel sizes. So I came here and I multiplied four times
embed here for the feed forward. And then from four times an embed coming back down to an embed
when we go back to the projection to the projection. So adding a bit of computation here and growing
that layer that is in the residual block on the side of the residual pathway. And then I train
this and we actually get down all the way to 2.08 validation loss. And we also see that the network
is starting to get big enough that our train loss is getting ahead of validation loss. So we
start to see like a little bit of overfitting. And our our generations here are still not amazing
but at least you see that we can see like is here this now grief sync. Like this starts to almost
look like English. So yeah, we're starting to really get there. Okay, and the second innovation
that is very helpful for optimizing very deep neural works is right here. So we have this addition
now that's the residual part, but this norm is referring to something called layer norm. So
layer norm is implemented in PyTorch. It's a paper that came out a while back here.
And layer norm is very, very similar to bashroom. So remember back to our make more series part 3.
We implemented bashroom realization and bashroom realization basically just made sure that
across the bash dimension, any individual neuron had unit Gaussian distribution. So it was zero
mean and unit standard deviation, one standard deviation output. So what I did here is I'm copy
pasting the bashroom 1D that we developed in our make more series. And see here we can initialize
for example this module and we can have a batch of 32, 100 dimensional vectors feeding through
the bashroom layer. So what this does is it guarantees that when we look at just the 0th column,
it's a 0 mean 1 standard deviation. So it's normalizing every single column of this input.
Now the rows are not going to be normalized by default because we're just normalizing columns.
So let's not implement layer norm. It's very complicated. Look, we come here, we change this
from 0 to 1. So we don't normalize the columns, we normalize the rows. And now we've implemented
layer norm. So now the columns are not going to be normalized, but the rows are going to be
normalized. For every individual example, it's 100 dimensional vector is normalized in this way.
And because our computation does not span across examples, we can delete all of this buffers stuff
because we can always apply this operation and don't need to maintain any running buffers.
So we don't need the buffers. We don't, there's no distinction between training and test time.
And we don't need these running buffers. We do keep gamma and beta. We don't need the momentum.
We don't care if it's training or not. And this is now a layer norm. And it normalizes the
rows instead of the columns. And this here is identical to basically this here. So let's now
implement layer norm in our transformer. Before I incorporate the layer norm, I just wanted to
note that as I said, very few details about the transformer have changed in the last five years.
But this is actually something that's likely the parts from the original paper. You see that the
add and norm is applied after the transformation. But in now it is a bit more basically common to
apply the layer norm before the transformation. So there's a reshuffling of the layer norms.
So this is called the pre norm formulation. And that the one that we're going to implement as
well. So select deviation from the original paper. Basically, we need to in layer norms,
layer norm one is an end dot layer norm. And we tell it how many words the embedding dimension.
And we need the second layer norm. And then here, the layer arms are applied immediately on x.
So self that layer norm one in applied on x and self that layer to apply to x before it goes
into self attention and feed forward. And the size of the layer norm here is an embeds of 32.
So when the layer norm is normalizing our features, it is the normalization here
happens. The mean and the variance are taken over 32 numbers. So the batch and the time act as batch
dimensions, both of them. So this is kind of like a per token transformation that just normalizes
the features and makes them a unit mean, unit Gaussian at initialization. But of course,
because these layer norms inside it have these gamma and beta trainable parameters. The layer
normal eventually create outputs that might not be unit Gaussian, but the optimization will determine
that. So for now, this is the this is incorporating the layer norms and let's train them up. Okay,
so I let it run. And we see that we get down to 2.06, which is better than the previous 2.08.
So a slight improvement by adding the layer norms. And I'd expect that they help even more if we
have bigger and deeper network. One more thing I forgot to add is that there should be a layer norm
here also typically, as at the end of the transformer and right before the final linear layer that
decodes into vocabulary. So I added that as well. So at this stage, we actually have a pretty complete
transformer coming to the original paper. And it's a decoder only transformer. I'll talk about that
in a second. But at this stage, the major pieces are in place. So we can try to scale this up and
see how well we can push this number. Now, in order to scale up the model, I had to perform some
cosmetic changes here to make it nicer. So I introduced this variable called n layer, which
just specifies how many layers of the blocks we're going to have. I create a bunch of blocks and we
have a new variable number of heads as well. I pulled out the layer norm here. And so this is
identical. Now one thing that I did briefly change is I added dropout. So dropout is something
that you can add right before the residual connection back, right before the connection back into the
residual pathway. So we can drop out that as the last layer here, we can drop out here at the end
of the multi headed attention as well. And we can also drop out here, when we calculate the
basically, affinities and after the softmax, we can drop out some of those. So we can
randomly prevent some of the nodes from communicating. And so dropout comes from this paper from 2014
or so. And basically it takes your neural mat. And it randomly, every forward backward pass,
shuts off some subset of neurons. So randomly drops them to zero and trains without them.
And what this does effectively is because the mask of what's being dropped out has changed
every single forward backward pass. It ends up kind of training an ensemble of sub networks.
And then at test time, everything is fully enabled and kind of all of those sub networks are merged
into a single ensemble, if you can, if you want to think about it that way. So I would read the paper
to get the full detail. For now, we're just going to stay on the level of this is a regularization
technique. And I added it because I'm about to scale up the model quite a bit. And I was concerned
about overfitting. So now when we scroll up to the top, we'll see that I changed a number of
hyper parameters here about our neural mat. So I made the best size be much larger, now 64.
I changed the block size to be 256. So previously was just eight, eight characters of context. Now
it is 256 characters of context to predict the 257th. I brought down the learning rate a little
bit because the neural mat is now much bigger. So I brought down the learning way. The embedding
dimension is not 384. And there are six heads. So 384 divide six means that every head is 64
dimensional as it as a standard. And then there are also going to be six layers of that. And the
dropout will be a point to so every forward backward pass 20% of all of these intermediate
calculations are disabled and dropped to zero. And then I already trained this and I ran it. So
drum roll, how does it perform? So let me just scroll up here.
We get a validation loss of 1.48, which is actually quite a bit of an improvement on what we had
before, which I think was 2.07. So we went from 2.07 all the way down to 1.48 just by scaling up
this neural mat with the code that we have. And this of course ran for a lot longer. This
may be trained for I want to say about 15 minutes on my a 100 GPU. So that's a pretty good GPU.
And if you don't have a GPU, you're not going to be able to reproduce this. On a CPU, this would be,
I would not run this on a CPU or MacBook or something like that. You'll have to bring down
the number of layers and the embedding dimension and so on. But in about 15 minutes, we can get
this kind of a result. And I'm printing some of the Shakespeare here. But what I did also is I
printed 10,000 characters, so a lot more and I wrote them to a file. And so here we see some of the
outputs. So it's a lot more recognizable as the input text file. So the input text file just for
reference looked like this. So there's always like someone speaking in this matter. And
our predictions now take on that form. Except of course they're non-sensical when you actually
read them. So it is every crimpy be house. Oh, those preparation. We give heed.
Oh, oh, sent me you mighty lord. Anyway, so you can read through this. It's nonsensical, of course, but
this is just a transformer trained on the character level for 1 million characters that come from
Shakespeare. So there's sort of like blabbers on in Shakespeare like manner, but it doesn't of course
make sense at this scale. But I think I think still a pretty good demonstration of what's possible.
So now I think that kind of like concludes the programming section of this video. We basically
kind of did a pretty good job in implementing this transformer, but the picture doesn't exactly
match up to what we've done. So what's going on with all these additional parts here? So let me
finish explaining this architecture and why it looks so funky. Basically what's happening here is
what we implemented here is a decoder only transformer. So there's no component here. This
part is called the encoder. And there's no cross attention block here. Our block only has a self
attention and the feed forward. So it is missing this third in between piece here. This piece does
cross attention. So we don't have it and we don't have the encoder. We just have the decoder. And
the reason we have a decoder only is because we are just generating text and it's unconditioned
on anything. We're just blabbering on according to a given data set. What makes it a decoder is
that we are using the triangular mask in our transformer. So it has this autoregressive property
where we can just go and sample from it. So the fact that it's using the triangular mask
to mask out the attention makes it a decoder. And it can be used for language modeling. Now the
reason that the original paper had an encoder decoder architecture is because it is a machine
translation paper. So it is concerned with a different setting in particular. It expects some
tokens that encode say for example French. And then it is expected to decode the translation in
English. So you typically these here are special tokens. So you are expected to read in this and
condition on it. And then you start off the generation with a special token called start.
So this is a special new token that you introduce and always place in the beginning.
And then the network is expected to output neural networks are awesome. And then a special
end token to finish the generation. So this part here will be decoded exactly as we have done it.
Neural networks are awesome. Will be identical to what we did. But unlike what we did, they want to
condition the generation on some additional information. And in that case, this additional
information is the French sentence that they should be translating. So what they do now is they
bring the encoder. Now the encoder reads this part here. So we're all going to take the part of French
and we're going to create tokens from it exactly as we've seen in our video. And we're going to
put a transformer on it. But there's going to be no triangular mask. And so all the tokens are
allowed to talk to each other as much as they want. And they're just encoding whatever's the
content of this French sentence. Once they've encoded it, they've basically come out in the top
here. And then what happens here is in our decoder, which does the language modeling,
there's an additional connection here to the outputs of the encoder. And that is brought in
through cross attention. So the queries are still generated from x. But now the keys and the values
are coming from the side. The keys and the values are coming from the top generated by the nodes
that came outside of the decoder. And those tops, the keys and the values there, the top of it,
feed in on a side into every single block of the decoder. And so that's why there's an additional
cross attention. And really what it's doing is it's conditioning the decoding, not just on the past
of this current decoding, but also on having seen the full fully encoded French prompt sort of.
And so it's an encoded decoder model, which is why we have those two transformers, an additional
block, and so on. So we did not do this because we have no we have nothing to encode. There's no
conditioning. We just have a text file and we just want to imitate it. And that's why we are using a
decoder only transformer exactly as done in GPT. Okay, so now I wanted to do a very brief walkthrough
of nano GPT, which you can find on my GitHub. And nano GPT is basically two files of interest.
There's trained up by and modeled up by trained up by is all the boilerplate code for training the
network. It is basically all the stuff that we had here is the training loop. It's just that it's a
lot more complicated because we're saving and loading checkpoints and pre trained weights. And we are
decaying the learning rate and compiling the model and using distributed training across
multiple nodes or GPUs. So the training that pogates a little bit more hairy complicated.
There's more options, etc. But the model that I should look very, very similar to what we've done
here. In fact, the model is almost identical. So first, here we have the causal self attention
block. And all of this should look very, very recognizable to you. We're producing queries,
keys, values. We're doing dot products, we're masking, applying softmax, optionally dropping out.
And here we are pulling the way the values. What is different here is that in our code,
I have separated out the multi headed attention into just a single individual head. And then
here I have multiple heads and I explicitly concatenate them. Whereas here, all of it is
implemented in a batch manner inside a single causal self attention. And so we don't just have a B
and a T and a C dimension. We also end up with a fourth dimension, which is the heads. And so it
just gets a lot more sort of hairy because we have four dimensional array tensors now. But it is
equivalent mathematically. So the exact same thing is happening as what we have. It's just a
bit more efficient because all the heads are now treated as a batch dimension as well.
Then we have the multiple layer perceptron. It's using the Galoon nonlinearity, which is defined
here, instead of Ralu. And this is done just because opening I used it and I want to be able to load
their checkpoints. The blocks of the transformer are identical, the communicate and the compute
phase as we saw. And then the GPT will be identical. We have the position encodings, token encodings,
the blocks, the layer norm at the end, the final linear layer. And this should look all very
recognizable. And there's a bit more here, because I'm loading checkpoints and stuff like that.
I'm separating out the parameters into those that should be weight-decade and those that shouldn't.
But the generate function should also be very, very similar. So a few details are different,
but you should definitely be able to look at this file and be able to understand a lot of the pieces
now. So let's now bring things back to chat GPT. What would it look like if we wanted to train
chat GPT ourselves? And how does it relate to what we learned today? Well, to train in chat GPT,
there are roughly two stages. First is the pre-training stage and then the fine-tuning stage. In the
pre-training stage, we are training on the large chunk of internet and just trying to get a first
decoder-only transformer to babble text. So it's very, very similar to what we've done ourselves.
Except we've done like a tiny little baby pre-training step. And so in our case, this is how you print
a number of parameters. I printed it and it's about 10 million. So this transformer that I created here
to create little Shakespeare transformer was about 10 million parameters. Our dataset is roughly
one million characters, so roughly one million tokens. But you have to remember that opening
eye uses different vocabulary. They're not on the character level. They use these sub-word
chunks of words. And so they have a vocabulary of 50,000 roughly elements. And so their sequences
are a bit more condensed. So our dataset, the Shakespeare dataset would be probably around 300,000
tokens in the open-eye vocabulary roughly. So we trained about 10 million parameter model on
roughly 300,000 tokens. Now when you go to the GPT-3 paper and you look at the transformers that they
train, they train to number of transformers of different sizes. But the biggest transformer
here has 175 billion parameters. So ours is again 10 million. They used this number of layers in a
transformer. This is the end in bed. This is the number of heads. And this is the head size.
And then this is the batch size. So ours was 65. And the learning rate is similar. Now when they
train this transformer, they trained on 300 billion tokens. So again, remember ours is about 300,000.
So this is about a million fold increase. And this number would not be even that large by today's
standard. So you'd be going up one trillion and above. So they are training a significantly larger
model on a good chunk of the internet. And that is the pre-training stage. But otherwise,
these hyperparameters should be fairly recognizable to you. And the architecture is actually like
nearly identical to what we implemented ourselves. But of course, it's a massive infrastructure
challenge to train this. You're talking about typically thousands of GPUs having to, you know,
talk to each other to train models of this size. So that's just the pre-training stage.
Now, after you complete the pre-training stage, you don't get something that responds to your
questions with answers. And it's not helpful and etc. You get a document complete. Right? So
it babbles, but it doesn't babble Shakespeare in bables internet. It will create arbitrary
news articles and documents and it will try to complete documents because that's what it's
trained for. It's trying to complete the sequence. So when you give it a question, it would just
potentially just give you more questions. It would follow with more questions. It will do
whatever it looks like some close document would do in the training data on the internet. And so
who knows, you're getting kind of like undefined behavior. It might basically answer with two
questions with other questions. It might ignore your question. It might just try to complete some
news article. It's totally unaligned, as we say. So the second fine tuning stage is to actually
align it to be an assistant. And this is the second stage. And so this chat GPT blog post from
OpenAI talks a little bit about how the stage is achieved. We basically, there's roughly three
steps to this stage. So what they do here is they start to collect training data that looks
specifically like what an assistant would do. So they have documents that have the format where
the question is on top and then an answer is below. And they have a large number of these,
but probably not on the order of the internet. This is probably on the order of maybe thousands
of examples. And so they then fine tune the model to basically only focus on documents that look
like that. And so you're starting to slowly align it. So it's going to expect a question at the top
and it's going to expect to complete the answer. And these very, very large models are very sample
efficient during their fine tuning. So this actually somehow works. But that's just step one.
That's just fine tuning. So then they actually have more steps where, okay, the second step is you
let the model respond and then different raters look at the different responses and rank them
for their preferences to which one is better than the other. They use that to train the reward model.
So they can predict basically using a different network how much of any candidate response
would be desirable. And then once they have a reward model, they run PPO, which is a form of
policy gradient reinforcement learning optimizer, to fine tune this sampling policy.
So that the answers that the GPT now generates are expected to score a high reward according to
the reward model. And so basically there's a whole lining stage here or fine tuning stage.
It's got multiple steps in between there as well. And it takes the model from being a document
completer to a question answer. And that's like a whole separate stage. A lot of this data is not
available publicly. It is internal to open AI. And it's much harder to replicate this stage.
And so that's roughly what would give you a chat GPT. And nano GPT focuses on the pre-training
stage. Okay, and that's everything that I wanted to cover today. So we trained to summarize a
decoder only transformer following this famous paper attention is all you need from 2017.
And so that's basically a GPT. We trained it on a tiny Shakespeare and got sensible results.
All of the training code is roughly 200 lines of code. I will be releasing this code base. So
also it comes with all the Git log commits along the way as we built it up.
In addition to this code, I'm going to release the notebook, of course, the Google collab.
And I hope that gave you a sense for how you can train these models, like say GPT-3,
that will be architecturally basically identical to what we have. But they are somewhere between
10,000 and 1 million times bigger, depending on how you count. And so that's all I have for now.
We did not talk about any of the fine-tuning stages that would typically go on top of this.
So if you're interested in something that's not just language modeling, but you actually want to,
you know, say, perform tasks, or you want them to be aligned in a specific way, or you want
to detect sentiment or anything like that, basically anytime you don't want something that's just a
document completer, you have to complete further stages of fine-tuning, which we did not cover.
And that could be simple supervised fine-tuning, or it can be something more fancy like we see in
chat GPT, where we actually train a reward model and then do rounds of PPO to align it with
their respective reward model. So there's a lot more that can be done on top of it.
I think for now we're starting to get to about two hours mark, so I'm going to kind of finish here.
I hope you enjoyed the lecture, and yeah, go forth and transform. See you later.